. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
WELCOME TO THE MARCH 24TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG PRESENT MR.
PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA SALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE ROMITA
SALONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LEARNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL.
>> ON BEHALF OF THIS BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETING EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE
THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
>> YES, MR. PRESIDENT. THE CLERK'S OFFICE IS
IN RECEIPT OF A MEMO REQUESTING EXCUSAL TODAY FROM TODAY'S
BOARD MEETING FROM SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER.
NUMBER ONE AND TO THOSE OF YOU WHO HAVE JOINED US IN THE
PUBLIC GALLERY, THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES YOU TO ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON IN THE
BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND FLOOR
IN CITY HALL. AND WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GEO
VTV FOR ORG OR WATCH THE PROCEEDING ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S
CHANNEL 26. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT
YOU'D LIKE TO PROVIDE IN WRITING YOU CAN SEND AN
EMAIL TO TO BOSSI AT AS F KORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE IF
YOU JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS HERE'S THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOODLATTE
PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102 IF
YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION AND FOR A FUTURE
MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO
REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT
LEAST TO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER MADE BY CHAN SECONDED BY DORSEY.
MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION. SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED.
>> AND THEN LET'S GO. MADAM CLERK TO UNFINISHED
BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM ONE. >> ITEM ONE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE POLICE CODE TO REQUIRE THAT
INDIVIDUALS WHO NOTARIZE OR ASSIST PEOPLE IN COMPLETING
IMMIGRATION DOCUMENTS OFFER A DOCUMENT PREPARED BY THE CITY
THAT IDENTIFIES FREE OR LOW COST IMMIGRATION LEGAL SERVICES
PROVIDERS AND CONSULATES AND TO AUTHORIZE THE HUMAN RIGHTS
COMMISSION TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WHO WISH TO FILE A COMPLAINT WITH THE STATE
LICENSING OR ENFORCEMENT ENTITY AGAINST A NOTARY OR IMMIGRATION
CONSULTANT WHO ALLEGEDLY VIOLATED LEGAL REQUIREMENTS
APPLICABLE TO THOSE ACTIVITIES. >> CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEM ONE? >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I. SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR ONE WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I .
>> THEIR ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS TWO AND THREE
TOGETHER ITEMS TWO AND THREE ARE TWO ORDINANCES THAT AMEND
THE PLANNING CODE AND THE ZONING MAP FOR VARIOUS
PROPERTIES. >> ITEM TWO AMENDS THE PLANNING
CODE AND THE ZONING MAP TO ESTABLISH THE 2245 POST STREET
SPECIAL USE DISTRICT. ITEM THREE THIS ORDINANCE RE
ADOPTS THE FORMER PLANNING CODE SECTION AND ZONING MAP
DESIGNATIONS TO CREATE THE MISSION AND NINTH STREET
SPECIAL USE DISTRICT AT 1270 MISSION STREET LOCATED IN THE
AREA GENERALLY BOUNDED BY MISSION STREET ON THE SOUTH
LASKY STREET ON THE EAST. ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER
30 701 LOT NUMBERS 2223 AND 24 ON THE WEST AND ASSESSOR'S
PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER 30 701 LOT NUMBER 66 ON THE NORTH.
TO CHANGE THE HEIGHT LIMIT ON ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER
30 701 LOT NUMBERS 20 AND 21 FOR PROJECTS THAT COMPLY WITH
THE REQUIREMENTS OF THE ASSUMED FROM 120 X TO 200 X.
AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS FOR BOTH ITEMS LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER FOUR ITEM FOUR IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE TO ENHANCE AND MODIFY THE SIDEWALK FLOWER
STAND PERMIT PROGRAM TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
INCLUDE UPDATES AND CLARIFYING THE APPLICABLE FEES TO AMEND
THE POLICE CODE TO AUTHORIZE PUBLIC WORKS TO IMPOSE, ASSESS
AND COLLECT ADMINISTRATIVE PENALTIES.
>> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO ORDER THE
CONDITIONAL VACATION OF THE DESIGNATION OF PORTIONS OF
CHRISTMAS TREE POINT ROAD AND THE EASTERN ALIGNMENT OF
TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AS PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY FOR ROADWAY
AND SIDEWALK PURPOSES AND TO ORDER THE RE DESIGNATION OF
EASTERN TWIN PEAKS BOULEVARD AS PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY FOR
RECREATION AND PARK PURPOSES TO FACILITATE THE DEVELOPMENT OF
THE TWIN PEAKS PROMENADE PROJECT AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS
IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO MODIFY
THE FOLLOWING FIVE DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATIONS.
THE NUMBER ONE JESSIE ALLEY'S DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO
INCLUDE THE NORTHERN SIDE OF MISSION STREET TO EXCLUDE THE
PUBLIC STREET PORTION OF MISSION STREET BETWEEN JESSIE
STREET EAST AND JESSIE STREET WEST.
AND TO MAKE CLARIFYING REVISIONS TO THE MISSION THE
MINOR ALLEY DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE MINISTRY
BETWEEN SHAH ALLEY AND NEW MONTGOMERY STREET THREE THE
NATOMA DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE NATOMA
STREET BETWEEN NEW MONTGOMERY STREET AND ONE 80FT NORTHEAST
OF SECOND STREET. FOR THE FOURTH ITEM HERE THE
SECOND STREET DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION TO INCLUDE
GENESEE STREET BETWEEN SECOND STREET AND NEW MONTGOMERY
STREET AND FIVE THE YERBA BUENA LANE DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION
LOCATION TO INCLUDE THE SOUTHERN SIDE OF MARKET STREET
BETWEEN YERBA BUENA LANE AND TO 50FT NORTHEAST OF YERBA BUENA
LANE TO EXCLUDE THE PUBLIC STREET PORTION OF MARKET STREET
AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION ON SAME HOUSE
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS
ORDINANCE APPROVES THE POLICE SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY
FOR ELECTRONIC LOCATION TRACKING DEVICES AND MAKES THE
REQUISITE FINDINGS. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND I FIRST WANT TO THANK COLLEAGUES FOR
YOUR SUPPORT AND VOTES TO ALLOW A CONTINUANCE FOR THIS ITEM
WHICH THEN GIVEN THE ME THE OPPORTUNITY TO ASK QUESTIONS TO
OUR POLICE DEPARTMENT ABOUT THE SUPREME COURT'S RULING ON
TRACKING DEVICES AS RELATED TO THE FOURTH AMENDMENT AND THE
INCIDENT AROUND POTENTIAL MISUSE AND ALLEGED MISUSE OF
LOCK EQUIPMENT ALSO KNOWN AS THE AUTOMATED LICENSE PLATE
READER AND I HAVE RECEIVED ANSWERS FROM THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT AND I WOULD LIKE FOR THEM TO BE PRESENTING YOU THE
ANSWER THAT WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM BASED ON THE LETTER.
COLLEAGUES, IT IS OUR COLLECTIVE RESPONSIBILITY TO
ENSURE THAT THE CITY BALANCES SAFETY AND PRIVACY WHEN WE'RE
DEPLOYING TECHNOLOGY. SO WHEN WE APPROVE THESE
POLICIES WE INDEED NEED TO MAKE SURE THE DEPARTMENTS CAN FOLLOW
THROUGH WITH THE SAFEGUARDS NECESSARY TO CREATE THAT
BALANCE AS IT RELATED TO THE CASE MENTIONED IN THE MEDIA
WHERE FLOCK EQUIPMENT'S WAS MISUSED BY OUR ALLEGEDLY BY OUR
POLICE DEPARTMENT AND I THANK THE POLICE DEPARTMENT PROVIDING
THE LETTER RESPONDING TO THAT REQUEST.
IN ANSWERING A QUESTION. SO WITH THAT PRESIDENT MENDOZA
AND I WOULD LIKE TO CALL ON THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO WALK US
THROUGH AND MY APOLOGIES I DON'T THINK THE LETTER PROVIDED
BY THE POLICE DEPARTMENT I HAD THE CHANCE TO PUT ON LIKE TO
SAY TO FILE BUT I HAVE JUST SENT IT TO THE CLERK TO FOR US
TO DO SO. BUT I JUST WOULD LIKE FOR THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT TO WALK US THROUGH THE LETTER PROVIDED TO
MY OFFICE AND SO THAT WE CAN HAVE THAT ON THE RECORD.
WELCOME. THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN SUPERVISOR CHAN SUPERVISOR CHAN THANKS FOR
YOUR QUESTIONS AND THE OPPORTUNITY TO RESPOND TO THEM.
I'LL JUST AS YOU REQUESTED WALK THROUGH THE RESPONSE FROM THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT ON YOUR QUESTIONS ESPECIALLY REGARDING
THE FOURTH AMENDMENT IN 2012. >> THE FOURTH AMENDMENT OR THE
SUPREME COURT DID HOLD THAT A GPS TRACKING DEVICE A TRACKING
DEVICE LIKE STAR CHASE WHICH IS IN QUESTION HERE IS IN FACT A
SEARCH. SO THAT'S NOT DISPUTED.
A SEARCH GENERALLY REQUIRES A WARRANT UNLESS A WARRANT
EXCEPTION APPLIES. ONE SUCH EXCEPTION THAT HAS
LONG BEEN RECOGNIZED ARE EXIGENT CIRCUMSTANCES WHERE
THERE'S AN IMMEDIATE NEED FOR OFFICERS TO PROTECT PUBLIC
SAFETY OR APPREHEND A FLEEING SUSPECT.
ACCORDINGLY, THE POLICE DEPARTMENT'S ELECTRONIC
LOCATION TRACKING DEVICE POLICY WHICH IS BEFORE YOU TODAY DOES
LIMIT THE USE OF THESE ELECTRONIC LOCATION TRACKING
DEVICES TO WARRANTS OR WARRANT EXCEPTIONS INCLUDING EXIGENT
CIRCUMSTANCES. AS YOU KNOW, THE PURPOSE OF
STAR CHASE SPECIFICALLY IS SHORT TERM TRACKING FOR
CONTEMPORANEOUS APPREHENSION ALLOWING OFFICERS TO DISENGAGE
FROM VEHICLE PURSUITS WHILE MAINTAINING THE ABILITY TO
LOCATE A FLEEING VEHICLE OR SUSPECT.
THIS DOES REDUCE THE OPPORTUNITY OR CHANCE OF
COLLISION AND INJURIES TO OTHER OFFICERS, SUSPECTS OR MEMBERS
OF THE PUBLIC. >> SINCE YOU ASKED ABOUT FLOC
THE USE OF THE DEPARTMENT'S AUTOMATED LICENSE PLATE READERS
COURTS HAVE GENERALLY HELD THAT THERE IS NO REASONABLE
EXPECTATION OF PRIVACY FOR A LICENSE PLATE ON A PUBLIC
ROADWAY AS LICENSE PLATES ARE MEANT TO BE VISIBLE TO ANYONE.
>> AS SUCH THE FLOC HPR SYSTEM DOES CAPTURE IMAGES OF A
VEHICLE AND A LICENSE PLATE IN PUBLIC VIEW.
AGAIN, COURTS HAVE ANALOGIZED THE USE OF THESE SYSTEMS TO AN
OFFICER ON THE STREET VIEWING A LICENSE PLATE AND VEHICLE
DESCRIPTION. >> WITH ALL THAT SAID, THE
DEPARTMENT DEFINITELY RECOGNIZES THAT THERE ARE CIVIL
LIBERTIES CONSIDERATIONS WITH THE USE OF THESE TECHNOLOGIES
AND ALL SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGIES.
SO CONSISTENT WITH 19 B BOTH FLOC LPR TECHNOLOGY AS WELL AS
THE ELECTRONIC LOCATION TRACKING DEVICE POLICY BEFORE
YOU TODAY ARE GOVERNED BY SAFEGUARDS THAT DEFINE
AUTHORIZED AND PROHIBITED USES .
THEY RESTRICT ACCESS TO NECESSARY USERS.
THEY MAINTAIN AUDIT LOGS OF SEARCH QUERIES AND THEY KEEP
DATA SECURE. THE POLICIES ALL GO THROUGH AN
OVERSIGHT PROCESS THROUGH THE COMMITTEE ON INFORMATION
TECHNOLOGY AND ITS SUBCOMMITTEE PRIVACY SURVEILLANCE ADVISORY
BOARD. I CAN'T SPEAK FOR THESE
COMMITTEES BUT I CAN TELL FROM GOING THROUGH THESE PROCESSES
THAT THEY TAKE THEIR OVERSIGHT RESPONSIBILITY VERY SERIOUSLY
AND THEY WEIGH THE BENEFITS TO THE TO PUBLIC SAFETY AGAINST
CERTAIN CIVIL LIBERTIES CONSIDERATIONS.
>> YOU MENTIONED AN INCIDENT THAT WAS REPORTED PUBLICLY
ABOUT ONE MEMBER OF THE POLICE DEPARTMENT WHO QUERIED THE FLOC
SYSTEM IN A CONFLICT OF INTEREST.
>> I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO RECOGNIZE HERE THAT THE
SAFEGUARDS IN PLACE FOR THESE TECHNOLOGIES ARE WHAT IN FACT
THE DEPARTMENT USED TO INVESTIGATE THE ALLEGATION OF
MISUSE. THAT'S PRECISELY WHAT THEY'RE
THERE FOR AND FOR THIS MATTER SPECIFICALLY IT WAS FULLY
INVESTIGATED BY THE DEPARTMENT'S INTERNAL AFFAIRS
DIVISION. AND LIKE I MENTIONED, THE
POLICY ISSUE INVOLVED WAS A CONFLICT OF INTEREST.
>> SO TO SUMMARIZE ALL OF THAT, THESE TECHNOLOGIES STARCHES,
ELECTRONIC LOCATION TRACKING DEVICES, HPR ARE USED FOR
LIMITED PUBLIC SAFETY PURPOSES SUBJECT TO THE FOURTH AMENDMENT
OR EXCEPTIONS INCLUDING EXIGENT CIRCUMSTANCES WITH POLICY
SAFEGUARDS AND OVERSIGHT PROCESSES TO ENSURE
ACCOUNTABILITY. HAPPY TO ANSWER ANY FOLLOW UP
QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. PRESENT AMANDA MENG
AND COLLEAGUES AND THANK YOU SO MUCH TO THE POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND I ALSO APPRECIATE THE LETTER OUR RECORD HAS ANSWER MY
QUESTION AND I ABSOLUTELY LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING
MONITORING THIS PROTOCOLS AND ENSURING THAT WE DO
SAFEGUARD OUR DATA ON AN ONGOING BASIS.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE RULES COMMITTEE AS WELL AS QUITE TO
CONTINUE TO COMB THROUGH THE SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY REPORT
ON AN ANNUAL BASIS TO ENSURE AGAIN THE DEPARTMENT ABIDE BY
THE POLICY. AND FOR THAT I WILL BE
IN SUPPORT OF TODAY IN THIS LEGISLATION.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND I DO
WANT TO THANK THE POLICE DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR DUE
DILIGENCE AND FOR ALL THE WORK THAT THEY PUT INTO THIS.
I JUST WANT TO THANK OF COURSE MY COLLEAGUES ON THE RULES
COMMITTEE. AS YOU KNOW, WE FORWARDED THIS
WITH OUR RECOMMENDATION BECAUSE OF THE CONCERN.
SO I WANT TO APPRECIATE THE REQUEST FOR THE CONTINUANCE.
>> ONE THING WE KNOW FOR SURE WITH TECHNOLOGY PARTICULARLY
THIS TECHNOLOGY WE'VE ALREADY SEEN MISTAKES HAPPEN HERE
IN THE CITY AND IT ONLY TAKES ONE MISTAKE TO BE A PROBLEM
AND TO BE IN VIOLATION OF SOMEBODY ELSE'S RIGHTS.
I MEAN EVEN AS WE ARE HAVING THIS CONVERSATION ABOUT THIS
TECHNOLOGY, WE HAVE OTHER MUNICIPALITIES THAT ARE
ACTUALLY PAUSING THE USAGE OF THIS TECHNOLOGY BECAUSE THEY'VE
HAD CONCERNS AND THEY'VE HAD PROBLEMS AND IN SOME CASE
ENDING THEIR RELATIONSHIP DUE TO PRIVACY CONCERNS, DUE TO
DATA CONCERNS DUE TO THE ATTACKS AND THE EFFECTS THAT
THIS COULD HAVE ON OUR IMMIGRANT POPULATIONS.
SO FROM MY STANDPOINT IT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE TO SUPPORT
THESE DEVICES IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS WITH OTHER CITIES
THAT USE THEM CURRENTLY AND THEY'RE NOT TRUSTING THIS
TECHNOLOGY. I THINK AT THE VERY LEAST WE
SHOULD PUT A PAUSE ON TECHNOLOGY LIKE THIS AND LEARN
SOME MORE. WITHOUT PROPER SAFEGUARDS THIS
TECHNOLOGY CAN BE MISUSED AND WE KNOW IS
DISPROPORTIONATELY GOING TO AFFECT PEOPLE OF COLOR
AND ERODE TRUST BETWEEN COMMUNITY AND LAW ENFORCEMENT.
IN ADDITION, ONE DAY THIS TECHNOLOGY MIGHT TAKE AWAY SOME
OF OUR POLICE OFFICER JOBS, SOME OF OUR JOBS THAT ARE
AVAILABLE TO THE POLICE DEPARTMENT BECAUSE OF THIS
TECHNOLOGY. SO I HOPE PEOPLE ALSO
UNDERSTAND THE LABOR IMPACTS WITH TECHNOLOGY LIKE THIS EVEN
IN CITIES LIKE VIRGINIA, EVEN IN STATES LIKE VIRGINIA
AND CITIES LIKE NORFOLK, THEY'RE REVISITING WHETHER OR
NOT TO USE THIS TECHNOLOGY THEY FOUND THAT IS TRACKING PEOPLE
ON THEIR WAY TO WORK IS TRACKING PEOPLE ON THEIR WAY TO
SCHOOL AND IS JUST TRACKING PEOPLE GOING ON WITH THEIR
DAILY BUSINESS AND FROM MY STANDPOINT I THINK THAT IS A
VIOLATION OF PEOPLE'S PRIVACY REGARDLESS OF HOW VISIBLE A
LICENSE PLATE IS TO EVERYONE. PEOPLE ARE BEING SURVEILLED
WHEN THEY SHOULDN'T BE. SO I TRULY FEEL THAT SAFETY
CANNOT COME AT THE EXPENSE OF OUR FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS.
WE CANNOT ACCEPT THE TRADEOFF WHEN SORT OF SURVEILLANCE
ERODES THE VERY FREEDOMS THAT ALL OF US HERE ARE SWORN TO
PROTECT. SO MY THOUGHTS ON PAUSING ARE
NOT ABOUT REJECTING TECHNOLOGY OUTRIGHT BUT IT IS ABOUT
GETTING IT RIGHT. IT'S ABOUT ENSURING WE HAVE
STRICT GUARDRAILS AND INPUT FROM COMMUNITY MOVING FORWARD
AND I THINK OUR POPULATION IN SAN FRANCISCO DESERVES TO
FEEL SAFE AND FREE BUT WE HAVE TO BE ABLE TO PROTECT PROTECT
FOLKS AND ALSO HONOR THEIR PRIVATE RIGHTS.
SO I CAN'T SUPPORT THIS THIS TECHNOLOGY AT THIS TIME AND I
WISH THAT WE WOULDN'T MOVE FORWARD WITH THIS BECAUSE OF
THE POSSIBLE IMPACTS ON CERTAIN COMMUNITIES.
BUT IF THIS PASSES HERE WHICH I'M PRETTY SURE WILL TODAY WE
NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE KEEPING A CLOSE EYE ON HOW DID
THAT IS BEING STORED, HOW IS BEING USED, WHO IT'S AFFECTING
BECAUSE THIS IS GOING TO HAVE SOME NEGATIVE CONSEQUENCES FOR
SURE. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MADAM
CHAIR. THANK YOU, CHAIR WALTON.
SUPERVISOR WONG COLLEAGUES, I WANT TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF
THIS ORDINANCE APPROVING A SURPRISE SURVEILLANCE
TECHNOLOGY POLICY FOR ELECTRONIC LOCATION TRACKING
DEVICES. THIS IS A PUBLIC SAFETY TOOL
THAT CAN HELP US REDUCE DANGEROUS CAR CHASES AND THE
VERY HARMS THAT COME WITH THEM CRASHES, INJURIES, DEATHS
AND PROPERTY DAMAGE. THE POLICY IS EXPLICIT THAT ONE
OF THE CORE PURPOSES OF THIS TECHNOLOGY IS TO PROVIDE A
VEHICLE PURSUIT MITIGATION OPTION SO OFFICERS CAN
DISENGAGE FROM A HIGH RISK CHASE WHILE STILL MAINTAINING
LOCATION AWARENESS AND SAFELY COORDINATING AN APPREHENSION.
IT ALSO HAS VALUE BEYOND PURSUITS.
THESE DEVICES CAN HELP AS LOCATE SUSPECTS, RECOVER STOLEN
VEHICLES AND STOLEN PROPERTY AND SUPPORT THEFT ABATEMENT
OPERATIONS THAT GIVES LAW ENFORCEMENT A MORE PRECISE
AND LESS DANGEROUS WAY TO RESPOND IN SITUATIONS THAT
MIGHT OTHERWISE LEAD TO PROLONGED PURSUITS OR BROADER
RISKS TO THE PUBLIC. AT THE SAME TIME, I THINK IT IS
IMPORTANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE PRIVACY AND CIVIL LIBERTIES
CONCERNS THAT NATURALLY COME WITH ANY SURVEILLANCE
TECHNOLOGY. THAT IS WHY THE GUARDRAILS HERE
MATTER. THE POLICY LIMITS USE TO DEFINE
LAWFUL SCENARIOS. PROHIBITS USE FOR NON-LAW
ENFORCEMENT PURPOSES. PROHIBITS DISCRIMINATORY OR
HARASSING USE BARS USE RELATED TO ENFORCING BANS ON GENDER
AFFIRMING OR REPRODUCTIVE CARE. LIMITS ACCESS TO AUTHORIZED
PERSONNEL CONNECTED TO CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS.
REQUIRES TRAINING AND PROVIDES FOR OVERSIGHT AND DISCIPLINE IF
THE TECHNOLOGY IS MISUSED. SO FOR ME THIS IS ABOUT
BALANCE. WE SHOULD GIVE LAW ENFORCEMENT
TOOLS THAT CAN HELP PREVENT DANGEROUS PURSUITS AND IMPROVE
APPREHENSION OF SERIOUS OFFENDERS BUT ONLY WITH CLEAR
RESTRICTIONS ACCOUNTABILITY AND PUBLIC OVERSIGHT.
BASED ON THE POLICY BEFORE US. I BELIEVE THOSE SAFEGUARDS ARE
IN PLACE AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS ITEM.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM ON
ITEM SEVEN SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDEL HI
MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING
NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS
AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE HEALTH AND BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO REVISE THE DEFINITION OF A MOBILE FOOD
FACILITY PERMIT TO ADD DEFINITIONS FOR COMPACT MOBILE
FOOD OPERATIONS MOBILE SUPPORT UNIT AND PERMITTED AUXILIARY
CONVEYANCE PERMITS TO REFLECT RECENT AMENDMENTS TO THE
CALIFORNIA RETAIL FOOD CODE AND IN ADDITION TO OTHER
REQUIREMENTS TO REVISE EXISTING DEFINITIONS OF VARIOUS OTHER
TERMS TO REFLECT STATE LAW DEFINITIONS IN SAID CODE AND TO
AMEND THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO INCLUDE A DEFINITION FOR
COMPACT MOBILE FOOD OPERATIONS AND TO EXPAND THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC WORKS STREET VENDING AUTHORITY TO INCLUDE REGULATION
OF COMPACT MOBILE FOOD OPERATIONS AND TO REQUIRE THAT
THE DEPARTMENT CONSULT WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
AND THE FIRE DEPARTMENT WHEN ISSUING RULES AND REGULATIONS
THAT REGULATE STREET VENDORS. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THIS ITEM AN ITEM MADE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE ITEM NINE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 34.36 MILLION
FROM PERMANENT PREMIUM AND COMP TIME SALARIES AND TO
APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 34.36 MILLION TO OVERTIME SALARIES
IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO SUPPORT THE DEPARTMENT'S
PROJECTED INCREASES IN OVERTIME AS REQUIRED PER ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE SECTION 3.17 IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026.
COLLEAGUES, CAN WE TAKE THIS ITEM?
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUT A NUMBER
TEN ITEM TEN THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVE
AUTHORIZE ANIMAL CARE AND CONTROL TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $100,000 GIFT VALUE FROM THE
WILL TO LIVING TRUST IN SUPPORT OF VARIOUS ANIMAL CARE
AND CONTROL OPERATIONAL NEEDS EFFECTIVE SEPTEMBER 30TH, 2025.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 11 AND 12 TOGETHER ITEMS 11
AND 12 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE
DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO EXECUTE SECOND AMENDMENTS TO LEASES OF
TWO ADDRESSES FROM K L W INVESTMENTS LLC ITEM 11 IS FOR
APPROXIMATELY 11,000FT2 OF OFFICE SPACE AT 3119 3125
AND 3127 MISSION STREET TO EXTEND THE TERM BY FOUR YEARS
AND SIX MONTHS MARCH 31ST 2026 FOR A TOTAL TERM JULY 1ST 2015
THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2030 AND TO GRANT A FIVE YEAR OPTION
TO RENEW THE LEASE AT AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF APPROXIMATELY
410,000 FOR CONTINUING USE BY THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY
AND ITEM 12 THIS ITEM EXECUTES THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO A LEASE
OF APPROXIMATELY 39,000FT2 OF OFFICE SPACE AT 3120 MISSION
STREET TO EXTEND THE TERM BY FOUR YEARS AND SIX MONTHS MARCH
31ST 2026 FOR A TOTAL TERM FROM JULY 1ST 2015 THROUGH SEPTEMBER
30TH 2030 AND TO GRANT A FIVE YEAR OPTION TO RENEW THE LEASE
AT AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF 1.2 MILLION FOR CONTINUING USE BY
THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY. >> LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ARE
ADOPTED. >> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK I
THINK WE SHOULD GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER.
YES. THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 IS THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I BELIEVE THAT
FIRST UP TODAY IS DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM PROUD TO
RECOGNIZE AN EXTRAORDINARY LEADER, MENTOR AND FORCE IN OUR
CITY MICHELLE OLIVAS. >> MICHELLE MICHELLE KEEP YOUR
EYES AGO MICHELLE IS A SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE RAISED IN THE
MISSION WHERE SERVICE, CULTURE AND COMMUNITY WEREN'T JUST
VALUES THEY WERE EXPECTATIONS. SHE HAS CARRIED THAT ETHOS
FORWARD IN HER CAREER FOR MORE THAN 30 YEARS WHICH I'M
GUESSING WAS BEGINNING AROUND WHEN SHE WAS 5 OR 6 YEARS OLD
AND SHE HAS DEDICATED HER LIFE TO UPLIFTING YOUNG PEOPLE
AND STRENGTHENING THE NEIGHBORHOODS SHE CALLS HOME.
AS CO FOUNDER OF UNITED PLAYERS AND ITS DIRECTOR OF COMMUNITY
AND FAMILY ENGAGEMENT MICHELLE HAS HELPED TO BUILD SOMETHING
TRULY SPECIAL A BELOVED AND WIDELY RESPECTED
ORGANIZATION THAT SERVES YOUTH AMONG OTHERS BY HOLDING THEM
CLOSE THROUGH MENTORSHIP, ACADEMIC SUPPORT AND LEADERSHIP
DEVELOPMENT UNITED PLAYERS GIVES YOUNG PEOPLE THE TOOLS TO
SEE THEMSELVES NOT AS PRODUCTS OF THEIR ENVIRONMENT BUT AS
AGENTS TO CHANGE WITHIN IT AND FOR SO MANY OF THOSE YOUNG
PEOPLE MR. IS NOT ONLY A LEADER SHE'S AUNTIE MICHELLE A STEADY
PRESENCE, A SOURCE OF LOVE, ACCOUNTABILITY AND BELIEF
DURING THE PANDEMIC WHEN SO MANY OF OUR YOUNG PEOPLE WERE
AT RISK OF FALLING THROUGH THE CRACKS, MISHA AND HER TEAM
STEPPED UP IN EXTRAORDINARY WAYS THROUGH THE SOMA YOUTH
COLLABORATIVE WITH THE WEST WEST BAY.
THEY CREATED SAFE SUPPORTIVE SPACES WHERE STUDENTS COULD
LEARN, CONNECT AND SIMPLY BE KIDS AGAIN.
THEY MADE SURE YOUNG PEOPLE HAD MEALS, MENTORSHIP AND A PLACE
TO BELONG BECAUSE AS MICHELLE REMINDS US, YOU CAN'T LEARN IF
YOU'RE HUNGRY AND YOU CAN'T THRIVE IF YOU DON'T FEEL
CONNECTED. BUT WERE PERHAPS STANDS OUT
MOST PROMINENTLY IS HOW MICHELLE DEFINES COMMUNITY NOT
AS A CONCEPT BUT AS A RESPONSIBILITY.
HER WORK IS ROOTED IN A SIMPLE BUT POWERFUL BELIEF WHICH HAS
LONG SERVED AS UP'S MOTTO AND WHOSE ENDURING TRUTH
RESONATES THROUGHOUT THE SOMA NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> IT TAKES THE HOOD TO SAVE THE HOOD THAT THAT MEANS SO
THAT MEANS SHOWING UP NOT JUST WHEN IT'S EASY BUT ESPECIALLY
WHEN IT'S HARD. IT MEANS MEETING YOUNG PEOPLE
WHERE THEY ARE UNDERSTANDING THEIR EXPERIENCES AND BUILDING
THE KIND OF TRUST THAT ENDURES. IT MEANS CREATING A CULTURE
WHERE CARE, CONNECTION AND COMMUNITY COME FIRST
AND WE'RE ALL YOUNG PEOPLE KNOW THAT THEY ARE SEEN, SUPPORTED
AND VALUED. MEESHA IS ALSO A PROUD MOM OF
TWO AND AS MANY IN THE COMMUNITY WILL TELL YOU A
MOTHER FIGURE TO FAR MORE THAN JUST HER OWN CHILDREN.
SHE TEACHES RESILIENCE, SHE MODEL STRENGTH AND SHE BRINGS A
SPIRIT OF MINDFULNESS AND COMPASSION INTO EVERYTHING
SHE DOES. MR. OLIVAS REPRESENTS THE VERY
BEST OF SAN FRANCISCO. SHE IS A LEADER WHO DOESN'T
JUST TALK ABOUT CHANGE. SHE MAKES IT HAPPEN ONE YOUNG
PERSON AT A TIME, ONE FAMILY AT A TIME, ONE COMMUNITY AT A TIME
AND OUR CITY IS INESTIMABLE BETTER FOR IT MEASURE THANK
YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR DECADES OF
SERVICE, YOUR UNWAVERING COMMITMENT AND FOR THE LOVE YOU
BRING TO THE WORK THAT YOU DO FOR OUR CITY EVERY DAY.
>> CONGRATULATIONS ON THIS RECOGNITION HOLD THAT WE HAVE
WE HAVE OTHER SUPERVISORS WHO WANT TO SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT
YOU SO YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WAIT A FEW MOMENTS.
>> SUPERVISOR OR WALTON TRYING TO REACH YOUR ENDS?
>> NO THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM AND MICHELLE, I JUST WANT TO
SAY ONE THAT OBVIOUSLY EVERYBODY IN THIS ROOM AND MOST
CERTAINLY ME HAVE SO MUCH RESPECT FOR YOU AND YOUR WORK
THAT YOU'VE DONE IN OUR COMMUNITIES.
OUT OF RESPECT FOR MY OTHER COLLEAGUES, THAT'S THE ONLY
REASON YOU'RE NOT AN HONOREE OF MINE AT ANY POINT IN TIME.
BUT THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE NOT JUST IN OF THE MARKET, NOT
JUST IN YOUR COMMUNITY BUT ENTIRE CITY IS REALLY UNMATCHED
AND WE HAVE A LOT OF CHILDREN THAT GO FROM EVERYWHERE I GO TO
YOU AND RECEIVE SERVICES. AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU
FOR YOUR CONTINUED COMMITMENT. I KNOW IT'S A LOT OF WORK
WORKING WITH OUR YOUNG PEOPLE ESPECIALLY THESE DAYS BUT YOU
CONTINUE TO DO IT DAY IN AND DAY OUT.
AND AS SOMEONE WHO USED TO WORK FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN,
YOUTH AND FAMILIES AND JUST KNOW HOW YOU STARTED ALL THE
WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE AND TO SEE THE IMPACT THAT YOU ARE
MAKING NOW IS JUST SOMETHING THAT IS WONDERFUL TO WATCH
AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY CONGRATULATIONS TO YOU.
THIS IS WELL DESERVED AND I LOOK FORWARD TO OF COURSE
SEEING YOU CONTINUE TO DO ALL THE GREAT WORK AND COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD MISHRA IT'S
BEEN AN HONOR TO COLLABORATE WITH YOU OVER THIS LAST YEAR
IN OFFICE. WE CAME TO YOU WITH A PROBLEM
IN THE TENDERLOIN AND YOU CAME TO US WITH A SOLUTION.
YOU SHOWED INGENUITY, CREATIVITY, INNOVATION AND JUST
RESILIENCE TO ADDRESS TAKING YOUR MODEL OF WHAT YOU'VE BEEN
WORKING ON IN SOMA, BAYVIEW AND OTHER PLACES AND BRINGING
IT TO THE TENDERLOIN. SO IT'S BEEN AMAZING TO SEE THE
PROGRAM IN JUST A MONTH GROW ALREADY WITH THE YOUTH VIOLENCE
PREVENTION PROGRAM THAT YOU STARTED IN THE TENDERLOIN.
IT SEEMS LIKE THERE'S MORE AND MORE KIDS SHOWING UP THERE.
THEY WANT A BIGGER SPACE. SO THANK YOU AGAIN FOR
CONTINUING TO MAKE OUR CITY SAFER AND GIVING HOPE TO SO
MANY CHILDREN AND YOUTH THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE ARE IN YOUR DEBT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. HI MISCHA.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR DOING THE COMMENDATION
FOR THIS WONDERFUL WOMAN. IN ADDITION TO ALL THE GREAT
THINGS THAT MY COLLEAGUES HAVE ALREADY TALKED ABOUT, MISCHA IS
A LEGEND IN YOUTH DEVELOPMENT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND YOU KNOW, THIS RECOGNITION IS THAT SHE IS OF COURSE IN THE
PANTHEON OF THE MAMAS OF THE COMMUNITY.
>> THERE ARE LITERALLY HUNDREDS OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND PEOPLE WHO
ARE MAYBE NOT SO YOUNG ANYMORE WHO WOULD NOT HAVE SUCCEEDED
BUT FOR YOUR LOVE ATTENTION, CARE OR THOUGHTFULNESS IN ALL
OF THE THINGS THAT YOU HAVE DONE FOR GENERATIONS OF OUR
YOUTH AT THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE AROUND ANTI-VIOLENCE YOUR
PARTICULAR LOVE FOR THE COMMUNITY IN THE SOUTH MARKET
IN THE CARE THAT YOU HAVE PROVIDED TO THE SUPPORTS THAT
EXIST FOR FAMILIES RAISING KIDS HERE IN THE CITY.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH. IT HAS BEEN AN HONOR TO WATCH
YOU AND YOUR CAREER ALL THESE YEARS AND I'M SO HAPPY THAT
WE'RE HONORING YOU. >> NISHA WE COULD GO ON FOR
ANOTHER 20 MINUTES AS WE WORKED OUR WAY THROUGH EACH OF THE
SUPERVISORS SAYING NICE THINGS ABOUT UNITED PLAYERS AND ABOUT
YOUR WORK BUT I THINK WE'LL LET YOU SPEAK NOW.
>> THANK YOU BECAUSE I'M LITERALLY CRAWLING OUT OF MY
SKIN. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. THANK YOU SUPERVISORS.
I REALLY WANTED TO SAY NO WHEN DOMINGO REACHED OUT AND ASKED
ME BUT I TOOK IT. IT HAS TRULY BEEN MY HONOR
AND PLEASURE TO SERVE SAN FRANCISCO TO SERVE ITS YOUNG
PEOPLE. I AM A BORN AND RAISED CITY KID
AND SO I DID THAT TODAY. >> FOR THOSE OF US WHO ARE HERE
WHO WILL BE HERE, I HAVE FOUR KIDS, TWO GRANDKIDS AND IT HAS
BEEN MY YOU KNOW, JUST HONOR AND PRIVILEGE TO BE ABLE TO
SERVE SAN FRANCISCO AND ITS YOUNG PEOPLE.
>> I DIDN'T HAVE COMMENTS PLANNED BECAUSE I WAS CRAWLING
OUT OF MY SKIN. >> BUT I WANTED TO ASK MAY YOU
BE WITH MY FAMILY TO STAND UP? I ALSO I ALSO COULD NOT SAY NO
BECAUSE OF THEM. >> THIS FAMILY IS A FORCE.
WHAT WE HAVE CREATED IS BEAUTIFUL AND MAGICAL AND A LOT
OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE GRACED THESE SEATS MANY, MANY YEARS PASSED
DIDN'T THINK WE COULD DO IT. BUT WE HAVE AND WE HAVE
CONTINUED TO BECAUSE ALL THINGS ARE POSSIBLE IN COMMUNITY WITH
GOD, WITH LOVE. >> YOU KNOW, WE KNOW THAT TIMES
ARE HARD AND ONLY GETTING HARDER BUT IT IS THESE PEOPLE
THAT MAKE SAN FRANCISCO SPECIAL.
IT IS THESE PEOPLE THAT KEEP SAN FRANCISCO ALIVE.
IT IS THESE PEOPLE THAT KEEP SAN FRANCISCO GROWING AND OF
COURSE LIKE CHERISE DORSEY IS AMAZING AND A FORCE AND I'M
HONORED TO BE LIKE IN THE SAME RECOGNITION WITH HER.
BUT THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. I DON'T FEEL LIKE I WORK
BECAUSE I GIVE LOVE AND I RECEIVE LOVE AND YOU KNOW HARD
TIMES COME AND GO. WE BURY CHILDREN SOMETIMES WE
BURY CHILDREN AND WE ALSO CELEBRATE THEIR GRADUATIONS.
WE CELEBRATE THEIR CHILDREN, THEIR MARRIAGES, THEIR TRAVEL.
AND SO THANK YOU AGAIN, SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR SELECTING
ME EVEN THOUGH I WAS VERY RELUCTANT.
AND THANK YOU SAN FRANCISCO. I FREAKING LOVE THIS PLACE.
>> I CAN'T IMAGINE BEING ANYWHERE ELSE.
>> OH YOU KNOW YOU GO WITH THEM
. OH, OKAY.
UP NEXT FROM DISTRICT SEVEN SUPER VISOR MELGAR THANK YOU,
MR. PRESIDENT. >> TODAY I AM SO EXCITED TO
HONOR A DAUGHTER OF DISTRICT SEVEN OUR OWN BRITT ALEXANDRIA
BENTON. >> WILL YOU PLEASE COME UP?
>> SO BRITT GREW UP IN INGLESIDE TERRACES.
SHE ATTENDED PRESCHOOL AT SAN FRANCISCO STATE KINDERGARTEN
AND FIRST GRADE AT COMMODORE SLOAT ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, WHICH
IS OUR, YOU KNOW, LOCAL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL.
>> SHE ATTENDED LINCOLN HIGH SCHOOL AND WENT ON TO WORK AT
SUNSET YOUTH SERVICES BRIDGE JOURNEY AS SOMEONE BORN
AND RAISED IN DISTRICT SEVEN CONTINUES TO THIS DAY TO LIVE
IN DISTRICTS OF IT AND WORK IN DISTRICT SEVEN, SHE
CURRENTLY SERVES OF COURSE AS WE ALL KNOW AS A GOVERNMENT
AFFAIRS COORDINATOR AT THE CALIFORNIA ACADEMY OF SCIENCE
AS AND I KNOW THERE'S MANY FOLKS HERE IN THE AUDIENCE FROM
THE ACADEMY YAY ACADEMY. SHE HAS WORKED IN THAT CAPACITY
TO BRING ACCESS AND EXPLORATION TO OUR COMMUNITIES AND TO
BRIDGE THE WORLD OF SCIENCE WITH THE WORLD OF CIVICS.
THROUGHOUT HER WORK AT THE ACADEMY, BRITT HAS CONNECTED
COMMUNITIES TO LEARNING ABOUT THE NATURAL WORLD IN OPEN
COMMUNICATION AND RESOURCE CHANNELS FOR YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES TO APPRECIATE THE NATURAL WORLD AND TO BUILD THE
EFFORTS OF SUSTAINABILITY, CONSERVATION.
AND SHE IS HELPING BUILD A NEW GENERATION OF CALIFORNIA
STEWARDS FIGHTING CLIMATE CHANGE IN A MORE SUSTAINABLE
FUTURE FOR OUR PLANET. THROUGH TWISTS AND TURNS IN HER
CAREERS, BRITT HAS DEMONSTRATED UNMATCHED RESILIENCE
ADAPTABILITY AND A PERSONABLE CHARACTER BECAUSE WE ALL LOVE
HER IS I KNOW HER TO BE THAT PERSON WITH A SMILE FROM THE
ACADEMY SHE HAS ALWAYS ENTERED A ROOM AND HEARD A CONVERSATION
AND ENTERED A SITUATION WITH GRACE AND KINDNESS MAKING HER
AN OUTSTANDING PUBLIC SERVICE LEADER.
EVEN ON THE DARK DAYS WE HAVE RECENTLY EXPERIENCE WITH A
PASSING OF CLYDE THE ALLIGATOR BRITT HAS ALWAYS MAINTAINED
THAT CHARM, THAT WARMTH THAT OPTIM IS AN UNWAVERING WORK
ETHIC. >> WE ARE SO GRATEFUL FOR
BRITT'S INFLUENCE AND HER MANY CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I AM SO HONORED TO COMMEND
HER AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING TODAY.
>> WELCOME BRITT. >> I AM AT A LOSS FOR WHY IT'S
BECAUSE I DIDN'T KNOW I DID ALL OF THAT BUT I KNOW SOME OF IT
FIRST AND FOREMOST I WOULD LIKE TO THANK THE BOARD AND THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR MARTIN MELGAR FOR HONORING ME.
>> I WAS VERY SHOCKED TO HEAR ABOUT THIS BECAUSE I SAID
REALLY OVER WHO ME? >> BUT I FIRST AND FOREMOST I
JUST WANT TO THANK MY VILLAGE BECAUSE YOU KNOW, IT TAKES ONE
I WANT TO THANK MY PARENTS FOR LOVING ME AND GIVING ME THEIR
ALL ALONG WITH MY SIBLINGS ALSO I DON'T KNOW WOW I SHOULD HAVE
HAVE MORE TALKING POINTS BUT THIS IS A GOOD TIME TO SHOUT
OUT JUST ALL THE WOMEN IN MY LIFE FROM AIMEE TO LILA, MY
SISTERS DAWN, VICKI I ALSO WANT TO GIVE IKHWAN THE SHOUT OUT
BECAUSE HE KNOWS ME AND SAID HEY YOU KNOW WHAT?
>> YOU SHOULD GET INTO LEADERSHIP COMING TO THIS ROLE
RIGHT CLICK AND SEE WHAT HAPPENS AND THIS IS WHAT
HAPPENED ALSO JUST ONE LAST THING I DO WANT TO GIVE A SHOUT
OUT TO MY MOTHER MY MOTHER NAN WHEN SHE WAS A FORCE TO BE
RECKONED WITH SHE WAS AD5 HER BOTH MY PARENTS WERE D FIVE BAR
OWNERS I'M JUST GOING TO SAY THAT AND THEY JUST TAUGHT ME I
DON'T KNOW MY MOM SHE SHE IF IT WAS NOT FOR HER I WOULD TELL
YOU THAT SHE SHE TAUGHT ME THE IMPORTANCE OF WOMANHOOD
COMMUNITY BEING WHO YOU ARE AND LOVING THE SKIN THAT YOU'RE
IN. SHE ALSO TAUGHT ME ABOUT
INTEGRITY AND ORDER AND LOVE AND MOST IMPORTANTLY FAMILY
AND COMMUNITY OPINION. >> AND THAT'S ALL I HAVE TO
SAY. THANK YOU EVERYBODY.
>> THANK YOU FOR HONORING ME. THANK YOU EVERYBODY FOR THAT
STAND UP RIGHT NOW. THANK YOU.
OUT DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
MADAM COLLEAGUES IT IS MY HONOR TO RISE TODAY TO RECOGNIZE
AND CELEBRATE AN EXTRAORDINARY LEADER A TIRELESS ADVOCATE
AND A TRUE CHAMPION FOR OUR YOUNG PEOPLE.
CHERISE DORSEY SMITH SINCE 2007 SERIES HAS DEDICATED HER CAREER
TO THE SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN, YOUTH AND THEIR
FAMILIES STEADILY RISING THROUGH THE RANKS WITH PURPOSE,
INTEGRITY AND AN UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO YOUTH
DEVELOPMENT. TODAY AS EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR SHE
BRINGS NOT ONLY DEEP INSTITUTIONAL KNOWLEDGE BUT I
LIVED PASSION FOR ENSURING EVERY YOUNG PERSON IN OUR CITY
HAS AN OPPORTUNITY TO THRIVE. >> BORN AND RAISED IN SOUTHERN
CALIFORNIA, CERISE OFTEN SAYS SHE IS FROM THE BAY BY WAY OF
L.A. A REFLECTION OF THE LIFE SHE HAS BUILT HERE IN THE BAY
AREA AS FIRST IN HER FAMILY TO ATTEND COLLEGE AT UC SANTA
CRUZ. AND AS THE ELDEST OF FOUR.
SHE UNDERSTOOD EARLY ON THAT CARING FOR AND UPLIFTING OTHERS
WAS NOT JUST A RESPONSIBILITY BUT HER CALLING.
WHICH SHE HAS DESCRIBED AS HER DESIGN STATION HAS GUIDED HER
EVERY STEP OF THE WAY FROM HER EARLY DAYS IN STUDENT ADVOCACY
TO A TRANSFORMATIVE EXPERIENCE AS AN AMERICORPS MEMBER AT
GLORIA R DAVIS MIDDLE SCHOOL. SHERRIE SAW FIRSTHAND THE
INEQUITIES FACING OUR YOUTH AND MADE THE DECISION TO BE A
PART OF THE SOLUTION. >> SHE HAS NEVER LOOKED BACK.
>> THROUGHOUT HER CAREER FROM SAN FRANCISCO SCHOOL VOLUNTEERS
TO THE URBAN SERVICES YMCA AND ULTIMATELY D.C. WIFE
CHERISE HAS WORKED TO BRIDGE THE GAP BETWEEN COMMUNITY
AND GOVERNMENT. SHE HAS LED WITH VISION
CREATING PROGRAMS LIKE DC LIFE UNIVERSITY TO STRENGTHEN
COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS AND EXPANDING OPPORTUNITIES FOR
YOUTH WITH DISABILITIES THROUGH ROSELYN WIDE INCLUSION
COLLABORATIVE AND OVERSEEING CRITICAL INVESTMENTS THAT
DIRECTLY IMPACT THE LIVES OF YOUNG PEOPLE.
AND FAMILIES ACROSS OUR CITY. >> HER LEADERSHIP HAS BEEN
ESPECIALLY IMPACTFUL IN TIMES OF CRISIS DURING THE COVID 19
PANDEMIC. CHERISE LED THE COMMUNITY HUBS
INITIATIVE CREATING SAFE SUPPORTING SPACES FOR STUDENTS
AND FAMILIES WHEN THEY NEEDED IT MOST.
>> FOR THIS WORK SHE WAS RIGHTFULLY RECOGNIZED WITH THE
2022 SAN FRANCISCO GOOD GOVERNMENT AWARD.
>> AND HER IMPACT CONTINUES. FROM LAUNCHING INITIATIVES LIKE
THE LITERACY AND MATH SCHOOL PILOT SUMMER TOGETHER AND THE
STUDENT SUCCESS FUND TO SUCCESSFULLY LEADING A START
$150 MILLION INVESTMENT INTO COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS.
CHERISE HAS DEMONSTRATED WHAT IT MEANS TO LEAD WITH BOTH
HEART AND STRATEGY. BUT BEYOND TITLES
AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS WE'RE TRULY SET.
CHERISE IN PART IS HER UNWAVERING BELIEF IN SUPPORTING
THE WHOLE CHILD. >> MEETING YOUNG PEOPLE WHERE
THEY ARE AND ENSURING THEY ARE SURROUNDED BY THE RESOURCES,
CARE AND OPPORTUNITIES THEY DESERVE.
>> AND I'M SO HAPPY TO SAY THAT I'M EXCITED TO HAVE WORKED WITH
YOU FOR TWO PLUS YEARS AT DC LIFE AND I KNEW THAT YOU WOULD
BE IN THIS LEADERSHIP POSITION EVEN BACK THEN AND EVEN WHEN I
LEFT DC WHY IF YOU WERE THERE TO GIVE ADVICE AND HELP ME WITH
PROGRAMMATIC EXPERTISE SOME OF WHICH STILL IS BEING INSTITUTE
IT TODAY. >> YOUR WORK HAS TOUCHED
COUNTLESS LIVES ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
YOUR LEADERSHIP HAS STRENGTHENED OUR COMMUNITIES,
UPLIFTED OUR FAMILIES AND CREATED A BRIGHTER FUTURE
FOR OUR YOUTH. SO TODAY WE SAY THANK YOU.
WE HONOR YOU. WE CELEBRATE YOU.
AND CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR OUTSTANDING SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND THE CHILDREN AND FAMILIES.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR THIS REALLY GREAT COMMENT ATION.
I HAVE HAD THE PLEASURE OF WORKING WITH CHERISE FOR ALMOST
TWO DECADES REALLY SINCE I WAS AT THE JAMESTOWN COMMUNITY
CENTER. AND HAVE ALWAYS APPRECIATED HER
GREAT STRATEGIC MIND BUT ALSO JUST HER CALM EMOTIONAL
STRENGTH BECAUSE NO MATTER HOW BAD THINGS GET.
>> CHERISE ALWAYS HAS A PLAN. >> CHERISE ALWAYS HAS A PLAN
AND CAN BREAK IT DOWN AND EXPLAIN IT TO YOU IN A WAY
THAT YOU'LL UNDERSTAND IT. SO I JUST APPRECIATE YOU
AND ABOVE ALL I APPRECIATE EVERYTHING YOU HAVE DONE FOR
THE YOUNG PEOPLE OF OUR COMMUNITY.
I THINK THAT YOU KNOW, WHEN CRISES HAPPEN WHICH INVARIABLY
THEY DO AND PEOPLE LIKE YOU ARE WHAT SAVES THE DAY AND YOU HAVE
DONE IT OVER AND OVER AGAIN. SO I'M GRATEFUL FOR YOU.
I AM ALSO GRATEFUL THAT YOU HAVE STEPPED UP INTO THIS
LEADERSHIP POSITION THAT WAS NOT YOU KNOW, A GIVEN.
I'M JUST SO GLAD THAT YOU DID. AND I'M LOOKING FORWARD TO MANY
YEARS OF WORKING WITH YOU TO MAKE SURE THAT YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES IN OUR CITY SUCCEED.
SO THANK YOU AGAIN, SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THIS
AND CONGRATULATIONS, SHERIFF. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT MANDO MAN. >> I REMEMBER AS BUDGET
COMMITTEE CHAIR I REMEMBER THAT IT WAS A VERY TOUGH TIME WHEN
NOW SUPERINTENDENT MARIA SU BUT THEN OUR DC Y OF DIRECTOR HAVE
TO TRANSITION AND SUDDENLY SHURI SHOW UP AT THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE DURING SOME SERIOUS TOUGH TIME.
IT WAS JUST WRAPPING UP DC Y I HAVE JUST WRAPPING UP FIVE YEAR
RFP AND GOING INTO A BUDGET DEFICIT AND SUDDENLY THINGS
LANDED ON HER LAP AND I REMEMBER THE FIRST BUDGET
COMMITTEE HEARING THAT CHERISE CAME AND PERCENT AND I REMEMBER
I WENT BACK TO THE OFFICE AND I IMMEDIATELY CALLED MARIA SU
AND I SAID WHO IS THIS CHERISE DORSEY SMITH?
>> SHE IS AWESOME. >> SHE SHE CAME IN NO NONSENSE.
SHE PRESENTED THE BUDGET. SHE DEFENDED THE DECISIONS
AND MAKING SURE THAT YOU KNOW, BE IT THE FIVE YEAR RFP RESULTS
B OF THE APPEAL PROCESS AS WELL AS STUDENT SUCCESS
IMPLEMENTATION. SHE HAD ANSWER TO EVERY
QUESTION THAT I HAD AND SHE WAS FIRM AND SHE WAS ASSERTIVE
AND SHE KNOW SHE KNEW HER THINGS AND I AND THEN YOU KNOW
THEN SUBSEQUENTLY WE MET AGAIN AT THE FREE CITY COLLEGE
OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE. I SHOWED UP AGAIN AND ASKING
SOME REALLY TOUGH QUESTIONS AND CHERISE WAS AGAIN THERE TO
ANSWER EVERY SINGLE ONE OF THEM EVEN THOUGH THEY'RE SUCH A VAST
MAJORITY LIKE DIFFERENT THINGS STUDENTS SAYS FREE CITY OR YOU
KNOW WITH THE RFP WITH D.C. I HAVE LIKE THE ENTIRE FIVE YEAR
WORTH OF GRANTS. IT'S AMAZING THAT YOU KNOW IT
ALL. YOU ANSWER QUESTIONS AT ANY
MOMENT THAT IS THE KIND OF LEADERSHIP CITY DEPARTMENT
NEEDS AND THAT OUR CITY DESERVES ESPECIALLY OUR KIDS
AND OUR YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES.
YOU'RE AMAZING LEADER. I'M SO GLAD THAT SUPERVISOR
WALTON HONORING YOU TODAY YOU MORE THAN DESERVING THE HONOR
THAT YOU'RE BEING RECOGNIZED. YOU ARE TRULY AMAZING AND TRULY
A GREAT LEADER. >> WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR
SERVICE. >> OKAY.
I'LL TRY NOT TO CRY. >> OH, ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WATSON AND ALL THE
SUPERVISORS FOR THIS HONOR. I'M DEEPLY HUMBLED AND TRULY
GRATEFUL. I WANT TO THANK EVERYONE WHO
CAME OUT TODAY. >> OH MY GOD.
IT'S SO MANY PEOPLE AND YOUR PRESENCE MATTERS.
YOUR SUPPORT MATTERS AND I DON'T TAKE ANY OF THAT FOR
GRANTED. OH, I STILL BLAME MY CHILD.
OH, MY GOD. HAVING A DAUGHTER.
>> OH, MY GOODNESS. OH, ALEX, THIS IS ALL YOUR
FAULT, LITTLE GIRL. >> I LOVE YOU AND I KNOW I
STAND ON THE SHOULDERS AND BACKS OF MANY WHO HAVE COME
BEFORE ME SOME WHO ARE IN THIS ROOM TODAY MEESHA I MET HER WAY
BACK IN MY AMERICAN TIME. OH, SHE PROBABLY DIDN'T TELL
YOU? I DON'T KNOW THAT.
>> OH, FOR THAT I AM FOREVER THANKFUL AND IN CONSTANT HONOR
OF WHO YOU ARE AND WHAT YOU ALL DO DAILY WITHOUT THANKS
AND WITHOUT RECOGNITION. >> SO I ACCEPT THIS HONOR ON
YOUR BEHALF AS WELL. >> MOST OF YOU KNOW I'M NOT
SOMEONE WHO SEEKS THE SPOTLIGHT LIKE I DON'T EVEN I'M LIKE WELL
I'M A PEER BECAUSE I DON'T DO THIS WORK FOR THE RECOGNITION.
I DIDN'T START OFF DOING ANY OF THIS FOR THE RECOGNITION I DO
THIS WORK BECAUSE IT'S NECESSARY AND BECAUSE IT NEEDS
TO BE DONE. >> WHEN I FIRST STARTED MY
CAREER I NEVER IMAGINED THAT I WOULD BE STANDING HERE AS THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN
AND THEIR FAMILIES. I MEAN I JOKED ABOUT IT BUT I
NEVER SAT LONG ENOUGH TO ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW, SET MY
SIGHTS ON IT. SO IF YOU WOULD HAVE TOLD ME
THIS IS WHERE I WOULD BE TODAY MARCH 24TH, 2027, I WOULD BEEN
LIKE YOU LIE SO I STAND HERE TODAY NOT JUST HONORED BUT
CLEAR IN MY PURPOSE. I OVERSEE A DEPARTMENT WHOSE
TAGLINE SAYS WE WANT TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO A GREAT PLACE TO
GROW UP AND THAT QUESTION IS WHAT DOES THAT REALLY MEAN FOR
ME IT MEANS COMMITTING TO SERVING THE WHOLE CHILD
INNOCENT IN THEIR ENTIRETY. >> SERVING THE WHOLE CHILD
MEANS UNDERSTANDING THAT A YOUNG PERSON'S POTENTIAL CANNOT
BE SEPARATED FROM THEIR CIRCUMSTANCES.
IT MEANS RECOGNIZING THAT THE ACADEMIC SUCCESS ALONE IS NOT
ENOUGH. A CHILD CANNOT LEARN IF THEY
ARE HUNGRY, THEY CANNOT FOCUS IF THEY'RE NAVIGATING TRAUMA
THEY CANNOT DREAM IF THEY DON'T FEEL SAFE SEEING AND VALUED.
>> IF WE TRULY WANT TO SERVE CHILDREN IN YOUTH AND MAKE SURE
THAT THEY ARE THRIVING, IT TAKES MORE THAN INTENTION.
>> IT TAKES COMMITMENT. IT TAKES MANY PEOPLE EVERYBODY
HERE IN THIS ROOM COMING TOGETHER TO ENSURE THAT YOUNG
PEOPLE HAVE THE RESOURCES, HAVE THE OPPORTUNITIES, THE SUPPORTS
SYSTEMS AND ANY AND EVERYTHING THAT THEY NEED TO SUCCEED.
>> IT REQUIRES MORE THAN WORDS. IT REQUIRES MORE THAN PROGRAMS.
IT REQUIRES ALL OF US SHOWING UP STAYING COMMITTED AND DOING
THE HARD AND CONSISTENT WORK NO MATTER WHAT.
>> THRIVING. THIS DOESN'T HAPPEN BY CHANCE.
IT HAPPENS WHEN WE ARE DELIBERATE, WHEN WE ARE
INTENTIONAL, WHEN WE SET ASIDE ALL THE EGOS AND THE DRAMA
AND WE ARE REALLY HERE FOR CHILDREN, FOR YOUTH AND FOR
THEIR FAMILIES. >> I REMEMBER WRITING MY
COLLEGE ESSAY THAT I DIDN'T WANT TO BE ANOTHER STATISTIC.
I DIDN'T WANT TO BECOME A PART OF THE NARRATIVE SO OFTEN
WRITTEN FOR BLACK GIRLS GROWING UP IN COMPTON, CALIFORNIA, I
ATTENDED A BLACK SCHOOL WHILE LIVING IN A CRIP NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> IF FOLKS KNOW ABOUT THAT, THOSE TWO COLORS DO NOT MATCH
AND IT IS A VERY DANGEROUS BUT I'M THE OLDEST OF THREE AND WAS
RAISED IN A SINGLE PARENT HOUSEHOLD JUST BARELY GETTING
BY AND NOW 33 YEARS LATER YES, I'M DATING MYSELF 33 YEARS
LATER I FIND MYSELF HOLDING ON TO THE SAME CONVICTION BUT WITH
A DEEPER RESPONSIBILITY. I STILL DON'T WANT TO BE A
STATISTIC BUT THIS TIME I DON'T WANT TO BE PART OF A STATISTIC
ABOUT AN ADULT WHO HAS FAILED A CHILD.
>> RITA PIERSON, A PROFESSIONAL EDUCATOR, ONCE SAID EVERY CHILD
DESERVES A CHAMPION AN ADULT WHO WILL NEVER GIVE UP ON THEM,
WHO UNDERSTANDS THE POWER OF CONNECTION AND INSIST THAT THEY
BECOME THE BEST THAT THEY COULD POSSIBLY BE.
SO I CHOOSE AGAIN TO SERVE THE WHOLE CHILD TO BE THAT CHAMPION
BECAUSE WHEN WE CHOOSE THAT WHEN WE'RE FULLY, INTENTIONALLY
AND UNPOLISHED, UNAPOLOGETIC, UNAPOLOGETICALLY WE ARE NOT
JUST CHANGING INDIVIDUAL LIVES .
WE ARE SHAPING THEIR FUTURE OF OUR COMMUNITIES.
WE ARE BUILDING SOMETHING STRONGER, MORE EQUITABLE
AND MORE JUST AND WE REFUSE TO BE ANOTHER STATISTIC.
>> THANK YOU FOR ALL THE WORK THAT YOU ALL ARE DOING AND THAT
YOU WILL BE DOING AND THANK YOU AGAIN FOR THIS HONOR
AND RECOGNITION. >> IT IS NOT SOMETHING THAT I
TAKE LIGHTLY. THANK YOU ALL FOR.
MADAM DIRECTOR, WE'RE GOING TO INVITE YOU INTO THE WELL TO
THANK YOU FOR
NOT
AND NEXT SET UP FROM DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> THANK YOU. WE'LL PRESENT DR. AT WORK
COLLEGE. IT IS MY GREAT HONOR TO
RECOGNIZE DR. DINA ATWOOD TODAY.
>> SHE HAS SPANNED MORE THAN 30 YEARS STRENGTHENING THE LAKE
WHALE COMMUNITY AND DISTRICT 11 BOTH AS A LONG TIME RESIDENT
AND AS THE PRINCIPAL OF SHERIDAN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL.
ALWAYS CENTER AROUND EQUITY. SHE HAS THOUGHTFULLY NURTURED A
COMMUNITY SCHOOL ROOTED IN STRONG PARTNERSHIP WITH
LOCAL COMMUNITY. >> THROUGH THIS COLLABORATION
DR. EVER HAS EXPANDED ACCESS TO ESSENTIAL SUPPORT SUCH AS
TUTORING WEEKENDS, SCHOOL PROGRAMS AND AFTERSCHOOL
ENRICHMENT. THIS HAS MADE A HUGE IMPACT
REDUCING BARRIERS TO LEARN. THIS HAS MADE A HUGE IMPACT
AND ALSO SUPPORTING STUDENTS AND FAMILY BEYOND THE
CLASSROOM. >> THIS PARTNERSHIP HAVE HELPED
CREATE A STABLE, WELCOMING ENVIRONMENT WHERE STUDENTS
STRAY AND FAMILIES FEEL CONNECTED AND SUPPORTED.
DR. EDWAR AND HER EXCEPTIONAL TEAM AS JARED AND ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL HAVE WORKED VERY COLLABORATIVELY TOWARDS
CONTINUED IMPROVEMENT. AS A RESULT, SHERIDAN HAS
BECAME A SAFE SPACE FOR THE COMMUNITY AND SO MUCH SO THAT
FORMER STUDENTS NOW RETURNING TO ENROLL THEIR OWN CHILDREN'S.
IT IS MY GREAT PLEASURE TO HONOR DR. EDWARDS FOR DECADES
OF SERVICE DURING WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH.
>> THANK YOU, DR. EDWAR, FOR LEADING WITH YOUR HEART, WITH
LOVE FOR THE LATE WILL AND FOR THE STRONG 11 FOR SAN FRANCISCO
AND FOR SUPPORTING EVERY STUDENT, EVERY STUDENT WITH THE
FOUNDATION THAT THEY NEED TO THRIVE.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THANK YOU.
COMMISSIONER CHEN. I WAS VERY SURPRISED WHEN I GOT
THE PHONE CALL THAT I GOT THIS HONOR BUT I ACCEPTED BECAUSE WE
AT SHERIDAN HAVE BEEN WORKING VERY HARD TO HELP OUR STUDENTS,
PUTTING STUDENTS FIRST, MAKING SURE THAT EVERY STUDENT HAS
WHAT THEY NEED. SO I ACCEPT THIS NOT JUST FOR
ME BUT FOR MY WHOLE SHERIDAN FAMILY AND COMMUNITY.
I WANT TO THANK COMMISSIONER CHEN.
I WANT TO THANK MY FAMILY AND AS A LONG OR LIFELONG
RESIDENT OF LAKEVIEW. I AM VERY EXCITED TO HAVE THIS
HONOR. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. >> NEXT UP FROM DISTRICT ONE
SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN COLLEAGUES TODAY IN CELEBRATION OF WOMEN'S
HISTORY MONTH WHERE HONORING LEADERS OF A VERY CRITICAL
WOMEN ARE CRITICAL LEADERS OF A VERY CRITICAL MOVEMENT FOR
WOMEN. IT IS THE WOMEN'S HOUSING
COALITION WE'RE HONORING THE COALITION BECAUSE IT IS AND IT
HAS BEEN A POWERFUL MOVEMENT AND A POWERFUL NETWORK OF OVER
22 ORGANIZATIONS AND GROWING IN DIFFERENT HOUSING
AND SERVICES SECTORS COMMITTED TO THE SAME VISION SAVE HOUSING
OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL WOMEN IN SAN FRANCISCO EVERY NIGHT
IN SAN FRANCISCO THERE ARE OVER 3000 WOMEN SLEEPING ON THE
STREETS BUT ACCORDING TO THE REPORTS THIS NUMBER IS GROSSLY
UNDERESTIMATED. WOMEN EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS
ARE UNDERCOUNTED AND UNDERSERVED
AND UNFORTUNATELY HOMELESSNESS IN WOMEN AND CHILDREN IS
GROWING FASTER THAN ANY OTHER POPULATION.
THEY ARE OFTEN VICTIMS AND SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE, SEXUAL ASSAULT AND TRAUMA AND ARE OFTEN
REVICTIMIZED WHILE LIVING ON THE STREETS.
THE WOMEN'S HOUSING COALITION BREAKS THE CYCLE OF VIOLENCE
AND HOMELESSNESS THROUGH COMPASSIONATE CARE AND A
BELIEVE STRONG BELIEVE THAT HOUSING IS A FUNDAMENTAL RIGHT
FOR EVERYONE. FOR ME, IN 2020 THEIR WORK
CENTERS AND UPLIFT WOMEN WITH DIGNITY AND RESPECT LEADING TO
HEALTHIER FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES.
COALITION MEMBERS COVER A WIDE ARRAY OF SAFETY NET SERVICES
FROM SHELTERS TO REENTRY PROGRAMS, HOTLINES, DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE, YOUTH AND OLDER ADULT SUPPORT HUMAN TRAFFICKING
SERVICES AND SO MUCH MORE. LAST YEAR THE COALITION HAS
REALLY HOLD ALL LEADERS ACCOUNTABLE INCLUDING ALL THE
WOMAN SUPERVISOR IN JUST CHAMBERS AND ALLIES TO DECLARE
THAT SAN FRANCISCO AS A SANCTUARY FOR WOMEN SEEKING
HOUSING AND TO URGE CITY DEPARTMENTS TO INVEST OUR
RESOURCES AND INVESTMENTS FOR SAFE SHELTER, AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND WRAPAROUND SERVICES SPECIFICALLY FOR WOMEN
AND WOMEN IDENTIFY SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC ABUSE, SEXUAL
EXPLOITATION AND VIOLENCE. HUMAN TRAFFICKING AND STREET
ENTRAPMENT AND TRAUMA. BUT WE ALL KNOW THERE'S SO MUCH
MORE MORE WORK TO DO. AND I KNOW THE COALITION HAS TO
DEDICATE TO FIGHT THIS FIGHT UNTIL EVERY WOMAN IS OFF THE
STREETS LIVING IN SAFE, STABLE AND SECURE HOUSING.
AND FOR THAT I AM JUST SO GRATEFUL TO THE COALITION.
TODAY WE HAVE I KNOW THERE'S SO MANY MORE LEADERS INVOLVING
WITH THE COALITION. BUT TODAY WE HAVE REBECCA
JACKSON, EVE LANGSTON AND SAMMY RAYNOR HERE WHO ARE ACTUALLY
THE COALITION CO-CHAIRS. >> BUT I KNOW THAT MY
COLLEAGUES ALSO WANT TO SAY A FEW WORDS IN HONOR OF YOUR YOUR
COAL IN HONOR OF YOUR LEADERSHIP IN THE COALITION.
BUT TRULY THE COALITION HAS BEEN WONDERFUL BUT THEY'RE BAD
. >> THEY REALLY ARE.
AND THEY HOLD US ACCOUNTABLE. >> AND I REALLY AM JUST HERE TO
BRING YOU BACK TO THIS CHAMBER. YOU'VE BEEN IN THIS CHAMBER AS
ADVOCATES MANY, MANY TIME AND VOICE YOUR CONCERN AND BE
OUR LEADERS. BUT I THINK THIS IS A MOMENT
THAT WE GET TO HONOR YOU AND SAY THANK YOU AND THANK YOU
FOR YOUR WORK AND THAT WE SEE YOU.
WE RECOGNIZE YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THAT WE WILL CONTINUE TO
WORK WITH YOU. AND DO WE RESPECT YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND THANK YOU FOR HOLDING US ACCOUNTABLE.
>> AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR RECOGNIZING THIS WONDERFUL ORGANIZATION
AND RECOGNIZING REBECCA AND SAMMY AND EVE FOR THE
WONDERFUL WORK THAT THEY DO EVERY DAY HOLDING US
ACCOUNTABLE THIS MONTH AS WE HAVE UNVEILED YOU KNOW, A
WOMEN'S AGENDA IN OUR CITY. THERE ARE NO MORE IMPORTANT
BUILDING BLOCKS IN THAT AGENDA THAN HOUSING THAN THE SHELTER
OVER PEOPLE'S HEADS THAT LEADS TO SECURITY AND SAFETY
AND SUCCESS FOR THEMSELVES AND THEIR FAMILIES.
SO WHAT YOU ARE DOING GOD'S WORK.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR PUTTING TOGETHER A ROADMAP TO SUCCESS
FOR WOMEN AND FOR ALL PEOPLE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WE APPRECIATE YOU AS SUPERVISOR OUR CHANCE AS WE SEE YOU WE
RECOGNIZE YOU. THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO
. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN, THANK YOU
FOR PRESSING. I ALSO JUST WANT TO WHAT I CALL
THAT SYSTEM ADVISOR IS ABOUT I AM VERY INSPIRED AT THAT.
THE COALITION ALWAYS STANDING AT THE INTERSECTIONS OF HOUSING
JUSTICE AND SURVIVOR CENTERED CARE.
>> YOU ARE A POWERFUL NETWORK THAT IS OVER 15 ORGANIZATION
VERY DEDICATED TO SIMPLE BUT PROFOUND TRUTHS HOUSING ITS
FUNDAMENTAL HUMAN RIGHTS. THE WOMEN'S HOUSING COALITION
REFUSED TO LET OVER 33,000 WOMEN WHO EXPERIENCE
HOMELESSNESS ON ANY GIVEN NIGHT REMAIN INVISIBLE.
THANK YOU FOR MAKING SURE THAT THEIR NEEDS HURT.
THANK YOU ALSO FOR YOUR TIRELESS ADVOCACY FOR THOSE
ESCAPING DOMESTIC VIOLENCE, TRAFFICKING AND SYSTEM
DISPLACEMENT. YOU AGAIN I THINK THAT'S MORE
THAN STATS ANY OTHER MORE WORDS THAT I, I CAN CONTINUE TO USE
TO DESCRIBE THE BRAVENESS, THE ADVOCACY OR THE LEADERSHIP THAT
THE LOVE THE LOVE. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH AND WELL,
THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON AND THANK YOU TO THE ENTIRE BOARD AND A SPECIAL
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHAN NOT JUST FOR THIS
RECOGNITION BUT FOR YOUR CONTINUED SUPPORT AND BELIEF
IN OUR WORK. WE ARE BEYOND HONORED TO STAND
HERE TODAY REPRESENTING THE SAN FRANCISCO WOMEN'S HOUSING
COALITION. WE JUST WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT
TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE LEADERSHIP IN THIS ROOM WHO IN RECENT
WEEKS HAVE TAKEN MEANINGFUL AND VERY IMPORTANT IMPORTANT
STEPS TO UPLIFT WOMEN IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT MATTERS BEING
SEEN. MATTERS BEING HEARD, MATTERS.
AND OUR HOPE IS THAT TODAY IS NOT JUST A RECOGNITION THAT
IT'S MORE THAN A FLEETING MOMENT BUT PART OF THIS LARGER
MOMENTUM THAT WE CONTINUE MOVING FORWARD.
>> SAFETY FOR WOMEN TOGETHER AS PARTNERS AND ALLIES.
>> OUR COALITION IS A SCRAPPY HOME.
>> WE'RE JUST 5 OR 6 YEARS OLD AND WE ARE A GROUP OF
ORGANIZATIONS. >> YES, BUT MORE THAN THAT WE
ARE A GROUP OF FIGHTERS BORN OUT OF URGENCY AT A TIME WHEN
THE REALITIES AND NEEDS FACING WOMEN AND SURVIVORS WERE
IMPOSSIBLE TO CONTINUE TO IGNORE.
WE CAME TOGETHER NOT BECAUSE IT WAS EASY BUT BECAUSE IT WAS
NECESSARY BECAUSE WHAT WE WERE SEEING IN OUR WORK DEMANDED
SOMETHING BIGGER DEMANDS TO BE SEEN AND HEARD.
>> WE DON'T JUST TALK ABOUT THE ISSUES WE LIVE THEM IN OUR
DAILY WORK AS ENDEAVOR TOOLS, AS ORGANIZATIONS AND AS A
COALITION WE SEE AND WE FEEL WHEN AND WHERE SYSTEMS ARE
FALLING SHORT AND WE ARE WORKING HARD TO BREAK DOWN THE
BARRIERS THAT MAKE IT HARDER FOR WOMEN TO BE SAFE AND ACCESS
HOUSING AND AT THE SAME TIME WE SEE EXTRAORDINARY RESILIENCE.
>> WE SEE HOPE. WE SEE THE POWER IN COLLECTIVE
ACTION AND ADVOCACY AND THAT IS WHAT DRIVES US TO KEEP PUSHING
EVERY SINGLE DAY WHILE A FEW OF US ARE HERE TODAY.
>> SO MANY OF OUR COLLEAGUES ARE NOT BECAUSE THEY'RE OUT
THERE RIGHT NOW. ADS ARE OUT, THE PROGRAMS
ANSWERING THE PHONES AND LITERALLY OPENING THE
DOORS, DOING THE WORK. >> WE WANT TO LIFT THEM UP
AND NAME OUR CORE MEMBERS BECAUSE THIS RECOGNITION
BELONGS TO ALL OF US. >> SO CHEERS TO CG CAMEO HOUSE
BLACK WOMEN REBEL AGAINST DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SAN FRANCISCO
SAFE HOUSE COMMUNITY FORD FREEDOM FOR THE HYPE CENTER THE
MARY ELIZABETH INN SINCE 1914 LA CASA DE LAS MADRES HOMELESS
PRENATAL PROGRAM THE WOMEN'S BUILDING YOUNG WOMEN'S FREEDOM
CENTER ASIAN WOMEN'S SHELTER COMPASS FAMILY SERVICES WOMEN
INC THE SAN FRANCISCO COLLABORATIVE AGAINST HUMAN
TRAFFICKING. >> MS. BEV UPTON, WHO
REPRESENTS THE ENTIRETY OF THE DOMESTIC VIOLENCE CONSORTIUM
AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST MISS ROMA GUY WHO MENTORS MANY OF US
IN OUR CONTINUED FIGHT FOR WOMEN.
>> THANK YOU. >> THIS RECOGNITION FROM THE
CITY MEANS A GREAT DEAL. BUT WE ALSO WANT TO BE CLEAR
THE FIGHT FOR SURVIVAL DOES NOT SLOW DOWN WHEN THE SPOTLIGHT
TURNS ON. IF ANYTHING, IT REMINDS US OF
HOW MUCH MORE WORK THERE IS TO DO.
THOUGH WE ARE YOUNG WE ARE MIGHTY.
IN A FEW SHORT YEARS WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO ACCOMPLISH MANY
MILESTONES. >> WE'VE HELD A CITY WIDE
RETREAT WITH ALL DEPARTMENT HEADS IDENTIFYING THE GAPS THAT
WE SEE ON THE GROUND. >> WE'RE ABLE TO PASS PROP
EIGHT THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING BOND WHICH FOR THE FIRST TIME
IN THE HISTORY OF THIS CITY PROVIDED A CARVE OUT FOR
SURVIVORS CREATING NEW HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES.
>> LAST YEAR WE LAUNCHED A CITYWIDE UNHOUSED WOMEN'S NEEDS
ASSESSMENT SURVEY WHICH IS CURRENTLY BEING ANALYZED.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO SHARING WITH EACH OF YOU AND THE CITY
DEPARTMENT HEADS THE RESULTS OF THAT SURVEY THROUGH ANOTHER
CITY RETREAT AND MAYBE LATER A HEARING.
>> THIS ISN'T JUST LIMITED TO THE WOMEN OF SAN FRANCISCO.
WE ARE SUPPORTING WOMEN ACROSS THE STATE.
WE ARE SPONSORING ASSEMBLY BILL 1573 THE UNSEEN UNHEARD HOUSING
ACT WHICH REQUIRES COUNTIES TO COME UP WITH A HOUSING PLAN FOR
SURVIVORS OF SEXUAL ASSAULT, HUMAN TRAFFICKING AND DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE THROUGH THE HOUSING ELEMENT.
>> WE'RE ALSO SUPPORTING OTHER BILLS LIKE ASSEMBLY BILL 1877
BORN OUT OF THESE HALLS WHICH OUR OWN DR. PAM TAYLOR BLACKMON
OF MARYVILLE IS OUT IN SACRAMENTO TODAY SUPPORTING
THAT WOULD GIVE PROSECUTORS THE ABILITY TO PURSUE FELONY
CHARGES WHEN A CRIMINAL PROTECTIVE ORDER VIOLATION
INDICATES A CREDIBLE AND SERIOUS THREAT.
THIS IS JUST A SMALL PIECE OF WHAT WE'VE BEEN ABLE TO
ACCOMPLISH AND A REMINDER THAT THE WORK STILL NEEDS TO BE
DONE. IT'S WHY IT'S SO IMPORTANT TO
CONTINUE TO SUPPORT THESE ORGANIZATIONS AND THESE
SERVICES NOT ONLY THROUGH ACCOLADES BUT THROUGH ADVOCACY,
THROUGH LEGISLATION. >> AND YES, THERE ARE A CITY
BUDGET. >> BUT ACCOLADES IS ALSO NICE
TOO. SO WE THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> IN CLOSING, WE ACCEPT THIS HONOR WITH SO MUCH GRATITUDE.
THANK YOU FOR MAKING NOT ONLY OUR COALITION BUT WOMEN SEEN
IN THIS CITY AND THE OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO ONCE
AGAIN PRESENT THE URGENCY AND NEED FOR OUR COMMUNITY TO
DO BETTER FOR WOMEN IN OUR COMMUNITY.
>> AND REALLY FOR US I THINK IT'S ABOUT COMING BACK TO HOW
ARE WE GOING TO SOLVE HOMELESSNESS AS A COMMUNITY NOT
JUST FOR WOMEN BUT FOR EVERYONE AND EVERY SINGLE MEMBER OF THIS
BOARD IS ALIGNED ON SAFETY. >> AND THAT IS WHAT OUR
PROGRAMS AND OUR SERVICES REPRESENT IS BRINGING THAT
SAFETY INTO THE SHELTERS AND THE SAFETY NET THAT SHOULD
BE THERE TO CATCH OUR COMMUNITY.
>> SO THANK YOU FOR THIS OPPORTUNITY TO CONTINUE OUR
PARTNERSHIP
. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> NEXT UP DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES.
TODAY I AM HONORED TO WELCOME LYNN DAVIS UP TO THE PODIUM.
>> LINDY, WHERE ARE YOU? THERE YOU ARE.
>> IN CELEBRATION OF WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH.
IT IS AN ABSOLUTE HONOR TO COMMEND YOU, LYNN, FOR YOUR
DECADES OF DEDICATED SERVICE TO THE OPERA PLAZA NEIGHBORHOOD
AND YOUR EXTRAORDINARY COMMITMENT TO BUILDING
COMMUNITY RIGHT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO MARKING THIS MOMENT
AS LYNDON'S HER TENURE AFTER MORE THAN A DECADE OF
LEADERSHIP AS PRESIDENT OF THE OPERA PLAZA HOA.
BORN IN PHENIX, ARIZONA, LYNN IS A NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY
GRADUATE WHO CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1976 MAKING THIS
CITY HER PERMANENT HOME ROOTING HERSELF HERE FOR NEARLY 50
YEARS AND CHANNELING HER ENERGY INTO THE PEOPLE AND THE
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT SHE LOVES. FOR 36 YEARS LYNN WORKED IN ONE
OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST PRESTIGIOUS LAW FIRMS,
PILLSBURY, MADISON AND SUTRO MANAGING THEIR ADMINISTRATIVE
OPERATIONS AND COORDINATING THE OPENING OF MULTIPLE OFFICES.
SHE ALSO WORKED FOR 15 YEARS AS A MEMBER OF UNITED WAY HELPING
TO RAISE MILLIONS OF DOLLARS FROM STAFF AND ATTORNEYS.
AND IF THAT WASN'T ENOUGH, SHE HELPED COORDINATE THE SAN
FRANCISCO BAR ASSOCIATION'S FOOD FROM THE BAR CAMPAIGN FOR
THE SAN FRANCISCO AND MARIN COUNTY FOOD BANKS.
>> SINCE RETIRING IN 2012, LYNN HAS DEVOTED HERSELF FULLY TO
COMMUNITY SERVICE VOLUNTEERING WITH BREAD AND ROSES,
SUPPORTING THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY SCHOOL SERVING IN THE
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT NORTHERN STATIONS COMMUNITY
POLICE ADVISORY BOARD AND BECOMING NURSE CERTIFIED TO
SERVE HER NEIGHBORS IN TIMES OF EMERGENCY AND AS PRESIDENT OF
THE UPPER PLAZA HOA BOARD OF DIRECTORS A ROLE SHE'S HELD
SINCE 2014. LYNN HAS BEEN A STEADY,
COMPASSIONATE STEWARD OF HER COMMUNITY ORGANIZING
AND LEADING COMMUNITY MEETINGS WITH SKILL AND WITH CARE.
>> LYNN IS ALSO A MEMBER OF SAN FRANCISCO VILLAGE WHERE SHE
FOCUSES ON ENRICHING THE LIVES OF OUR SENIORS THROUGH WRITERS
WORKSHOPS AND EMBODYING HER LIFELONG BELIEF THAT EVERYONE
DESERVES CONNECTION, DIGNITY AND A VOICE.
EVERYONE. >> EVERYBODY.
LYNN IS THERE FOR EVERY BODY. WHEN ERIC TACKETT, A BELOVED
FIXTURE OUTSIDE THE BOOKS SINK AT OPERA PLAZA FOR 30 YEARS WAS
ATTACKED AND HOSPITALIZED IN 2013, IT WAS LYNN WHO
STEPPED FORWARD TO HELP LOCATE HIS FAMILY ENSURE HE WAS CARED
FOR SPENDING HER OWN TIME AND ENERGY TO HELP A PERSON WHO
HAD NO ONE ELSE TO TURN TO. >> LYNN'S EFFORT ON ERIC'S
BEHALF EXEMPLIFY WHO SHE IS SOMEONE WHO SEES THE HUMANITY
IN EVERY PERSON IN HER COMMUNITY AND WHO ACTS ON THAT
RECOGNITION WITH QUIET, DETERMINED GRACE.
LYNN EMBODIES THE SPIRIT OF SAN FRANCISCO AT ITS BEST PRACTICAL
COMPASSION FIT AND DEEPLY ROOTED IN A BELIEF THAT A
NEIGHBORHOOD IS ONLY AS STRONG AS THE CARE ITS RESIDENTS GIVE
TO EACH OTHER. IT IS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT
EVERY MORNING YOU SIT IN YOUR GREAT GRANDFATHER'S MAHOGANY
ROCKING CHAIR AND LOOK EASTWARD TO SEE THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY
AND EAST BAY HILLS. SO FROM ALL OF US I WISH THAT
YOU CONTINUE TO ENJOY YOUR MORNINGS AND YOUR ADVENTURES
AHEAD IN YOUR NEXT CHAPTER. LYNN ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS, THANK YOU FOR YOUR EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE TO OPERA
PLAZA TO SAN FRANCISCO'S ELDERS AND TO ITS MOST VULNERABLE
RESIDENTS AND TO THE VISION OF A CITY WHERE NO ONE IS
INVISIBLE AND EVERYONE BELONGS .
>> LYNN THE FLOOR IS YOURS. THANK YOU.
>> AND NOW I CAN LAUGH BECAUSE ALL OF THIS WAS JUST SAID
AND MAYBE I'LL SAY TWO SENTENCES FROM THIS.
>> I STILL REMEMBER DRIVING TO THE MOUNT MADONNA CENTER
IN WATSON VILLE FOR A WEEKEND RETREAT.
I WAS 50 YEARS OLD IN 19 97 AND TAKING A DEEP BREATH ABOUT
ENTERING MIDDLE AGE. >> THE TEACHER WAS ANGELA
AND WITHIN MOMENTS I KNEW I WOULD STUDY WITH HER DURING
FOUR FOLD WAY COURSES IN 1998 AND THROUGH 2001.
>> HER MAJOR THEMES CONTINUE TO INTERWEAVE THROUGH MY LIFE.
>> ONE WALKING THE PRACTICAL PATH WITH MYSTICAL FEET.
I HEAR THAT EVERY DAY WALKING THE PRACTICAL PATH WITH
MYSTICAL FEET TO BOTH SLASH AND COMER AND AND THAT'S A
LITTLE HARDER TO TALK ABOUT BECAUSE SOMETIMES YOU GET STUCK
AND YOU DON'T KNOW HOW TO GET YOURSELF UNSTUCK.
>> AND SO WHAT YOU DO OR WHAT I DO IS I THINK BOTH SLASH
AND COME. >> AND AND THE THIRD IS VISION
QUESTS. >> AND I DID THOSE DECADES AGO
AND IT CHANGED MY LIFE. SO THEN IN 19 76 I TOOK A THREE
WEEK JOB AT THE CORPORATE LAW FIRM THAT ULTIMATELY SHORTENED
TO PILLSBURY. >> THREE WEEKS 40 YEARS LATER I
RETIRED. DON'T ASK ME WHY BUT I DID.
>> I WORKED MANY OFFICES AROUND THE UNITED STATES AND I JUST
RELISHED IN MAKING BOTH AND DECISIONS AROUND
COMPLICATED ADMINISTRATIVE BLUES.
>> THE OTHER THING IS I KNEW I NEEDED TO SEE WATER BECAUSE
THAT'S WHAT ROOTS ME TO THIS PLANET EARTH.
AND EVEN THOUGH I WAS BORN IN PHENIX, ARIZONA, THERE
WASN'T A LOT OF WATER EXCEPT FOR THE VERDE RIVER AND PHENIX,
ARIZONA. BUT IT WAS TIME FOR ME TO GET
TO SAN FRANCISCO SO I CONNECTED WITH MY OLDER BROTHER JACK
AND HIS TWO CHILDREN SARAH AND HAYDEN.
>> AND THEY MY OLDER BROTHER LOVE HIS HEART BUILT HOUSEBOATS
ON CHANNEL CREEK IN SAN FRANCISCO.
RIGHT OFF OF THIRD AND I THINK HE BUILT FOUR HOUSEBOATS
BECAUSE TWO AND A HALF SUNK. AND NEVER AGAIN CAME BACK UP
THAT I REMEMBER. >> I ENJOYED DINNER WITH THE
HOUSEBOAT AS AUNTIE WITH A NIECE AND GREAT NIECE AND I
JUST KEPT IN TOUCH WITH ALL OF THE FAMILY AROUND.
AND THEN I BOUGHT MY CONDOMINIUM AT OPERA PLAZA
IN 2008 AND JOINED THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS AND BECAME MADAM
PRESIDENT BECAUSE THERE WERE A LOT OF SPANISH PEOPLE THERE
AND AT MAX'S ONE OF THE WONDERFUL PEOPLE WHEN HE SAW ME
I ALWAYS SAID MADAM PRESIDENT, OKAY.
EACH MORNING I SIT IN MY GRANDFATHER'S MAHOGANY ROCKING
CHAIR THAT CAME ALL THE WAY FROM THE EAST COAST AND I LOOK
FORWARD TO SEEING THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AND THE EAST BAY
HILLS. SO THAT IS LYNNE LOUISE DAVIS.
>> THANK YOU
. >> ALL RIGHT.
NEXT UP WE HAVE DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MADELINE.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF WELCOMING BRIDGMAN,
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF FISHERMAN'S WHARF COMMUNITY
BENEFIT DISTRICT THREE. >> WOULD YOU PLEASE COME UP
AND JOIN US AS WE CELEBRATE WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH?
I'M SO HAPPY THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS A CHAMPION IN BREA TO SHAPE
ONE OF OUR CITY'S MOST IMPORTANT SPACES FISHERMAN'S
WHARF. BREE WAS SELECTED LAST YEAR AS
THE NEW EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF FISHERMAN'S WHARF CBD, A
PROCESS IN WHICH SHE BEAT OUT MORE THAN 270 OTHER APPLICANTS
FOR THE ROLE. SHE HAS 18 YEARS OF EXPERIENCE
IN THE PUBLIC SPACE STEWARDSHIP AND PREVIOUSLY SERVED AS THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF YERBA BUENA GARDENS CONSERVANCY.
BRIA DOES NOT HAVE AN EASY JOB IN REPRESENTING FISHERMAN'S
WHARF. SHE MUST WEIGH THE NEEDS OF
TOURISM WITH THE PUSH TO ATTRACT LOCALS AND T BALANCE
OF A WORKING WATERFRONT WITH PROUD ROOTS.
WITH THE NEED TO STAY MODERN IN A COMPETITIVE TOURISM
MARKET. >> BUT SHE APPROACHES THIS WORK
WITH DEDICATION, OPTIMISM AND A DOGGED PERSISTENCE THAT IS
GETTING RESULTS. BECAUSE OF THIS, UNDER HER
LEADERSHIP THERE IS RENEWED EXCITEMENT AND MOMENTUM
THROUGHOUT ALL OF THE WHARF RESTAURANTS ARE FILLING UP
AGAIN. FOOT TRAFFIC IS PICKING UP.
A NEW PUBLIC PLAZA WILL OPEN LATER THIS YEAR.
THE SKY STAR FERRIS WHEEL IS DELIGHTING PASSENGERS WITH
BREATHTAKING VIEWS AND BRIA HAS FOUND A REASON TO CELEBRATE
EVERY OCCASION IN THE WHARF. GET THE RECENT CRAB COURT CRAB
CRAWL. THE PIER PARTY SUMMER CONCERT
SERIES OR FERRY CREATIVE ACTIVATIONS FOR THE RECENT
SUPER BOWL. SHE LEADS AN INCREDIBLE TEAM
AND I SEE A NUMBER OF THEM HERE TODAY.
AND SHE WORKS TO EMPOWER THEM EACH DAY TO DO THEIR BEST WORK
WHETHER THAT BE CLEANING AND TAKING CARE OF PUBLIC
SPACES, PLANNING EVENTS, BOOSTING THE WHARF AS A TOURISM
ATTRACTION, LONGTIME MERCHANTS, HOSPITALITY PARTNERS THE
FISHING INDUSTRY HAVE ALL FELT HEARD AND SUPPORTED BY BREE
IN HER UNDERSTANDING OF THE IMPORTANCE OF THE ROLE THE CBD
PLAYS AND PROVIDING A SPACE FOR COLLABORATION AND TEAMWORK
ACROSS THE WHARF. OUR CITY IS VERY LUCKY TO HAVE
HER AS A PARTNER IN THIS WORK AND HER TEAM AT THE CBD AND WE
KNOW WE ARE IN GOOD HANDS. IT'S BEEN JUST ONE YEAR.
SHE'S ALREADY MADE HER MARK AND WE'RE VERY EXCITED TO SEE
WHERE SHE TAKES US NEXT SO THANK YOU BREE AND THE FLOOR IS
YOURS IF YOU HAVE ANY REMARKS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. >> AND I FIRST I MEAN LISTENING
ALL THESE AMAZING WOMEN SPEAK AND ALL OF THE WORK THAT
THEY'VE DEDICATED THEIR LIVES TO.
I AM IN AWE OF ALL THE HONOREES HERE.
SOME OF THEM HAVE LEFT BUT AND HUMBLED TO BE IN THEIR
COMPANY. THANK YOU FOR THIS VERY SPECIAL
HONOR AND A VERY SPECIAL THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR SAUTER FOR
SELECTING ME YOUR LEADERSHIP IS EXEMPLARY AND WE'RE VERY LUCKY
TO HAVE YOU AS OUR SUPERVISOR. >> I AM REMINDED OF ONE OF MY
FAVORITE QUOTES BY PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT FAR AND AWAY THE BEST
PRIZE THAT LIFE HAS TO OFFER IS THE CHANCE TO WORK HARD AT WORK
WORTH DOING AND I FEEL SO VERY BLESSED TO DO THE WORK THAT I
DO AND I FERVENTLY BELIEVE IN LEADING WITH HEART
AND INTEGRITY AND I'M SO PROUD AND TICKLED PINK TO BE ABLE TO
WORK IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AS I THINK A LOT
OF US IN THESE CHAMBERS FEEL THE SAME.
AS A COMMITTED PARTNER TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THE FISHERMAN'S WHARF COMMUNITY
BENEFIT DISTRICT PLAYS AN INTRINSIC ROLE.
>> THE CBD WORKS HARD TO PROVIDE VITAL SERVICES
AND SUPPORT THAT ENSURE THE WHARF REMAINS A POSITIVE
AND WELCOMING DESTINATION FOR BOTH LOCALS AND VISITORS FROM
AFAR. FOR GENERATIONS TO COME I AM
DEEPLY HONORED TO RECEIVE THIS COMMENDATION ESPECIALLY DURING
WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH AND I'M ALSO VERY VERY LUCKY
AND FORTUNATE TO BE SURROUNDED BY INTELLIGENT, CAPABLE
AND IMPACTFUL WOMEN. AND TO MY TEAM SPECIFICALLY ON
CECILE, CAITLIN, MARLO AND JOSH .
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR WORK AND I WILL SHARE THIS
HONOR WITH THEM. >> THANK YOU
FROM DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR HUANG PLUME AND THE AMERICAN
RED CROSS COME ON UP. >> HEY, THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT MENEM AND COLLEAGUES AS WE CELEBRATE WOMEN'S HISTORY
MONTH IT IS ESPECIALLY FITTING TO BEGIN BY HONORING ONE OF THE
MOST INFLUENTIAL WOMEN IN AMERICAN HISTORY CLARISSA
HARLOWE BARTON, KNOWN TO US AS CLARA BARTON A VISIONARY
HUMANITARIAN A CIVIL WAR NURSE AND A RELENTLESS ADVOCATE FOR
THOSE IN NEED. CLARA BARTON FOUNDED THE
AMERICAN RED CROSS IN 1881 AND HELPED SHAPE OUR NATION'S
COMMITMENT TO NEUTRAL COMPASSIONATE RELIEF IN TIMES
OFRISIS. HER LEGACY CONTINUES TO INSPIRE
MILLIONS AND REMAINS AT THE HEART OF THE RED CROSS MISSION
HERE IN THE BAY AREA. >> THE RED CROSS CONTINUES TO
LEAD WITH THE SAME SPIRIT OF COMPASSION AND PROFESSIONALISM
. THIS YEAR IS ESPECIALLY
MEANINGFUL. IT MARKS THE 120TH ANNIVERSARY
OF THE PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN THE RED CROSS AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO A PARTNERSHIP THAT BEGAN IN THE
AFTERMATH OF THE 1906 EARTHQUAKE AND HAS GUIDED OUR
SHARED COMMITMENT TO READINESS AND RECOVERY EVER SINCE.
EVERY DAY OFTEN WITHOUT FANFARE, RED CROSS VOLUNTEERS
AND STAFF STEP FORWARD. WHEN SAN FRANCISCANS ARE FACING
THEIR MOST DIFFICULT MOMENTS WHEN THERE IS A FIRE IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE NIGHT WHEN A FAMILY HAS BEEN DISPLACED, WHEN
A PATIENT NEEDS LIFESAVING BLOOD OR WHEN DISASTER STRIKES
THE RED CROSS IS THERE. THEY PROVIDE SHELTER, FOOD
AND EMERGENCY SUPPORT AFTER DISASTERS.
THEY MAINTAIN A SAFE AND RELIABLE BLOOD SUPPLY THAT
SAVES LIVES EVERY SINGLE DAY. >> THEY TRAIN OUR NEIGHBORS
IN CPR FIRST AID AND EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS AND THEY SUPPORT
MILITARY MEMBERS, VETERANS AND THEIR FAMILIES WITH ROUND
THE CLOCK GLOBAL SERVICES. BEHIND ALL OF THIS IS A NETWORK
OF VOLUNTEERS ORDINARY PEOPLE DOING EXTRAORDINARY THINGS FOR
OTHERS. I ALSO WANT TO MENTION MY OWN
OFFICE'S CLOSE CONNECTION TO THE RED CROSS MY STAFF.
JESSICA SERVED AS A AMERICORPS MEMBER WITH THE RED CROSS AND I
MYSELF IN ONE OF MY FIRST JOBS OUT OF COLLEGE.
I SERVED FOR ONE YEAR AS A AMERICORPS RED CROSS MEMBER OF
THE BAY AREA CHAPTER WHERE I SERVED AS A DISASTER
PREPAREDNESS SPECIALIST, CPR INSTRUCTOR AND DURING MY
EXPERIENCES WITH THE NATIONAL GUARD WHEN THERE WAS THE TUBBS
FIRE I WAS DEPLOYED TO THE SANTA ROSA EVACUEES SHELTER
AND AS THE LARGEST EVACUEE SHELTER DURING THE TUBBS FIRE
AND WERE CLOSELY WITH RED CROSS VOLUNTEERS THAT WERE DEDICATING
WEEKS OF THEIR TIME VOLUNTEERING THEIR LIVES TO
HELP SUPPORT THOSE THAT WERE IN NEED AND IN NEED OF SHELTER
. RED CROSS MONTH IS A REMINDER
THAT OUR COMMUNITY IS THE STRONGEST WHEN WE LIFT ONE
ANOTHER UP. SO TODAY ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS, I WANT TO THANK THE AMERICAN RED CROSS OF THE
BAY AREA CHAPTER FOR THEIR CONTINUED SERVICE PARTNERSHIP
AND DEDICATION TO SAN FRANCISCO.
IT IS MY HONOR TO PRESENT THIS PROCLAMATION RECOGNIZING MARCH
2026 AS AMERICA'S RED CROSS MONTH.
JOINING US TODAY ARE BOARD CHAIR KENZIE FERGUSON
GOVERNMENT RELATIONS MANAGER ARIANA NASSERI AND REGIONAL
CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER JUSTIN MILLER.
WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP AND LEADERSHIP.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. FIRST OFF I NEED TO START BY
EXPRESSING MY GRATITUDE. SUPERVISOR HUANG THANK YOU FOR
HONORING US AND TO EVERYONE ON THE BOARD FOR HAVING US HERE
TODAY. YOU ALREADY MENTIONED 145 YEARS
AGO CLARA BARTON STARTED A LEGACY WOMEN LEADING THROUGH
PHILANTHROPIC EFFORTS AND THAT LEGACY LIVES ON.
AND TODAY I'M JOINED BY MY BOARD CHAIR KENZIE FERGUSON
AND SHE IS GOING TO TALK A LITTLE BIT MORE ABOUT THE
IMPACT RIGHT HERE IN OUR COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU, JUSTIN AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG.
IT'S NICE TO SEE YOU AGAIN. MY NAME'S KENZIE FERGUSON.
I HAVE THE HONOR AND PRIVILEGE TO SERVE AS THE VOLUNTEER CHAIR
OF THE BAY AREA CHAPTER OF RED CROSS.
>> AND I'M JUST SO HAPPENS I FINALLY GOT A CHANCE TO LIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO IN 2019, LIVED OUT ON THE PENINSULA, FINALLY
GOT TO LIVE IN THIS GLORIOUS CITY.
>> SO AS JUSTIN WAS SAYING, THE AMERICAN RED CROSS IS A
CONGRESSIONALLY CHARTERED NONPROFIT ESTABLISHED IN THE
PRINCIPLE OF PREVENTING AND ALLEVIATING HUMAN
SUFFERING. IN THE PAST FISCAL YEAR WE'VE
RESPONDED TO OVER 860 DISASTER EVENTS RIGHT HERE IN THE BAY
AREA. THE MAJORITY OF THESE WERE HOME
FIRES. WE'VE OPENED THOUSANDS OF
DISASTER CASES COLLECTED OVER 150,000 UNITS OF BLOOD
AND TRAINED CLOSE TO 100,000 PEOPLE IN FIRST AID.
LIFESAVING CPR AND IT REALLY DOESN'T STOP THERE.
OUR VOLUNTEERS STAND WITH THE MILITARY FAMILIES FOR THE
MOMENT. THEIR LOVED ONES ARE SWORN
IN TO SERVE THIS COUNTRY THROUGH DEPLOYMENTS,
EMERGENCIES AND TIMES OF CRISIS ENABLING CONNECTION WHEN IT
MATTERS MOST. >> THIS INCLUDES OVER 8000
FAMILIES HERE IN THE BAY AREA. >> OUR HEARTS ARE WITH THOSE
ALL AROUND THE GLOBE AS WE REMAIN COMMITTED TO HELP
IN TIMES OF INTERNATIONAL CRISIS.
WE STAND ALONGSIDE RED CROSS AND RED CRESCENT SOCIETIES
WHOSE TEAMS ARE ON THE GROUND AT THIS VERY MOMENT RESPONDING
TO HUMANITARIAN NEEDS AND SUPPORTING COMMUNITIES WITH
PROTECTION, RELIEF AND ESSENTIAL RESOURCES.
>> AND AS YOU ALL HAVE SAID, OUR HISTORY OF SERVICE IN SAN
FRANCISCO DATES BACK OVER A CENTURY.
>> AND THIS CITY IS REALLY DEFINED BY RESILIENCY.
>> EARTHQUAKES, WILDFIRES, HOME FIRES, EVEN TSUNAMI WARNINGS
YOU NAME IT. SAN FRANCISCO HAS HAD TO LIVE
THROUGH IT. AND THE RED CROSS HAS STOOD
ALONGSIDE THE CITY THROUGH IT ALL.
>> A BEACON OF HOPE AND RECOVERY FOR THOSE
EXPERIENCES SOME OF THE GREATEST HARDSHIPS IN THEIR
LIVES THIS CITY THAT IS ALWAYS PROGRESSING THAT'S WHAT I LOVE
ABOUT THIS CITY. >> BUT THAT PROGRESS IS ONLY
POSSIBLE THANKS TO THE STRENGTH OF THE RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN
ELECTED OFFICIALS AND COMMUNITY PARTNERS.
THE RED CROSS IS MADE UP BY THE COMMUNITY AND WORKS FOR THE
COMMUNITY WITH ALL THEIR OVER 90% OF THE WORK FORCE OF THE
RED CROSS IS COMPRISED OF VOLUNTEERS.
>> IT'S A SYMBOL OF HOPE, A SIGN OF PEOPLE.
THE PEOPLE WANT TO PLAY A DIRECT ROLE IN KEEPING
COMMUNITIES SAFE. >> SO WHEN WE WIN, WHEN FOLKS
WALK THROUGH THOSE DOORS ON MARKET STREET AND ROLL UP THEIR
SLEEVES TO DONATE TO DONATE BLOOD, THEY'RE SERVING THE
MISSION AND THEY'RE SAVING LIVES OF PEOPLE JUST LIKE ME.
>> I RECEIVE TWO UNITS OF LIFESAVING BLOOD ABOUT A DECADE
AGO AND I WAS ONE OF THE HARDEST PARTS OF MY LIFE.
AND THE RED CROSS WAS THERE WITH LOCAL VOLUNTEERS MANY OF
WHOM ARE YOUR CONSTITUENTS PUT THEIR LIVES ON PAUSE FOR WEEKS
TO DEPLOY TO DISASTER OPERATIONS ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
>> THEY SERVE OUR MISSION AND TODAY BY HONORING THE RED
CROSS WITH THIS PROCLAMATION RECOGNIZING ONE OF OUR HISTORIC
MILESTONES, YOU ARE ALL SERVING THE MISSION.
THE TRADITION OF MARCH IS RED CROSS MONTH AS WELL AS WOMEN'S
HISTORY MONTH. >> IT BEGAN 80 YEARS AGO RIGHT
HERE WITH PRESIDENT FRANKLIN D ROOSEVELT ISSUED THE FIRST
NATIONAL RED CROSS MONTH PROCLAMATION.
>> ALMOST A CENTURY LATER, THE MISSION AND IMPACT OF THE RED
CROSS IS MORE RELEVANT THAN EVER.
>> WE HOPE THAT TODAY IS NOT JUST SYMBOLIC BUT
TRANSFORMATIVE. >> EACH OF YOUR DISTRICTS IS
FILLED WITH POTENTIAL OPPORTUNITIES FOR DONOR
AND VOLUNTEER RECRUITMENT AND ENGAGEMENT DISASTER
RESILIENCY AND PREPAREDNESS. >> MOBILE BLOOD DRIVES AND ALL
AROUND HUMANITARIANISM. >> TOGETHER LET'S USE TODAY AS
A CATALYST TO INVIGORATE THE PARTNERSHIP BETWEEN OUR TEAMS
TO ENABLE US TO MEET THE HUMANITARIAN NEEDS OF ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS. AND ONCE AGAIN I THANK YOU ALL
FOR THE TIME. SUPERVISOR ONE MY FORMER BOARD
MEMBER I THANK YOU FOR THE HONOR.
>> WE ARE HERE TO RECEIVE TODAY AND I THANK YOU FOR YOUR
CONTINUED PARTNERSHIP
DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
COLLEAGUES IN HONOR OF WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH IT IS MY HONOR TO
RECOGNIZE TATYANA I LOVE LUCY. FOR NEARLY A DECADE OF SERVICE
THE TENDERLOIN AND THE CHILDREN AND FAMILIES WHO CALL IT HOME.
TATYANA WHY DON'T YOU COME TO THE STAGE AND BRING YOUR FAMILY
AND FRIENDS ON AS WELL? >> FOR ALMOST TEN YEARS TATYANA
HAS HELPED MAKE THE TENDERLOIN SAFER FOR CHILDREN ON THEIR WAY
TO AND FROM SCHOOL. >> SHE HAS BECOME A TRUSTED
PRESENCE FOR FAMILIES AND AN IMPORTANT PART OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD'S EVERYDAY LIFE. HER PRESENCE IS FELT IN DEEPLY
PERSONAL WAYS AND THROUGHOUT THE TENDERLOIN PEOPLE PEOPLE
SPEAK ABOUT HER WITH REAL AFFECTION AND GRATITUDE.
>> TATIANA'S OWN JOURNEY TO SAN FRANCISCO REFLECTS A DEEP
COMMITMENT TO SERVING OTHERS AND IS A CLASSIC AMERICAN
STORY. >> SHOULD BORN AND RAISED
IN RUSSIA GRADUATE AID FROM MEDICAL UNIVERSITY IN 1995
AND COMPLETE HER MASTER'S DEGREE IN MEDICINE IN 1998.
>> AFTER MARRYING HER HUSBAND JALAL ON A BIOPSY, SHE LIVED
AND WORKED IN YEMEN FOR 15 YEARS BEFORE MOVING WITH HER
FAMILY TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 2014.
>> LIKE MANY IMMIGRANTS WHO CAME TO THIS CITY IN SEARCH OF
OPPORTUNITY AND STABILITY, SHE BUILT A NEW LIFE HERE THROUGH
SERVICE TO HER COMMUNITY. >> IN 2016, TATIANA BEGAN
VOLUNTEERING WITH THE SAFE PASSAGE PROGRAM AT THE
TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY BENEFIT DISTRICT.
>> WHAT BEGAN AS A VOLUNTEER WORK SOON GREW INTO A LARGER
ROLE. OVER TIME SHE TOOK ON MORE
RESPONSIBILITY SERVING AS SHIFT LEAD.
IN 2017 PROJECT COORDINATOR IN 2018 ASSISTANT MANAGER
IN 2022 AND THE MANAGER OF THE SAFE PASSAGE PROGRAM STARTING
IN 2024. THROUGHOUT THAT WORK SHE HAS
HELPED CONNECT SCHOOLS, FAMILIES, COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS AND CITY AGENCIES IN SUPPORT OF STUDENT SAFETY.
HER EFFORTS HAVE MADE A REAL DIFFERENCE FOR CHILDREN
NAVIGATING DIFFICULT STREET CONDITIONS AND ONE OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S MOST ACTIVE NEIGHBORHOODS.
>> COMMUNITY MEMBERS CONTINUALLY DESCRIBE TATIANA AS
SOMEONE WHO SHOWS UP WITH CONSISTENCY AND HEART AND THAT
KIND OF DAILY CARE HAS MADE HER A BELOVED PART OF OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD LIFE. >> HER WORK HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED
ACROSS THE CITY. >> IN 2022 SHE RECEIVED THE
GRASSROOTS LEADERSHIP AWARD FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
IMMIGRANT RIGHTS COMMISSION FOR HER ADVOCACY ON BEHALF OF
IMMIGRANTS AND THE WIDER COMMUNITY.
>> SHE'S ALSO SPOKEN PUBLICLY ABOUT THE SAFETY CHALLENGES
CHILDREN FACE NEAR SCHOOLS, INCLUDING THE NEED FOR
IMPROVEMENTS ON DANGEROUS STREETS AND ADVOCACY CONNECTED
TO THE FULL SEVEN HOWARD STREETSCAPE PROJECT.
SHE CALLED ATTENTION TO THE FACT THAT CHILDREN WERE WALKING
TO SCHOOL ALONGSIDE FAST MOVING AND AGGRESSIVE TRAFFIC.
>> SHE HELPED MAKE SURE THOSE CONCERNS WERE HEARD.
AND SHE HAS PAIRED COMPASSION WITH ADVOCACY MAKING SURE THE
EXPERIENCES OF TENDERLOIN, CHILDREN AND FAMILIES ARE NOT
ONLY ACKNOWLEDGED AND ACKNOWLEDGED BUT ACTED ON.
>> AT THE HEART OF ALL THIS IS TATIANA'S STEADY COMMITMENT TO
THE WELL-BEING OF CHILDREN AND FAMILIES IN THE TENDERLOIN.
HER WORK HAS HELPED STUDENTS GET TO SCHOOL MORE SAFELY
AND HAS STRENGTHENED TRUST WITHIN THE COMMUNITY.
AS KATE ROBINSON OF THE TLC PD SAID, I'VE NEVER MET ANYONE
MORE GIVING HEART DRIVEN COMMUNITY LEADER IN MY LIFE.
>> THAT SENTIMENT IS ECHOED ACROSS THE COMMUNITY BY THOSE
WHO KNOW TATIANA AS A SOURCE OF KINDNESS, JOY AND STEADINESS.
ESPECIALLY DURING DIFFICULT TIMES.
TATIANA THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU HAVE DONE
AND CONTINUE TO DO FOR THE TENDERLOIN.
>> YOUR DEDICATION HAS MADE A LASTING DIFFERENCE AND IT IS AN
HONOR TO RECOGNIZE YOU. THIS WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH.
YOU'VE SHOWN UP FOR THIS NEIGHBORHOOD WITH SO MUCH CARE
AND LOVE AND YOUR WORK HAS LEFT A LASTING MARK ON THE
TENDERLOIN. WE ARE SO PROUD TO CELEBRATE
YOU AND THANK YOU FOR BEING SUCH A GUIDING LIGHT EVERY
SINGLE DAY ON THE WAY TO AND FROM WORK.
I HAVE NEVER SEEN YOU NOT HAVE A SMILE.
>> SO THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
TATIANA, CAN YOU GRAB THAT MICROPHONE AND SPEAK DIRECTLY
INTO IT PLEASE? >> THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS
HONOR. >> I'M VERY GRATEFUL AND I
DEEPLY PROUD TO RECEIVE THIS RECOGNITION DURING HUMAN
HISTORY MONTH. >> IT'S A MEANS TO ME NOT ONLY
SO IMPORTANT NOT ONLY AS A WOMAN IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT FOR
ME AS AN IMMIGRANT, AS A MOTHER AND SOMEONE WHO BELIEVE DEEPLY
IN THE POWER OF COMMUNITY. MY JOURNEY THERE HERE HAS NOT
BEEN SIMPLE. >> I WAS BORN AS SYBILLA WOULD
SAY IN RUSSIA AND GROW UP AND GET MY POLITICAL PASSION.
AND I MEET MY HUSBAND TO RUSSIA AND ME MOVE TOGETHER IN YEMEN
AND WE LIVE IN YEMEN FOR 15 YEARS.
WE MAKE OUR SUCCESSFUL CAREER. >> WE GROW UP OUR KIDS AND INTO
2014. LIFE TOOK US ACROSS THE COUNTRY
AND DIFFERENT CULTURE AND WE COME TO SAN FRANCISCO AND START
AND OUR NEW CHAPTER STARTING OVER IN YOUR COUNTRY IT'S NOT
EASY. >> LIKE MANY IMMIGRANTS I HAD
TO LEARN NEW SYSTEM AND NEW LANGUAGE AND FOUND MY PLACE
AGAIN. >> BUT WHAT HELPED ME MOST WAS
IT WAS COMMUNITY PEOPLE WHO WELCOMING US SUPPORTED US
AND SHOWING KINDNESS FOR US. >> THEN YEARS AGO I STARTED TO
WORK WITH SKILLS TO BE THE DISASTER.
THE MUSICIAN OPENED THE DOOR FOR ME AND WELCOMED ME AND I
STARTED AS VOLUNTEER. AND STEP BY STEP I GET MY
POSITION AND I REMEMBER I STARTED ON THE CORNER EARLY
IN THE MORNING WATCHING FAMILY STUDENTS AND NEIGHBORS PASSING
BY AND I QUICKLY RECOGNIZE THAT THIS WORK WAS NOT ONLY ABOUT
CROSSING PEOPLE, IT WAS ABOUT PROTECT HOPE, SUPPORT FAMILIES
AND CHILDREN, CUTE PEOPLE THAT THEIR COMMUNITY CARES ABOUT
THEM. OVER THIS YEAR I EVERY DAY
SUPPORT COMMUNITY BUT THIS RECOGNITION DOES NOT BELONG TO
ME ALONE. IT'S BELONG TO MY PEOPLE MY
TEAM WHO STAND ON THIS CORNER EVERY DAY.
>> VOLUNTEERS FOR WORKING WITH US SCHOOL STAFF, COMMUNITY
PARTNERS AND FAMILIES WHO BELIEVE IN CREATING SAFE SPACE
FOR CHILDREN TODAY DURING WOMAN HISTORY MONTH.
>> I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE STRENGTH OF WOMEN EVERYWHERE.
>> WOMAN WHO LEAD QUIETLY, WHO SUPPORT FAMILIES WHO SUPPORT
ORDERS OF AND WHO CONTINUES TO BUILD STRONG COMMUNITIES
AND WHEN WHEN THEY WORK IT'S DIFFICULT.
>> I AM PROUD TO STAND AMONG SOME MONEY INSPIRING WOMEN WHO
MAKE A DIFFERENCE EVERY DAY OFTEN WITHOUT RECOGNITION BUT
ALWAYS WITH HEART. >> THIS SUNDERLAND COMMUNITY
HAS TEACH ME SOMETHING VERY POWERFUL WHEN PEOPLE CARE FOR
EACH OTHER WHEN WE SHOW UP FOR ONE TO OTHER WE CAN CREATE
SAFETY, DIGNITY AND HOPE. AND ONE MUST CHALLENGE
ENVIRONMENT. THANK YOU FOR RECOGNITION.
I SHARE IT WITH MY FAMILY, WITH MY TEAM, WITH MY SAFETY
STEWARDS AND WITH MY COLLEAGUE AND WITH MY THEN THE LAND
COMMUNITY WHO INSPIRES ME EVERY DAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR MY ALL HERE. >> AND I WANT TO ASK YOU
EVERYONE HERE MOTHER HALF SISTER WIFE FRIENDS WHO WOMAN
PLEASE BUY SOME SMALL FLOWER FOR WOMAN AROUND HERE AND SAY
THANK YOU AND HAPPY WOMAN'S MONTH.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH
TO MY. >> ALL RIGHT WITH THAT MADAM
CLERK LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 13 .
ITEM 13 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO
THE GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN LUTHERAN SOCIAL SERVICES OF
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING FOR MONEY MANAGEMENT SERVICES TO EXTEND
THE GRANT TERM BY 24 MONTHS JUNE 30TH 2026 FOR A TOTAL TERM
OF JULY 1ST 2021 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO INCREASE THE
AGREEMENT AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 5.2 MILLION FOR A
NEW TOTAL OF APPROXIMATELY 15.2 MILLION.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM ON ITEM 13.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THEIR ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 14 ITEM 14 THIS IS
A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE A CONTRACT NUMBER 1330 FOR
INFRASTRUCTURE FACILITY PROJECT AGREEMENT WITH PRG POTRERO
PROPERTIES LLC FOR THE DESIGN CONSTRUCTION AND FINANCING OF A
BUS STORAGE AND MAINTENANCE FACILITY FOR THE POTRERO YARD
MODERNIZATION PROJECT SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT I FIRST WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON
AS WELL AS OUR FORMER COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR HILLARY RONEN FOR
ALL THEIR EFFORT AROUND THIS. BUT I ALSO WANT TO GIVE
ACKNOWLEDGMENT TO MY MENTOR AND FOR A MORE FOR A MORE FORM
FORMER SUPERVISOR DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR SOPHIA MAXWELL FOR A
LOT OF EFFORT OVER THE TIME AND AND OVER THIS ALMOST TWO
DECADES PERIOD REALLY REVOLVING PATROL YOUR AS POTENTIAL SITES
FOR HOUSING AS WELL AS A BUS MAINTENANCE SPACE I THINK THAT
FOR ALL THIS EFFORT AND GIVEN ALSO ON TOP OF WHAT WE HAVE
JUST BEEN THROUGH AS A BODY LAST YEAR ALONG WITH
MAYOR LURIE AND HOW WE HAVE ALL THESE INTENSE DEBATES
AND TRYING TO PUSH THE CITY FORWARD AND MEETING THE DEMANDS
OF 82,000 UNITS OF HOUSING BY THE STATE HOUSE STATE HOUSING
ELEMENT AND THE STATE MANDATES OUT OF WHICH WE KNOW THAT THERE
SHOULD BE 56,000 OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND SEEING MY
COLLEAGUES INCLUDING FORMER SUPERVISORS THAT REALLY WITH
THEIR HERCULEAN EFFORTS TO TRY TO HAVE HOUSING AND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AT THE SITE FOR US TO COME TO THIS CONCLUSION TODAY
IS RATHER DISAPPOINTING NOT ONLY FOR ME AS A BUDGET
COMMITTEE CHAIR THAT I HAVE TO APPROVE THIS AND A VOTE
IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT AS IT CURRENTLY NOW STANDS BUT
ALSO AS JUST SOMEONE THAT HAS BEEN REALLY BOTH WORKING ON
THIS BUT ON AND OFF FOR FOR QUITE SOME TIME AND AS AS WELL
AS BEING HOPING TO SEE HOUSING ON SITE FOR FOR QUITE SOME TIME
SO HERE WE ARE AND SEEING THAT WE SHOULD AND OUGHT TO MOVE
THIS PROJECT FORWARD BECAUSE NOT ONLY THAT IT'S PART OF THE
BOND BOND PROJECT THAT IT'S UPCOMING FOR THE VOTERS
APPROVAL WHICH I SUPPORT AND THAT WE ALSO SEE THAT THERE
ARE STILL AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT MAY NOT BE THE UNIT
NUMBER THAT WE SEEK ORIGINALLY BUT NONETHELESS IT DOES PROVIDE
UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING HOWEVER, BECAUSE OF THE
SIGNIFICANT REDUCTION AND WE HAD THIS DISCUSSION DURING
BUDGET COMMITTEE LAST WEDNESDAY BUT TO ENSURE THAT THIS COME
OUT OF BUDGET COMMITTEE IN A TIMELY FASHION WE VOTED OUT
WITH RECOMMENDATION WITH THE UNDERSTANDING THAT I WILL
POTENTIALLY COME TO YOU WITH AMENDMENTS AS WELL AS A LETTER
UPDATED AND PROVIDED BY SFM TO AGAIN REITERATE THE REASON OF
WHY FROM THEIR POINT OF VIEW AND FROM THEIR STANDPOINT THIS
IS NOT FINANCIALLY FEASIBLE FOR S.F. MTA TO CONTINUE TO PURSUE
AND FOR ME IS TO SAY WELL LET'S MAKE SURE THAT OUR AND TO
REALLY URGE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO IDENTIFY FUNDING SOURCES TO CONSTRUCT THE MUCH
NEEDED HOUSING IN THE FUTURE EITHER BE PART OF THIS PROJECT
OR ADD ANOTHER SITE. AND SO WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I
WOULD LIKE TO MAKE AMENDMENTS TO KEEP THE CITY ON TRACK TO
DELIVER HOUSING THAT WE NEED FOR THE COMMUNITY.
CLEARLY THEY'RE NONBINDING BUT I NONETHELESS I THINK THAT THIS
BODY SHOULD MAKE THAT STATEMENT SO THAT WE ARE CONSISTENT FROM
NOT ONLY WHAT WE AS A BODY APPROVE LAST YEAR AS FAMILY
ZONING PLAN AND RESPONDING TO THE STATE HOUSING MANDATE
AND THE AMENDMENTS THAT I AM PROPOSING TODAY IS ON PAGE
FOUR, LINE FIVE ADDING THE CLAUSE WHEREAS IN MARCH 2020
FOR THE PLANNING COMMISSION AND BOARD SUPERVISORS EACH
UNANIMOUSLY APPROVED ENTITLEMENTS LEGISLATION ON
FILE WITH THE CLERK OF BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN FILE NUMBER
240136 WHICH IS HEREBY DECLARED TO BE A PART OF THIS RESOLUTION
AS IS SET FORTH FULLY HERE AND FOR THE PATROL YOUR MARGIN
IZATION PROJECT THAT ALLOW FOR THE 465 UNITS AFFORDABLE
HOUSING COMPONENT WHERE EACH BODY CITING THE WIDESPREAD
AND STRONG PUBLIC COMMUNITY SUPPORT FOR THE INNOVATIVE
JOINT DEVELOPMENT PROJECT. THEN ON PAGE 14 LINE 15 TO ADD
FURTHER RESOLVE THAT GIVEN DOESN'T EVICTIONS REDUCTION OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS IN THE PATROL YARD MODERNIZATION
PROJECT AFTER THE MIDYEAR ENGAGEMENT PROCESS WITH THE
COMMUNITY, THE BOARD SUPERVISORS URGES H C D TO
IDENTIFY FUNDING SOURCES TO CONSTRUCT THE INFRASTRUCTURE
NEEDED TO ENABLE FUTURE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT OPPORTUNITIES AS
PART OF THE PATROL. YOUR MODERNIZATION PROJECT
AND BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED THAT THE BOARD SUPERVISOR URGES AS A
FIRM TO IDENTIFY ADDITIONAL SITES AND COLLABORATE WITH
EMULEX CITY TO DELIVER 465 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO
THE COMMUNITY AS PROVIDED IN THE ENTITLEMENT LEGISLATION
2024 THE COPIES HAS BEEN DISTRIBUTED AND SHARE WITH YOU
COLLEAGUES AND I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS MADE A
MOTION. IS THERE A SECOND FOR THE
MOTION FROM SUPERVISOR MELGAR? DOES EVERYBODY HAVE THE
AMENDMENTS THAT ARE PROPOSED? YES.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDEL MAN THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR NAVIGATING THIS MESSY SITUATION AND THANK
YOU FOR YOUR OPENNESS TO ADAPTING MY AMENDMENTS TO YOUR
AMENDMENTS. I REALLY APPRECIATE THE
COLLABORATIVE AND SO I HAVE BEEN YOU KNOW WATCHING THIS
PROCESS FOR MANY, MANY YEARS AND I HAVE TO SAY THAT I AM
REALLY DISAPPOINTED IN THE PROCESS.
I THINK THE OUTCOME IS YOU KNOW ,A RESULT OF MESSINESS, YOU
KNOW, AND I HAVE TO SAY THAT, YOU KNOW, I'M YOUR
REPRESENTATIVE TO THE METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION
COMMISSION ON THAT REGIONAL BOARD.
WE HAVE LONG HELD TO THE PRINCIPLE OF TRANSIT ORIENTED
DEVELOPMENT TRANSIT ORIENTED COMMUNITY EASE AND THAT MEANS
THAT WE MAXIMIZE THE SPACE THAT'S CLOSE TO TRANSIT HUBS TO
BUILD HOUSING SO PEOPLE WILL TAKE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION.
LOW INCOME PEOPLE ARE LESS LIKELY TO OWN CARS AND MORE
LIKELY TO TAKE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION.
SO I AM EAGER TO SEE A PLAN FROM OUR AGENCY THAT HOLD TO
THAT PRINCIPLE THAT HAS A FULL INVENTORY OF THEIR ASSETS
AND MAXIMIZES THEIR ASSETS TOWARDS THAT.
THAT BEING SAID, YOU KNOW THIS BOARD HAS ALSO FOR MANY YEARS
HELD TO THE PRINCIPLE OF PUBLIC LANDS FOR PUBLIC USE.
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS ONE OF THOSE USES BUT IT IS NOT THE
ONLY USE I THINK WHERE THE MESSINESS COMES IN IS THAT
WE'VE SORT OF BLENDED THE LINES ABOUT WHO SHOULD PAY FOR WHAT
AND WHOSE RESPONSIBILITY IS WHAT AND PROMISES WERE MADE TO
THAT COMMUNITY THAT MADE THE COMMUNITY DEEPLY DISAPPOINTED
AFTER THEY PUT IN A LOT OF WORK IN ORGANIZING TOWARD SOMETHING
THAT DID NOT COME ABOUT AND THAT IS DEEPLY
DISAPPOINTING AND THE METROPOLITAN THAT THE EMPTY SAN
FRANCISCO MTA IS NOT THE AGENCY RESPONSIBLE FOR SUBSIDIZING
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. THAT AGENCY IS THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND I THINK THERE'S
BEEN A BLURRING OF THE RESPONSIBILITIES OF THAT
AND COMMITMENTS THAT WERE MADE THAT SHOULDN'T HAVE BEEN MADE
FRANKLY BECAUSE IT MADE EXPECTATIONS OF COMMUNITY WHO
DESPERATELY NEED HOUSING FOR SOMETHING THAT DID NOT COME TO
FRUITION. SO I HOPE THAT GOING FORWARD WE
ARE MORE INTENTIONAL, MORE RESPONSIBLE ABOUT OUR USE OF
RESOURCES AND WHAT IS PROMISED TO THE COMMUNITY AND ABOVE ALL
NOT TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE WORK OF THE COMMUNITY FOR STUFF
THAT DOESN'T COME THROUGH. THANK YOU AGAIN SUPERVISOR CHAN
FOR SHEPHERDING THIS THROUGH THE PROCESS AND FOR COMING OUT
THE OTHER END AND FOR THE LANGUAGE THAT YOU'RE PROPOSING
TODAY WHICH I WILL BE SUPPORTING.
>> THANK YOU. SURPRISED CHEN I THANK YOU BILL
PRESS IN CALI I'M ALSO DEEPLY BELIEVE THAT DEVELOPMENT ON OUR
PUBLIC LANDS MUST BE HELD TO A HIGHER STANDARD AND THIS IS WHY
AS A CITY WE SHOULD BE PRIORITIZING THIS INVESTMENT
IN WAYS THAT MEAN THAT NOT ONLY SERVE OUR PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE
NEEDS BUT ALSO DELIVER OUR AFFORDABLE HOUSING GOALS.
>> NOW I KNOW THAT THIS MODERNIZATION PROJECT IS A LONG
OVERDUE AND I AM VERY MUCH IN SUPPORT OF UPDATING THE
PETROLIA TO BETTER SERVE THE NEEDS OF MUNI EMPLOYEES AND THE
FACILITIES THAT NEED FOR OUR TRANSIT NETWORK.
BUT I AM DEEPLY UP DISAPPOINTED IN THE MASSIVE REDUCTION
IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING SCOPE FOR THIS PROJECT.
THIS IS A TREMENDOUS POLICY FAILURE FOR THE AGENCY AND OUR
CITY. AND I BELIEVE THE AGENCY HAS A
DUTY TO PROBLEM SOLVE AND TO DEVELOP A PLAN B TO MAKE GOOD
ON ITS COMMITMENT. AND THIS IS WHY I ALSO ON TOP
OF THE AMENDMENT I ALSO HAVE INTRODUCED A RESOLUTION
OFFERING ADDITIONAL PATH FORWARD THAT WILL URGE TO
AGENCY TO LEVERAGE OTHER UNDERUTILIZED PUBLIC LANDS
IN ITS PORTFOLIO TO DELIVER THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNIT THAT
WERE ELIMINATED. >> WITH THAT, THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT MILLER.
MILLER FIRST JUST WANT TO THANK ALL THE COMMUNITY THAT WAS
INVOLVED IN THIS PROCESS A LOT OF DAYS AND A LOT OF HOURS TO
EVEN GET TO A POINT WHERE WE GOT AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
IF YOU REMEMBER IN THE BEGINNING THAT WASN'T THE
CONVERSATION AND THIS WAS ALSO PROPERTY THAT AT THE TIME WAS
IN DISTRICT TEN AND YOU KNOW THAT I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING
I CAN POSSIBLY TO MAKE SURE THAT WE HAVE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. >> SO EVEN FROM ONSET TO GET
THE LANGUAGE IN THE RFP TO SAY AT LEAST 50% AFFORDABLE AND UP
TO 100% WAS A BATTLE AND A FIGHT IN ITSELF AND PARTLY
BECAUSE AGAIN MTA IS NOT A DEVELOPER AND THERE'S SOMETHING
THAT THEY HAD TO PRIORITIZE IN TERMS OF MAKING SURE THAT
THE FLEET IS TAKEN CARE OF SO THEY CAN CONTINUE TO GROW
AND PROVIDE QUALITY TRANSIT HERE IN THE CITY.
BUT I DO YOU KNOW, JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THERE ARE TIMES WHEN
YOU GET A WIN BUT EVERYBODY'S NOT SATISFIED AND IT'S NOT THE
DESIRE WIN AND I LOOK AT THIS AS ONE OF THOSE CASES I CAN
REMEMBER IN THE SUPER BOWL WHEN THE NINERS LAST PLAYED
CINCINNATI AND WE WERE DOWN AND BEFORE THE GAME I BET ON A
BLOWOUT AND WE WON 2216 WASN'T THE MOST FUN GAME TO WATCH
IN TO THE END BUT WE CAME OUT VICTORIOUS AND THIS IS KIND OF
SOMETHING LIKE THAT BECAUSE 100% ALL AFFORDABLE IS A WIN TO
ME ANY TIME. AND I DO WANT TO BE CLEAR
BECAUSE I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE PEOPLE DON'T HAVE THE
IMPRESSION OF ALL THOSE 400 PLUS HOUSING WAS GOING TO BE
AFFORDABLE BECAUSE THAT IS NOT THE CASE.
WE LOST SOME MARKET RATE HOUSING.
WE DEFINITELY LOST SOME AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUT IT WAS
NOT GOING TO BE 100% AFFORDABLE LIKE WE HAVE WITH THESE HUNDRED
UNITS. SO I CAN STOMACH THAT.
I'M I'M ACTUALLY OBVIOUSLY WISH IT WAS MORE WE ARE ARBITRARY
GOALS SET BY THE STATE THAT THEY JUST WOKE UP ONE DAY
AND TRIED TO PUT ON US WE HAVE IN MY OPINION AN ARBITRARY OF
ZONING PLAN AND I DON'T KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO BE BUILT FROM
THAT BUT I WILL SAY THAT IN THIS CASE WE HAVE A WIN BUT
MOST CERTAINLY IT'S NOT WHAT EVERYONE DESIRED AND I THINK WE
HAVE TO TAKE THIS WIN AND GET SOME MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
OUT IN OUR COMMUNITY BUT I DEFINITELY WILL SUPPORT THE
AMENDMENTS. I THINK IT IS IT SAYS SOMETHING
ABOUT THE FOCUS ON WHAT WE NEED TO DO AND WHAT WE WANT TO DO ON
NOT ONLY PUBLIC LAND BUT JUST IN THE FUTURE IN TERMS OF
BUILDING SO MAKING THE COMMITMENT TO LOOK AT OTHER
SITES, MAKING A COMMITMENT TO LOOK AT OTHER RESOURCES I THINK
IS SOMETHING THAT IS IN LINE WITH WHAT THE MISSION SHOULD BE
AS A WHOLE. IF WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT
BEING A CITY THAT TRIES TO MEET ARBITRARY GOALS.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MINUTE THANK YOU EVERYONE.
SOMEONE FROM THE MTA WANT TO TALK WITH ME A LITTLE BIT MR.
TRUE. GOOD AFTERNOON MR. PRESIDENT
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD JUDSON TRUE CHIEF OF STAFF
AND DIRECTOR OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS FOR THE S.F. MTA HERE
TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS. WHAT ARE IF YOU COULD AND I
DON'T LOVE DOING COMMITTEE HEARINGS OF FULL BOARD BUT I
THINK WE'RE REDOING THIS COMMITTEE HEARING AT THE FULL
BOARD. SO IF WE'RE DOING THAT I THINK
WE NEED TO TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT THE MTA'S THINKING
IN CHANGING THIS PROJECT AND MY IMPRESSION I MEAN SUPERVISOR
CHAN NOTED THIS HAS BEEN GOING ON FOR A COUPLE OF DECADES
COULD COULD YOU WALK? >> I THINK WE ARE ALL
DISAPPOINTED BY THIS OUTCOME ALTHOUGH I THINK FOR DIFFERENT
REASONS. >> BUT COULD YOU TALK THROUGH
WHAT THE THEORY ON HOUSING OVER THIS BUS YARD WAS WHY WE NEED
TO REDO THE BUS YARD WHERE IT GOT TO IN TERMS OF THE
AFFORDABILITY COMMITMENTS AND WHY YOU ARE NOW MOVING
MOVING AWAY FROM TRYING TO DO HOUSING ON TOP OF A PODIUM.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. TO ASK THEM TO YEAH FOR YOU THE
PRIMARY MY TAKE IT AWAY MY POWERPOINT DECK AND MY TALKING
POINTS I'LL DO MY BEST TO COVER THOSE ITEMS SUCCINCTLY.
>> I THINK THAT THE PERIOD MODERNIZATION PROJECT
REPRESENTS A TREMENDOUS INVESTMENT IN THE FUTURE OF
MUNI SERVICE IN SAN FRANCISCO THE YARD IS MORE THAN 110 YEARS
OLD I THINK IT'S 111 NOW WE WERE SAYING 110 ALL YEAR LAST
YEAR NOW IT'S 111 AND YOU KNOW I THINK THE PRIMARY MODE OF
TRANSPORTATION AT THE TIME WAS, YOU KNOW, A HORSE DRAWN CART OF
SOME SORT. SO THE YARD IS SEISMICALLY
UNSAFE. IT'S NOT A GOOD PLACE FOR OUR
MAINTENANCE STAFF TO MAINTAIN THE VEHICLES AND ABOUT ABOUT A
FIFTH OF OUR A LITTLE MORE THAN A FIFTH OF OUR RIDERSHIP COMES
OUT OF THE POTRERO COMES ON BUSSES COMING OUT OF THE PATROL
YARD NOW SO I THINK AS THE AGENCY LOOKED AT ITS ITS SITES
ONE OF THE OPPORTUNITIES WAS TO START WITH THIS SITE AND BOTH
GET A NEW BUS YARD AND THEN AS A AS THE CONVERSATION DEVELOPED
AS SUPERVISOR WALTON MENTIONED THERE WAS ALSO A THROUGH
ADVOCACY BY HIM AND I'M SURE SUPERVISOR MAXWELL BEFORE HIM
WITH WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN IN THAT OFFICE TO PRODUCE
HOUSING AS PART OF THE PROJECT. SO WITH THAT VISION AS THAT
VISION DEVELOPED THERE ARE TWO ASPECTS OF THE HOUSING.
ONE WAS A TYPICAL INFILL AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
ON THE 17TH AND BRYANT FRONTAGE OF THE PROJECT WHICH WE NOW
ESTIMATE WITH MOST CD COULD GENERATE ABOUT 100 UNITS.
THAT PROJECT IS IN PROCESS NOW AND ALTHOUGH IT IS YOU KNOW
AWAITS THE APPROVAL OF THIS PROJECT AGREEMENT TO TO SORT OF
GO TO THE NEXT STEPS THE OTHER MORE VISIONARY ASPECT OF THE OF
THE PROJECT WAS TO PUT ALLOW FOR A FOUR STORY BUILDING THAT
WOULD THEN BE STRONG ENOUGH FOR HOUSING TO GO ON TOP OF WHAT'S
CALLED THE PODIUM OF THE PROJECT.
>> AND I THINK THAT THAT REALLY CUTS TWO DIFFERENT WAYS.
ON THE ONE HAND YOU CAN SAY AND WE SAID OFTEN AS AN AGENCY
THAT WE WOULD BE AMONG THE FIRST BUS YARDS IN NORTH
AMERICA OR IN THE UNITED STATES TO HAVE HOUSING ABOVE THE BUS
YARD AND SAID THAT IN A VISIONARY POSITIVE WAY.
BUT I THINK IT ALSO ENDED UP ALSO IN THE SITUATION WHERE
WHILE WE WOULD BE THE FIRST TO HAVE HOUSING ABOVE A BUS YARD
AND MAYBE THERE'S A CHALLENGE WITH DOING THAT SO AS A
PROJECTS DESIGN DEVELOPED IT CAME TO THIS BOARD FOR APPROVAL
OF THE ESSENTIALLY A TERM SHEET FOR THE PROJECT AGREEMENT
IN LATE 2024 AND THERE WERE TWO MAIN SCENARIOS ONE WAS TO HAVE
A PODIUM THAT COULD HOLD 365 UNITS AND MULTIPLE PROJECTS
ABOVE THE BUS YARD. THE OTHER WAS IF THAT NEVER
CAME TO FRUITION FOR US TO BE ABLE TO PARK OUR PARATRANSIT
FLEET THERE IT WOULD BE A QUITE AN EXPENSIVE PARKING LOT FOR
OUR PARATRANSIT FLEET BUT THAT WAS A VISION AND THE WAY THE
FINANCING WAS STRUCTURED IS THAT THE MTA WOULD WOULD SORT
OF PAY FOR THE PODIUM UP FRONT AND THEN BE FUNDED FOR THAT
INVESTMENT IN THE PODIUM BY ANY EVENTUAL FUNDING AFFORDABLE,
AFFORDABLE OR WORKFORCE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS AS SUPERVISOR
WALTON SAID AND THIS MIGHT BE A FRIENDLY AMENDMENT TO THE TO
THE LANGUAGE IT WAS WORKFORCE AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING SO ABOUT
THE PROJECT AGREEMENT YOU KNOW THE EARLIER VERSIONS OF IT HAD
HALF OF EACH. SO I WILL ALSO JUST EMPHASIZE
IN THIS YOU KNOW THAT MOST ED DID NOT HAVE THE PODIUM HOUSING
IN THERE IN ITS PIPELINE AND BUT IT DID HAVE THE BRYANT
STREET HOUSING IN THE PIPELINE SO I THINK WHAT WE DID AS AN
AGENCY THERE WAS NO FUNDING FOR THERE WAS NO FUNDING FOR
HOUSING ABOVE THE PODIUM. IT WAS A FUTURE.
IT WAS IT WAS A FUTURE POSSIBILITY.
SO I THINK WE AS AN AGENCY HAVE LEARNED IMPORTANT LESSONS FROM
THIS PROJECT AND WE SHARE THE DISAPPOINTMENT THAT MEMBERS OF
THIS BOARD EXPRESSED TODAY AND IN COMMITTEE.
WE WOULD MUCH RATHER HAVE BROUGHT A PROJECT TO YOU THAT
ENABLED THE HOUSING EVEN IF IT WAS UNLIKELY TO COME TO
FRUITION ANYTIME SOON BECAUSE OF JUST THAT VISION AND HOW
MUCH NEED THERE IS IN THE COMMUNITY.
WE KNOW WE UNDERSTAND THE DISPLACEMENT THAT'S HAPPENED
IN THIS COMMUNITY AND THE NEED FOR HOUSING.
SO I'M GOING TO TRY TO WRAP UP QUICKLY.
SO IN 2025 AFTER THAT APPROVAL AT THE BOARD WE WENT OUT TO THE
CONTRACTOR COMMUNITY WITH OUR DEVELOPMENT PARTNER PETROW
NEIGHBORHOOD COLLECTIVE, WHICH IS LARGELY PLENARY THE COMPANY
PLENARY AND WE SAW IT BASICALLY COSTING FOR THE PROJECT AND WE
HAD ESTIMATED THE PROJECT AT ABOUT 560 MILLION AND THE
ESTIMATED COST CAME BACK ALMOST 30% HIGHER THAN THAT OVER 700
MILLION AND WE WERE FACED WITH THE DECISION AS AN AGENCY NOT
PODIUM OR NO PODIUM BUT REALLY CAN WE AFFORD THIS PROJECT
AND ALLOW IT TO MOVE FORWARD AT ALL GIVEN THE CONSTRAINTS ON
OUR BUDGET WHICH I DON'T THINK I NEED TO TELL ANYONE IN THIS
ROOM ABOUT. THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR
SUPPORT ON THAT FRONT. AND SO WE HAD WE ESSENTIALLY
THEN WENT INTO A VALUE ENGINEERING EXERCISE TO SEE
WHERE WE COULD SAVE MONEY TO MAKE THE PROJECT AFFORDABLE
AND THE BIGGEST CHUNK WAS ABOUT $70 MILLION FOR REMOVING THE
PODIUM. IT'S NOT JUST A STRONGER
BUILDING. IT'S ALSO A DEEPER BASEMENT YOU
KNOW, POTENTIAL FUTURE EGRESS LOBBY SPACES FOR THE HOUSING.
SO THERE'S A LOT OF DESIGN ASPECTS TO THAT AND SO WE DO
REGRET NOT GOING OUT TO THE COMMUNITY AND TALKING TO THIS
BOARD MORE AT THAT TIME ABOUT THE COSTING CHALLENGE OF THE
PROJECT. BUT WE WERE REALLY IN KENT WE
WERE IN AN INTENSE NEGOTIATION WITH OUR PRIVATE PARTNER AND WE
WERE TRYING TO FIGURE OUT WHETHER WE COULD MAKE THE
PROJECT WORK OR NOT. >> SO FAST FORWARD TO LAST FALL
WHEN WE DID COME BACK TO, YOU KNOW, THE COMMUNITY AND MANY
STAKEHOLDERS INCLUDING THIS BOARD AND DESCRIBE THE
SITUATION WHERE WE WERE AND WHERE WE NEEDED TO REMOVE
THE PODIUM TO MAKE THE PROJECT FEASIBLE.
WE BELIEVE AGAIN THAT THIS PROJECT IS A HISTORIC
INVESTMENT IN THE FUTURE OF MUNI AND WE THANK THE MEMBERS
OF THIS BOARD FOR THEIR SUPPORT OF THE ESSER BOND IN JUNE AT
THIS BODY. SO THAT REALLY LEFT US WHERE WE
ARE NOW AND YOU KNOW WHERE FOR FOR ALL THE DISAPPOINTMENT WE
ARE INCREDIBLY EXCITED ABOUT ABOUT THE MUNI FACILITY
AND GETTING GOING ON THAT WE HAVE VACATED THE FACILITY
AND LOOK FORWARD TO STARTING CONSTRUCTION AS SOON AS
POSSIBLE. I THINK I TRIED TO PROVIDE A
QUICK NARRATIVE THERE BUT IF I DIDN'T ANSWERING YOUR QUESTIONS
PRESIDENT ADELMAN OR ANY OF THE OTHER.
>> WELL, I THINK JUST TO SAY AGAIN ONE MORE TIME WHY THIS
PROJECT IS IMPORTANT WITHOUT THE HOUSING THIS PROJECT IS WE
CAN'T RUN MUNI SERVICE WITHOUT MAINTAINING THE VEHICLES AND WE
HAVE TO HAVE MODERN FUNCTIONAL YARDS TO MAINTAIN THE VEHICLES.
POTRERO YARD IS FUNCTIONALLY OBSOLETE AND IT'S IT'S NOT A
GOOD PLACE FOR OUR OUR MAINTENANCE STAFF OR OTHERS TO
WORK AND SO WE NEED A NEW BUS YARD TO RUN MUNI SERVICE
AND MTA HAS BEEN TRYING TO MAKE THIS PROJECT WORK FOR AT LEAST
TEN BUT PROBABLY MORE LIKE 15 OR 20.
>> YEAH WE SAY EIGHT YEARS BUT I THINK THAT THAT'S A PROBABLY
A STARTING POINT THAT DOESN'T TAKE INTO ACCOUNT ALL THE WORK
THAT WENT IN INTO THE EFFORT BEFORE THAT BUT IT'S BEEN A
DEDICATED EFFORT IN MANY OF THE OF THE BOTH AS A MTA STAFF
AND OUR PARTNERS ARE HERE IN THE ARE HERE IN THE ROOM
TODAY BECAUSE THIS IS SUCH AN IMPORTANT MILESTONE FOR THE
PROJECT NOW ADDING 70 MILLION DOLLARS OF COST TO A PROJECT
THAT YOU KNOW MAKES THE EFFORT THERE'S I THINK A LINE THAT IS
WE'RE SAYING AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS NOT AFFORDABLE TO CONSTRUCT.
IT'S AFFORDABLE AFFORDABLE FOR THE PEOPLE WHO WILL LIVE IN IT
BUT IT IS EQUALLY EXPENSIVE TO BUILD THE PODIUM ADDS MAKES
THIS HOUSING INHERENTLY HARDER TO BUILD, MUCH HARDER TO BUILD
AND THE CHOICE TO MAKE TO NOT USE ANY MARKET RATE HOUSING
IN THAT PROJECT WAS NOT THE MTA .
I CAN'T SPEAK SPECIFICALLY TO THOSE CONVERSATIONS.
I WAS AT THE MTA AT THE TIME BUT I THINK IT WAS A
CONVERSATION WITH YOU KNOW, BOTH THE COMMUNITY AND MEMBERS
OF THIS BOARD AND AND THOSE DECISIONS, YOU KNOW, WERE MADE
AND WE WE WENT FORWARD AND IMPLEMENTED THEM AS BEST WE
COULD AND WE WERE CERTAINLY A PART OF THOSE CONVERSATIONS.
>> I DO NOT WANT TO SUGGEST WE WERE NOT AND TO I MEAN IF I
HAVE $70 MILLION TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING, BUILDING A
PODIUM IS MAYBE NOT THE BEST WAY TO USE THAT ESPECIALLY WHEN
I HAVEN'T FIGURED OUT HOW TO PAY FOR THE ACTUAL AFFORDABLE
HOUSING THAT'S GOING TO GET BUILT.
>> BUT WHEN I'VE TALKED ABOUT THIS WITH YOU AND THE DIRECTOR
,THE GAP HERE IF WE WERE TO SLOW THIS DOWN TO TRY TO SAVE
SOME FUTURE FOR HOUSING ON THAT ON THAT PROPERTY IS NOT 70
MILLION RIGHT IT IS MUCH MUCH MORE THAN THAT THAT IS CORRECT.
PRESIDENT EDELMAN AT THIS POINT AND I DO WANT TO FIRST JUST
THINK MEMBERS OF THE BOARD FROM WHAT WE'VE HEARD TODAY THERE'S
NOT YOU KNOW, WE'RE NOT HEARING THAT THAT INTEREST AND IN
STOPPING THE PROJECT AT THIS POINT WE WOULD HAVE TO IF THE
PODIUM WAS GOING TO GO BACK INTO THE PROJECT, WE WOULD HAVE
TO GO BACK MUCH EARLIER IN THE DESIGN PROCESS AND BECAUSE THE
PODIUM DESIGN DID NOT ADVANCE AS FAR AS A DESIGN WITHOUT A
PODIUM AND WE WOULD HAVE TO GO BACK AND DO THAT ENGINEERING
WORK AND WE WOULD ALSO HAVE TO REBID IT.
WE DO ABOUT 60 BIDS FOR THE BOTH THE GENERAL CONTRACTOR
AND ALL THE SUBS WHO ARE PREPARED TO GET GOING ON THE
PROJECT. AND SO I THINK EVERYONE HERE
KNOWS THAT WHENEVER YOU DO BIDS AT ONE POINT IN THE PAST AND IN
THE FUTURE THEY ARE NEVER LESS EXPENSIVE.
SO WE DON'T KNOW EXACTLY WHAT IT WOULD BE BUT WE KNOW IT
WOULD BE SIGNIFICANTLY MORE THAN 70 MILLION AND OUR
PERSPECTIVE IS THAT IT WOULD LARGELY KILL THE PROJECT.
BUT AGAIN WE WANT TO VERY MUCH THANK THIS BODY FOR APPEARING,
YOU KNOW, WILLING TO MOVE FORWARD AND SUPPORTIVE OF THE
LARGER PROJECT DESPITE THE SHARED DISAPPOINTMENT.
>> SO I SEE SUPERVISOR CHERYL ON THE QUEUE THANK YOU PRESENT
GENTLEMEN. >> I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE I
UNDERSTAND THIS CORRECTLY THE $70 MILLION TO BUILD THE THE
THE PODIUM RIGHT THAT JUST MAKES IT POSSIBLE TO CONSIDER
BUILDING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS THAT RIGHT THROUGH THE CHAIR
THROUGH THE PRESIDENT AS SUPERVISOR CHERYL THAT IS
CORRECT. >> SUPERVISOR AND THEN SO THAT
ALMOST STRIKES ME AS LIKE A LAND ACQUISITION COSTS LIKE A
PROXY FOR LAND ACQUISITION COSTS.
IS THAT ABOUT RIGHT? THAT'S FAIR.
IS IT FAIR TO LOOK AT THAT WAY? SO AT $70 MILLION DIVIDED BY
365 POTENTIAL UNITS THAT'S A LAND ACQUISITION COST ABOUT
$191,000 PER UNIT. WHAT WHAT IS MOST KDDI TARGET
FOR THEIR SITE ACQUISITION COSTS ON A PER UNIT BASIS WOULD
MOST KDDI EVER CONSIDER SPENDING THIS MUCH MONEY PER
UNIT ON SITE ACQUISITION THROUGH THE CHAIR TO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL MOST IT IS IS HERE AND I WOULD DEFER TO THEM ON THEIR
THEIR HOW THEY LOOK AT LAND ACQUISITION IF YOU'RE
INTERESTED IN ANSWERING BUT MY MY GENERAL SENSE I'D LOVE TO
UNDERSTAND CAN SOMEONE FROM OCD COME ON UP A GOOD AFTERNOON
ROBERT BACA I'M THE JOINT DEVELOPMENT DIRECTOR AT MOST CD
SO WITH ACQUISITIONS AT 191 PER UNIT IT WOULD MAKE ANY HOUSING
PROJECT EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO FINANCE.
I WOULD HAVE TO GO BACK AND KIND OF LOOK AT OUR
PORTFOLIO. I MEAN MOST OF THE SITES THAT
WE ACQUIRE THROUGH LAND ALLOCATIONS OCCASIONALLY YOU
KNOW WE HAD A MULTI-SITE ACQUISITION KNOW FOR A COUPLE
OF YEARS AGO WHERE WE ACTUALLY FUNDED ACQUISITION OF THE FIVE
SITES SO I COULD GO BACK AND GET DATA FROM THAT.
BUT I'M PRETTY CERTAIN THAT WE HAVE NOT SPENT 181 PER UNIT
JUST FOR LAND COST. >> IS IT SAFE TO SAY THAT
YOU'VE NEVER SPENT ANYTHING CLOSE TO $191,000 PER UNIT
FIRST? I MEAN I WOULD PREFER TO TO
CONFIRM THAT AND GO BACK AND AND RESEARCH THAT BUT IT
WOULD BE VERY HARD TO MAKE A PROJECT VIABLE AT THAT COST.
>> SO FROM IS IT FAIR TO SAY THAT IF THE MTA COULD COME UP
WITH $70 MILLION TO ESSENTIALLY DO A SITE ACQUISITION COST FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, WE MIGHT WANT TO BUY SOMETHING ELSE
THAT'S CHEAPER. >> THERE'S PROBABLY BETTER
VALUE OUT THERE AND JUST AN EVEN IF THERE ARE $70 MILLION
TO BUILD THE PODIUM WE THINK IT WOULD BE VERY DIFFICULT
EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO ACTUALLY FUND KIND OF A TRADITIONAL
LIGHT TECH PROJECT BUT ALSO THE WORKFORCE HOUSING WHICH
SUPERVISOR WALTON HAD MENTIONED IS UNSUBSIDIZED HOUSING.
AND SO WE THINK THAT EVEN WITH THE PODIUM BUILDING, WITH ALL
THE COMPLEXITIES OF THE DESIGN, THE CONSTRUCTION, THE
COORDINATION WITH WITH CONSTRUCTION, WE THINK THAT
WOULD BE EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO BUILD ANY HOUSING UP THERE EVEN
WITH THE PODIUM PAY FOR FROM FROM WHAT I'M HEARING IS THAT
IF WE CAN FIND $70 MILLION WE'RE PROBABLY BETTER OFF
SPENDING IT ON AFFORDABLE HOUSING ELSEWHERE LIKE SPENDING
IT TO BUILD THIS PODIUM MIGHT ACTUALLY REDUCE THE AMOUNT OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING WE CAN BUILD IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I'M NOT SURE I FEEL COMFORTABLE URGING THE MTA TO
COME UP WITH A WAY TO BUILD THIS PODIUM.
I'D BE OKAY. I'D BE OKAY URGING US TO DO THE
FUTURE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS ELSEWHERE BUT YEAH SO I JUST
AND JANE, IF I'M MISUNDERSTANDING I'M OKAY WITH
URGING THEM TO FIND A FIND FUNDING TO DO SOMETHING
ELSEWHERE. I'M NOT SURE I'M COMFORTABLE
URGING THEM TO TO DO IT HERE BECAUSE OF JUST THAT COST
COMPONENT MIGHT REDUCE THE NUMBER OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING
UNITS WE CAN GENERATE OVERALL AND I WANT TO KNOW IF I'M
MISUNDERSTANDING THE PROPOSED AMENDMENT.
I'M HAPPY TO BE EDUCATED ON THAT SURPRISE.
>> MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT. I JUST WANT TO POINT OUT A
COUPLE OF THINGS AND THAT IS THE RESOLUTION THAT WE'RE
VOTING ON IS FOR THE NEW PROJECT THAT THEY HAVE COME UP
WITH 100 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND MODERNIZATION FOR
THE YARD. THAT IS WHAT WENT TO THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE. THAT'S WHAT WE'RE VOTING ON
TODAY. FURTHER, THE AMENDMENTS THAT
OUR COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS PUT IN FRONT OF US WHAT IT
SAYS IS THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS URGES M0 EACH CD
NOT MTA A MORTGAGE CD TO IDENTIFIED FUNDING SOURCES TO
CONSTRUCT THE INFRASTRUCTURE NEEDED TO ENABLE FUTURE HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT OPPORTUNITIES AS PART OF THE POTRERO
MODERNIZATION YARD. >> IT DOESN'T SAY IN THE
MODERNIZATION YARD OR DOES IT SAY THE PODIUM SPECIFICALLY.
SO I THINK IT'S OPEN ENOUGH TO REASSURE THE COMMUNITY THAT
WE'RE TAKING THIS WHOLE PROMISE THAT WAS MADE TO THE COMMUNITY
SERIOUSLY IN THAT WE WILL URGE CD TO ATTEMPT TO DO THIS.
AND SO I DON'T THINK IT PUTS ANY SPECIFIC RESPONSIBILITY ON
THIS PROJECT THAT IT CANNOT SUSTAIN NOR ARE WE DOING
ANYTHING TO, YOU KNOW, ENSURE THAT THEY ARE, YOU KNOW, MONEY
HAVING SPENDING HAVING TO SPEND MONEY ON THIS VERY WELL NEEDED
EMERGENCY PROJECT BECAUSE IT IS A LIFE AND SAFETY ISSUE AT THIS
POINT THAT THEY SHOULDN'T BE DOING.
>> NOT NOR DOES IT NOR DOES IT IMPLY A DELAY IN THE PROJECT AT
ALL EITHER. I'M NOT SURE YOU KNOW WHERE THE
WHERE THAT WAS BECAUSE I DON'T I DON'T SEE A DELAY IN THIS
PROJECT AS THE LANGUAGE IS SUPPOSED.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL THAT ALL
SOUNDS GREAT. >> I THINK I BASICALLY AGREE
WITH EVERYTHING YOU JUST SAID. THE THE WORDING THAT THREW ME
OFF A LITTLE BIT WAS THE THE AND I HAVE TWO DIFFERENT COPIES
OF THINGS. SO AGAIN, FORGIVE ME IF I'M
WRONG HERE THERE IS AN AS PROVIDED IN THE ENTITLEMENT
LEGISLATION SO IF I'M LOOKING AT THE WRONG THING HERE I AM.
>> GREAT. THANK YOU.
EXCELLENT. OKAY.
SO I THINK AS LONG AS FURTHER RESOLVED THIS AS PROVIDED
IN THE ENTITLEMENT LEGISLATION AS LONG AS WE'RE NOT URGING THE
MTA TO BUILD THE PODIUM WHICH I THINK MIGHT RESTRICT THE AMOUNT
OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING WE COULD ACTUALLY BUILD THE CITY OVERALL
AS LONG AS WE ARE MAXIMIZING THE NUMBER OF HOUSING UNITS WE
CAN BUILD IN THE CITY OVERALL AND WE'RE NOT SLOWING DOWN THIS
PROJECT, I'M OKAY BUT I THINK WE NEED TO BE REALLY CAREFUL
THAT WE DON'T ENCOURAGE THE MTA TO SPEND STAFF TIME DOING
SOMETHING THAT IS SIMPLY IMPOSSIBLE WHICH I THINK WOULD
FURTHER MISLEAD THE COMMUNITY WHO DEFINITELY FEELS LET DOWN
HERE AND REASONABLY SO MY I GUESS LAST SOMEWHAT CRANKY
THOUGHT ON THIS SOMETIMES YOU KNOW THIS BOARD ASKS OUR CITY
DEPARTMENTS TO DO IMPOSSIBLE THINGS AND THEY ARE ABLE TO
RISE TO THE OCCASION AND SOMEHOW DELIVER
AND SOMETIMES WE ASK THEM TO DO IMPOSSIBLE THINGS AND WE GET
EXTRAORDINARY DELAY AND MORE AND MORE COSTS FOR PROJECTS.
AND IN MY VIEW THAT IS WHAT HAS HAPPENED HERE AND THAT IS THE
DISAPPOINTMENT THAT I HAVE. >> SO I FOR MY OWN VOTE FOR ME
I AM NOT INCLINED AT THIS POINT TO TELL EITHER OF THESE TWO THE
TWO AGENCIES WHICH I THINK HAVE DONE THEIR VERY, VERY BEST, YOU
KNOW, TO GIVE THEM MORE DIRECTION ON ON THIS PARTICULAR
PROJECT. I THINK THEY NEED TO GET THE
RAIL YARD OR THE BUS YARD DONE AND I THINK WE NEED TO DO
EVERYTHING WE CAN TO FIND FUNDING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING
. BUT I TRUST THAT MOST CD IS
GOING TO BE A STRONG PARTNER IN THAT.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE
AMENDMENT ON THE PROPOSED AMENDMENT ON THE AMENDMENT.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MIDDLEMAN NO
MIDDLEMAN NO SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR ONE HUANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN
VOTING NO AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MR. PRESIDENT THAT WAS
SORRY THAT'S THAT'S THE AMENDMENT THAT WAS ALL RIGHTS
ON THE AMENDED ITEM PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 14 AS AMENDED
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
GENTLEMEN I SUPERVISE FOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR
SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISE HER CHIN CHIN
I SUPERVISE HER CHIN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE TEN EYES AND NOW WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 15 ITEM
15 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE PORT COMMISSION LEASE
NUMBER L 1737 EIGHT WITH DYLAN TOURS A LLC FOR APPROXIMATELY
1500FT2 ON THE GROUND FLOOR OF A TWO STORY BUILDING LOCATED AT
490 JEFFERSON STREET FOR A FIVE YEAR TERM TO COMMENCE ON MAY
1ST 2026 THROUGH APRIL 30TH 2031 FOR AN INITIAL ANNUAL BASE
RENT OF 72,000 WITH 3% ANNUAL INCREASES AND ONE FIVE YEAR
OPTION TO RENEW. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM 16 THIS IS A
MOTION TO ESTABLISH PRIORITY IS FOR THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
BUDGET AND APPROPRIATIONS COMMITTEE AND THE PROCESS TO
GUIDE THE BOARD'S DELIBERATIONS ON THE CITY BUDGET FOR FISCAL
YEAR 2026 THROUGH 27 AND 2027 THROUGH 2028 SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 17
ITEM 17 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ADD THE COMMEMORATIVE STREET
NAME ED DECKER WAY ON OAK STREET BETWEEN VAN NESS AVENUE
AND FRANKLIN STREET IN RECOGNITION OF ED DECKER'S
RETIREMENT FROM THE NEW CONSERVATORY THEATER CENTER
AND IN CELEBRATION OF HIS FOUNDING OF THE ORGANIZATION
FOR FIVE YEARS AGO SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION,
THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 18 ITEM 18 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO REQUIRE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS TO PERFORM
EVALUATIONS AND REPORT PERIODICALLY ON MECHANICAL
STREET SWEEPING OPERATIONS TO INCLUDE SUBMITTAL OF WRITTEN
PERFORMANCE REPORTS TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE
MAYOR TO AMEND THE HEALTH CODE TO REVISE AND CLARIFY OUTDATED
TERMS CONCERNING REFUSE RECEPTACLE REQUIREMENTS AND TO
AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 19 ITEM 19 MOTION TO APPOINT GAIL RENEE PROSPERO
TERM ENDING MARCH 1ST 2027 AND CARLA CUEVAS TERM ENDING
MARCH 1ST 2029 TO THE SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT OVERSIGHT BOARD.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. MADAME CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
COMMITTEE REPORTS. PLEASE CALL ITEMS 20 THROUGH 37
TOGETHER ITEMS 20 THROUGH 37 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
MARCH 23RD. THE CHAIR REQUESTED THAT THE
COMMITTEE SEND THE FOLLOWING ITEMS AS COMMITTEE REPORTS
ITEMS 20 THROUGH 37 ARE 18 RESOLUTIONS CONSIDERED BY THE
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
WHICH INITIATE LANDMARK DESIGNATIONS UNDER ARTICLE TEN
OF THE PLANNING CODE FOR ITEM 24 THE CENTURY CLUB OF
CALIFORNIA LOCATED AT 1355 FRANKLIN STREET FOR ITEM 21 THE
RELIGIOUS SCHOOL FOR THE CONGREGATION EMANU-EL GRAB HORN
PRESS BUILDING LOCATED AT 1335 THROUGH 1337 SUTTER STREET FOR
ITEM 22 THE INVERNESS GARAGE LOCATED AT 1565 BUSH STREET FOR
ITEM 23 THE ALLEN WEAVER DURANT SMITH AUTO SHOWROOM LOCATED AT
1625 VAN NESS AVENUE FOR ITEM 24 THE FIRST CHURCH OF CHRIST
SCIENTISTS LOCATED AT 1700 FRANKLIN STREET FOR ITEM 25 THE
GOLDEN GATE SPIRITUALIST CHURCH LOCATED AT 19 ZERO ONE FRANKLIN
STREET FOR ITEM 26 THE PACIFIC STATES TELEPHONE AND TELEGRAPH
COMPANY FOR THE NATIONAL URBAN LEAGUE LOCATED AT 2015 STEINER
STREET FOR ITEM 27 FOR MR. CUDWORTH HOUSE LOCATED AT 2032
THROUGH 2040 UNION STREET ITEM 28 THE UPPER FILLMORE
STOREFRONTS LOCATED AT 2035 THROUGH 2047 FILLMORE STREET
FOR ITEM 29 FOR THE LINCOLN GRILL LOCATED AT 2049 THROUGH
2051 FILLMORE STREET FOR ITEM 30 THE FIRST A.M.E. ZION CHURCH
LOCATED AT 2155 THROUGH 2159 GOLDEN GATE AVENUE FOR ITEM 31
FOR THE ENTRANCE NATIONAL INSTITUTE LOCATED AT 20 209 VAN
NESS AVENUE FOR ITEM 32 THE PRESIDIO THEATER LOCATED AT
2336 THROUGH 2346 CHESTNUT STREET FOR ITEM 32 A 33 THE
ARTHUR CASTLE HOME LOCATED AT 20 402 STEINER STREET ITEM 34
FOR THE HANNIBAL LODGE NUMBER ONE LOCATED AT 20 804 BUSH
STREET FOR ITEM 35 FOR THE BRIDGE THEATER LOCATED AT 3008
GEARY BOULEVARD FOR ITEM 36 FOR THE VOGUE LOCATED AT 3290
SACRAMENTO STREET AND FOR ITEM 37 FOR MEL'S DINER LOCATED AT
3355 GEARY BOULEVARD AND COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN
TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS IS
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF SENATE BILL 1292
INTRODUCED BY SENATOR RICHARDSON FROM SOUTHERN
CALIFORNIA CURBS SPACE DOWNTOWN IN OUR COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS IS
AT A PREMIUM AND THE DEMAND IS GROWING AS PARCEL DELIVERY FOOD
DELIVERY AND RIDESHARE CONTINUES TO GROW.
HOWEVER, MANAGEMENT OF THIS CURB DEMAND IS SEVERELY
LACKING. >> A STUDY IN LOS ANGELES
SHOWED THAT NEARLY HALF OF ALL LOADING ACTIVITY WAS
NON-COMPLIANT WITH MANY OF THOSE DELIVERIES AND DROP OFFS
HAPPENING AND TRAVEL LANES AND ACROSS CROSSWALKS DOUBLE
PARKING AND ILLEGAL STOPPING CREATES CONGESTED STREETS FOR
DRIVERS, SLOWER TRIPS FOR TRANSIT RIDERS AND UNSAFE
SITUATIONS FOR PEDESTRIANS AND CYCLISTS, PASSENGER
AND COMMERCIAL LOADING ZONES ARE INTENDED TO MAKE SPACE AT
THE CURB FOR DELIVERIES AND DROP OFFS BUT WITHOUT ROUND
THE CLOCK ENFORCEMENT THESE SPACES ARE SUBJECT TO MISUSE BY
ALLOWING THE USE OF MODERN TECHNOLOGY LIKE STATIONARY
CAMERAS AND SENSORS, SB 1292 WILL ENABLE SAN FRANCISCO TO
TACKLE THE ISSUE OF DOUBLE PARKING HEAD ON BY MAKING OUR
CURB POLICIES EFFECTIVE. SB 1292 ALSO ALLOWS FOR
AUTOMATION OF ACCESS FEES TO LOADING ZONES WHICH WOULD ALLOW
FOR COMMERCIAL FLEETS INCLUDING AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE COMPANIES TO
PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE AT HIGH VALUE CURB SPACE.
>> WHAT'S MORE IS THAT THE REVENUE THAT WOULD COME FROM
ENHANCED CURB MANAGEMENT WOULD ALSO HELP KEEP MUNI RUNNING.
>> THIS IS LEGISLATION THAT WILL ALLOW S.F. MTA TO
IMPLEMENT COMMONSENSE POLICIES THAT WILL MAKE OUR STREETS
SAFER, REDUCE CONGESTION AND SUPPORT OUR TRANSIT SYSTEM.
>> I'D LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISORS CHERYL AND DORSEY
FOR BEING AN EARLY CO-SPONSOR OF THIS RESOLUTION AND THE REST
I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MARK MOOD SUPERVISOR GENTLEMAN THANK YOU MADAM
CLERK. >> I GOT A FEW THINGS TODAY.
>> FIRST I AM INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO ALLOW THE SFP C TO
CONNECT NEW ELECTRIC CUSTOMERS MORE EFFICIENTLY IMPROVING THE
PC'S ABILITY TO SERVE ITS CUSTOMERS AND SUPPORT THE
CITY'S ELECTRIFICATION GOALS. UNDER EXISTING LAW THE SFP CAN
CONTRACT WITH DEVELOPERS WHO ARE PARTIES WHO HAD DEVELOPMENT
AGREEMENT WITH THE CITY TO INSTALL ELECTRIC INFRASTRUCTURE
THAT WOULD OTHERWISE FALL ON THE PUC TO BUILD.
THIS ORDINANCE WOULD EXTEND THAT AUTHORITY TO ALLOW THE PUC
TO CONTRACT WITH OTHER CUSTOMERS SIMILARLY INTERESTED
IN DEVELOPING AND USING P SFP ELECTRIC INFRASTRUCTURE
PROVIDING PROVIDE THE COST IS NO GREATER THAN WHAT THE CITY
WOULD OTHERWISE PAY AND FURTHER PROVIDED THAT THESE PARTIES
MEET CITY WORKFORCE AND LABOR STANDARDS.
THIS CHANGE WOULD ALLOW THE PUC TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF POTENTIAL
EFFICIENCIES LOWERING COSTS, SPEEDING CONNECTION
AND IMPROVING SERVICE. IMPORTANTLY THIS LEGISLATION
WOULD MANDATE THAT ANY SUCH ARRANGEMENT BE MEMORIALIZED
IN AN AGREEMENT WITH THE CONTRACTING CUSTOMER THAT AS I
SAID, ENSURES COMPLIANCE WITH THE CITY'S STANDARD
NONDISCRIMINATION LANGUAGE PREVAILING WAGES LOCAL HIGHER
AND FIRST SOURCE HIRING. >> I WANT TO THANK JEREMY SPITZ
AND HIS COLLEAGUES AT THE SFP C FOR THEIR WORK ON THE
LEGISLATION AS WELL AS MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE RONALD DEJOY.
>> I AM ALSO TODAY INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO RAISE THE
THRESHOLD FOR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS APPROVAL OF GRANTS
THAT IS EXCEPT AN EXPENSE FROM $100,000 TO $1 MILLION OR THE
FEDERAL SINGLE AUDIT THRESHOLD WHICHEVER IS HIGHER.
GRANTS REPRESENT BETWEEN 18 AND 23% OF OUR ANNUAL CITY
REVENUES MEANING OUR DEPARTMENTS ARE MANAGING
SIGNIFICANT GRANT PORTFOLIOS. BUT THE CURRENT PROCESS TO GET
THESE GRANTS APPROVED BY THE BOARD EATS UP SUBSTANTIAL STAFF
TIME FOR WHAT ARE ALMOST ALWAYS ROUTINE APPROVALS.
IN 2024 THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT RAISED ITS THRESHOLD FOR GRANTS
SUBJECT TO FEDERAL ORDER FROM $750,000 TO $1 MILLION.
SAN FRANCISCO'S CURRENT $100,000 THRESHOLD FOR BOARD
APPROVAL WAS SET IN 2012 AND HAS NOT BEEN ADJUSTED SINCE
AFTER DEPARTMENTS SUCCESSFULLY COMPETED FOR AN WINSOR GRANT.
STAFF HAS TO PREPARE THE FILE PRESENT THE BUDGET AND FINANCE
COMMITTEE AND OBTAIN APPROVAL FROM THE FULL BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THIS PROCESS WHICH CAN TAKE
WEEKS OR MONTHS REQUIRES SIGNIFICANT STEP STAFF TIME
FROM GRANT MANAGERS, DEPARTMENTAL BUDGET STAFF
AND BOARD STAFF. AND IN PRACTICE THE BOARD
APPROVE THESE THESE RESOLUTIONS ROUTINELY.
THE COMPLEXITY AND TIME LINE OF THIS PROCESS CAN ACTUALLY
DISCOURAGE DEPARTMENTS FROM PURSUING GRANTS THAT WOULD
BENEFIT SAN FRANCISCANS WHEN STAFF RESOURCES ARE LIMITED.
THE ADMINISTRATIVE BURDEN OF BOARD APPROVAL BECOMES A REAL
FACTOR IN DECIDING WHETHER TO APPLY FOR FUNDING.
I WANT TO BE CLEAR ABOUT WHAT THIS LEGISLATION DOES AND DOES
NOT DO. THIS IS NOT ABOUT ELIMINATING
OVERSIGHT. IT'S ABOUT RIGHT SIZING IT
AND ENSURING OUR FINANCIAL CONTROLS REMAIN ROBUST.
WHEN I INTRODUCED THIS DRAFTING REQUEST I ALSO ASKED THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE TO EVALUATE HOW WE COULD MAINTAIN
STRONG FINANCIAL CONTROLS FOR GRANTS THAT FALL BELOW THE
THRESHOLD FOR BOARD REVIEW. I SPECIFICALLY REQUESTED
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR PROTOCOLS AND PROCEDURES THAT WOULD
PRESERVE THE CONTROLLERS IMPORTANT TRACKING AND AUDITING
FUNCTIONS. THE CONTROLLERS RESPONSE
CONFIRMS THAT THIS INCREASES IMPLEMENTABLE CONSISTENT WITH
MAINTAINING STRONG FISCAL CONTROLS.
THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE HAS ALREADY BEGUN TO WORK ON
SOLUTIONS INCLUDING DEVELOPING A CENTRALIZED WORKFLOW SYSTEM
TO TRACK ALL GRANT PACKAGES FROM SUBMISSION THROUGH FINAL
APPROVAL. IMPORTANTLY, DEPARTMENTS WILL
STILL BE REQUIRED TO SUBMIT COMPLETE GRANT PACKAGES TO THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE. THE COMPTROLLER WILL STILL
REVIEW THESE PACKAGES FOR COMPLIANCE WITH GRANT STANDARDS
GRANT TO REGULATIONS AND FEDERAL REQUIREMENTS
AND THE COMPTROLLER WILL SUBMIT AN ANNUAL REPORT OF ANY GRANTS
THAT FELL BELOW THE THRESHOLD FOR BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
APPROVAL. THIS LEGISLATION WOULD PRODUCE
TANGIBLE BENEFITS FOR SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENTS WILL BE
ABLE TO ACCEPT AND BEGIN EXPENDING GRANT FUNDS MORE
QUICKLY ACCELERATING DELIVERY OF SERVICES TO RESIDENTS,
DEPARTMENTAL STAFF, COMPTROLLER STAFF AND CONTROL STAFF WILL
SPEND LESS TIME ON ROUTINE APPROVALS AND CAN FOCUS ON
HIGHER VALUE WORK INCLUDING ENHANCED MONITORING OF LARGER,
MORE COMPLEX GRANTS. BY REDUCING ADMINISTRATIVE
BURDEN WE MAKE IT MORE ATTRACTIVE FOR DEPARTMENTS TO
PURSUE GRANT OPPORTUNITIES THAT BENEFIT OUR RESIDENTS.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR HIS EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP. I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE CITY
COMPTROLLER GREG WAGNER AND HIS STAFF FOR THEIR THOUGHTFUL
ENGAGEMENT AND TIME ON THE LEGISLATION.
I WANT TO THANK SARA CROWLEY AND THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE
AND I WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE MELANIE
MATHISEN ALL FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION.
AND LASTLY, COLLEAGUES STAND CALLING FOR A HEARING TO
DISCUSS THE ON GOING LABOR NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN SEIU UWW
AND VARIOUS AVIATION SERVICE CONTRACTORS AT SAN FRANCISCO
INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT. THE MASTER AGREEMENT AS I THINK
A NUMBER OF YOU KNOW EXPIRED LAST APRIL AND NEGOTIATIONS
HAVE BEEN ONGOING SINCE THEN. WORKERS HAVE NOW BEEN OPERATING
UNDER AN EXPIRED CONTRACT FOR NEARLY A YEAR.
AND ALTHOUGH MULTI EMPLOYER CONTRACTS CAN TAKE TIME IT HAS
BEEN TOO LONG FOR THESE WORKERS.
THE ONGOING NEGOTIATIONS INVOLVE A GROUP OF CONTRACTORS
OPERATING UNDER A MASTER AGREEMENT THAT INCLUDES G2
MENZIES PRIME FLIGHT UNIFY ABM AND COMPASS FLICK.
THESE COMPANIES PROVIDE ESSENTIAL SERVICES TO THE
AIRLINES AND THESE WORKERS CLEAN OUR PLANES, ASSIST
PASSENGERS WITH DISABILITIES, HANDLE BAGGAGE AND KEEP OUR
AIRPORT RUNNING EVERY SINGLE DAY.
THEY ARE ESSENTIAL TO THE SUCCESS OF SFO.
SFO IS AN AIRPORT IN ONE OF IN ONE OF THE WEALTHIEST
REGIONS IN THE WORLD SERVING MILLIONS OF TRAVELERS EACH YEAR
EACH YEAR. AS MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WE REPRESENT CONSTITUENTS WHO TAKE GREAT
PRIDE IN OUR AIRPORT. BUT WE CANNOT TAKE PRIDE IN AN
AIRPORT IN AN AIRPORT WHERE WORKERS DO NOT HAVE THE DIGNITY
AND SECURITY OF A FAIR CONTRACT.
OVER THE PAST YEAR MANY OF US TO VISIT SFO AND SPOKEN
DIRECTLY WITH THESE WORKERS. I'VE MET INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE
WORKING MULTIPLE JOBS JUST TO MAKE ENDS MEET CONTRACTORS,
AIRLINES, AIRPORT LEADERSHIP IN THE UNION SHARE
RESPONSIBILITY FOR ENSURING THESE NEGOTIATIONS MOVE FORWARD
IN GOOD FAITH. SFO HAS LONG BEEN A LEADER
IN SETTING HIGH STANDARDS FOR AIRPORT WORKERS AND I KNOW IT
IS IMPORTANT TO ALL OF US THAT SFO CONTINUE TO LEAD IN THIS
AREA. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING RESOLUTIONS TO
INITIATE 15 NEW HISTORIC LANDMARKS IN DISTRICT THREE
ACROSS CHINATOWN, NORTH BEACH, HILL AND UNION SQUARE.
>> THESE NEW ARTICLE TEN HISTORIC LANDMARK DESIGNATIONS
WILL BRING WELL-DESERVED RECOGNITION AND PROTECTION TO
ICONIC BUILDINGS ACROSS OUR NEIGHBORHOODS INCLUDING THE
CALIFORNIA MASONIC MEMORIAL TEMPLE, RECIBIO CAFE, GREAT
CHINA THEATER AND TRANSAMERICA PYRAMID.
>> THROUGH THESE LANDMARKS WE WILL CELEBRATE HISTORIC LGBT Q
ENTERTAINMENT SPACES IMPORTANT ITALIAN-AMERICAN HERITAGE
SPACES AND ICONIC CHINATOWN BUILDINGS.
EACH DESIGNATION TELLS A STORY OF THE INTEGRITY OF THE
BUILDING AND ARCHITECTURE BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY HOW THE
ACTIVITIES INSIDE THE WALLS SHAPED HELPED HELPED SHAPE THE
SAN FRANCISCO WE KNOW TODAY. AND IF YOU'LL EXCUSE ME, I WANT
TO GIVE A FEW HIGHLIGHTS OF SOME OF THESE BUILDINGS
AND THEIR HISTORY OF OUR 50 AND A FEW TO HIGHLIGHT.
>> FIRST THE CHINESE TELEPHONE EXCHANGE BUILDING ON
WASHINGTON'S STREET IN CHINATOWN.
THE EXCHANGE OPERATED CHINATOWN'S OWN TELEPHONE
SERVICE WHICH BEGAN IN 1887. EMPLOYEES HANDLED MORE THAN
13,000 CALLS A DAY IN ENGLISH AND FIVE CHINESE DIALECTS.
A SAN FRANCISCO EXAMINER ARTICLE FROM 1901 DETAILED THE
SKILL AND MEMORY THE OPERATORS NEEDED TO WORK AT THE EXCHANGE.
THAT ARTICLE QUOTES THE WORK OF THE EXCHANGE WOULD DRIVE AN
AMERICAN OPERATOR INSANE FOR AN ADDITION TO THE 255 NUMBERS ON
THE EXCHANGE. THERE ARE AT LEAST 125
TELEPHONES WHICH ARE EITHER IN CHINESE LODGING HOUSES OR
IN CLUBS. THE OPERATIVES HAVE NEARLY 1500
NAMES TO REMEMBER. TOGETHER WITH THEIR OWNERS
PLACE OF RESIDENCE FOR EXAMPLE WILL KEE BRINGS HIS TELEPHONE
AND SAYS HE WANTS TO TALK TO CHUNG.
HE KIN? HE GIVES NO NUMBER FOR CHUNG
LIVES IN SOME BIG TENEMENT AND HAS NO TELEPHONE NUMBER.
IT IS THE DUTY OF THE TELEPHONE OPERATOR TO REMEMBER ALL OF
THESE NAMES AND IT IS CLAIMED HE DOES SO WITHOUT EFFORT.
NEXT WE HAVE MONAE'S CANDLELIGHT ON BROADWAY
IN NORTH BEACH OPENED IN 1934 WITH A TAGLINE OF WHERE GIRLS
WILL BE BOYS. MONIZ IS CONSIDERED BY MANY TO
BE THE FIRST OPENLY LESBIAN NIGHTCLUB IN THE UNITED STATES.
IT IS JUST STEPS AWAY FROM ANOTHER PROPOSED LANDMARK FOR
NOTE JAZZ CLUB WHICH OPENED IN THE 1920S.
STARTING AS A PROHIBITION ERA SPEAKEASY AND WOULD GO ON TO
BECOME HOME TO SOME OF THE FIRST DRAG PERFORMANCES IN THE
UNITED STATES. INVITING VISITORS WITH
PAMPHLETS READING THE MOST INTERESTING WOMEN ARE NOT WOMEN
AT ALL. NEXT WE HAVE THE MAYBACH
BUILDING ON STOCKTON, NORTH BEACH.
DESIGNED BY THE SAME ARCHITECT WHO BROUGHT US THE PALACE OF
FINE ARTS, THE MAYBACH BUILDING WAS BUILT FOR USE IN 1907 AS
THE NEW HOME OF TELL HYDE NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER.
TELL HIGH IS SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST SETTLEMENT HOUSE A CENTER
THAT HAS ADVANCED EDUCATION, HEALTH CARE AND PROGRESSIVE
CAUSES THROUGH ITS 132 YEAR HISTORY.
WELL, TAKING CARE OF OUR YOUTH AND SENIORS EVERY DAY WE'RE
ALSO PROPOSING TO INCLUDE THE SINGH CHONG BUILDING ON GRAND
AVENUE IN CHINATOWN. >> THE SINGH CHONG BUILDING WAS
ONE OF THE FIRST BUILDINGS TO BE BUILT IN CHINATOWN AFTER THE
1906 EARTHQUAKE. >> ITS COLORFUL, OUTSIZED
DECORATIVE ELEMENTS HIDE A DARKER STORY OF THE
DISCRIMINATION AND CHALLENGES THAT CHINATOWN NAVIGATED
IN REBUILDING DURING A TIME WHEN OUR OWN CITY GOVERNMENT
SANCTIONED A BODY TITLED THE COMMITTEE ON THE LOCATION OF
CHINATOWN TO TRY AND FORCIBLY MOVE CHINATOWN RESIDENTS
AND BUSINESSES TO HUNTERS POINT.
THE SECOND BUILDING WAS A CORNERSTONE IN FIGHTING THIS
REMOVAL INSTEAD INSTEAD REBUILDING CHINATOWN
AND EMBRACED TOURISM AS A PART OF THIS RECOVERY.
>> WELL, SO HAVE THE ITALIAN ATHLETIC CLUB ON STOCKTON
STREET IN NORTH BEACH A BUILDING THAT HAS TRULY BECOME
THE HEARTBEAT OF OUR CITY'S ITALIAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
STEPS AWAY FROM WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK.
IT SERVES AS A MODEL FOR 1930S ART DECO DESIGN IN SAN
FRANCISCO. IN DISTRICT THREE WE'RE SHOWING
THAT WE CAN BOTH CELEBRATE HISTORY AND EMBRACE TODAY'S
PRESSING NEEDS OF MORE HOUSING, BETTER INFRASTRUCTURE
AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT. >> A FEW MONTHS AGO I HELPED
BREAK GROUND ON THE LARGEST HOUSING PROJECT IN DISTRICT
THREE IN OVER 20 YEARS THAT WILL WELCOME FAMILIES FOR THE
NEXT GENERATION. AND TODAY I'M INTRODUCING THESE
15 NEW LANDMARK DESIGNATIONS FOR ICONIC SITES IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. PRESERVATION AND PROGRESS DON'T
NEED TO BE IN CONFLICT AND IN FACT DISTRICT THREE PROVES
EVERY DAY THAT THEY CAN THRIVE ALONGSIDE ONE ANOTHER.
>> I WANT TO THANK MICHELLE ANDREWS IN MY OFFICE FOR HER
LEADERSHIP ON THIS EFFORT AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
DEDICATED TEAM PARTICULARLY SHANNON FERGUSON, ALEX WESTHOFF
AND RICH SUCRE AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR EXCUSE ME SAUDER
SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING AN UPPER FILLMORE ENTERTAINMENT ZONE THIS
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE STRETCHING ALONG FILLMORE BETWEEN SUTTER
TO JACKSON WILL HELP ACTIVATE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS, SUPPORT OUR
RESTAURANTS AND BARS AND PERHAPS MOST IMPORTANTLY BE
READY IN TIME FOR THE FILLMORE JAZZ FESTIVAL THIS UPCOMING
SUMMER. >> THE UPPER FILLMORE CORRIDOR
IS ON THE RISE WITH MANY NEW RESTAURANT ENTREPRENEURS
FILLING VACANCIES, THE IMPENDING RESTORATION OF THE
CLAY AS A NEIGHBORHOOD CORNERSTONE FOR ARTS
AND COMMUNITY AND MORE. I LOOK FORWARD TO THOUGHTFULLY
IMPLEMENTING THIS ENTERTAINMENT ZONE TO BUILD ON THIS MOMENTUM
AND ENHANCE THIS VIBRANT MERCHANT STREET.
I'M VERY GRATEFUL FOR THE PARTNERSHIP WITH THE FILLMORE
MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION ESPECIALLY TIM OMI AND PATTY
MANGAN AND WITH SUPERVISOR MAHMUD WHOSE DISTRICT ALSO
SHARES THIS FILLMORE CORRIDOR AS WELL.
COLLEAGUES, THANK YOU IN THEIR ASSESSMENT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH, MADAM
CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I WANT TO
HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF JOSE THE OASIS GARCIA BORN
IN GUADALAJARA, MEXICO. MR. GARCIA WAS ONE OF 15
CHILDREN AND LEARNED THE VALUE OF HARD WORK EARLY ON AT JUST
11 YEARS OLD WITH THE SIXTH GRADE EDUCATION.
HE LEFT SCHOOL TO HELP SUPPORT HIS FAMILY IN THE LATE 1970S.
HE MADE THE COURAGEOUS DECISION TO COME TO THE UNITED STATES
ALONE IN PURSUIT OF THE AMERICAN DREAM IN SAN
FRANCISCO. HE MET THE LOVE OF HIS LIFE
MARIA DE LA CRUZ GARCIA IN ESL CLASSES AT CITY COLLEGE'S
MISSION CAMPUS TOGETHER WITH VERY LIMITED RESOURCES.
THEY BUILT A LIFE GROUNDED IN LOVE, RESILIENCE
AND DETERMINATION ENDURING EVEN THE HARDSHIP OF RENTING A
CLOSET AS THEIR LIVING SPACE. THROUGH IT ALL, MR. GARCIA
REASSURED HIS WIFE THAT THEIR CIRCUMSTANCES WOULD NOT DEFINE
THEIR FUTURE. HE BUILT HIS LIFE THROUGH HARD
WORK AND SACRIFICE. SPENDING 22 YEARS AS A BAKER
IN SAN RAFAEL BEFORE LATER WORKING AT THE SAINT REGIS
HOTEL WHERE HE WAS KNOWN FOR HIS HUMILITY, GENEROSITY
AND STRONG WORK ETHIC WORK ETHIC.
>> A PROUD NATURALIZED U.S. CITIZEN, HE REMAINED DEDICATED
TO HIS COMMUNITY THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE.
>> IN THE EARLY 1990S, MR. AND MRS. GARCIA PURCHASED A
HOME IN SAN FRANCISCO'S VISITATION VALLEY CREATING
STABILITY AND OPPORTUNITY FOR GENERATIONS.
THEIR DAUGHTERS SOPHIA AND VERONICA BECAME FIRST
GENERATION SAN FRANCISCO NATIVES WHO GRADUATED FROM SAN
FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY AND BUILT MEANINGFUL CAREERS
WHILE THEIR FOUR GRANDDAUGHTERS CONTINUE TO PURSUE THEIR DREAMS
IN ART AND EDUCATION. IN MAY OF 2023, MR. GARCIA WAS
DIAGNOSED WITH STAGE FOUR GASTRIC CANCER.
>> EVEN THEN HE CONTINUED WORKING THROUGH CHEMOTHERAPY
UNTIL RETIRING IN MARCH OF 2024.
GUIDED BY HIS DEEP CATHOLIC FAITH, HE REMAINS STRONG
AND HOPEFUL. ON MARCH 16TH, 2026, JOSE DE
SOUZA GARCIA PASSED AWAY AT HOME SURROUNDED BY LOVE.
AFTER FIGHTING WITH STRENGTH AND DIGNITY UNTIL HIS FINAL
BREATH, HIS LEGACY OF FAITH, SACRIFICE AND LOVE LIVES ON
THROUGH THE FAMILY AND COMMUNITY HE HELPED BUILD.
MAY HE REST IN ETERNAL PEACE. >> REUNITED WITH THE LOVE OF
HIS LIFE. ARREST.
>> SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR WONG.
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO
CONDEMN THE ACTIONS OF THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S
IMMIGRATION AND CUSTOMS ENFORCEMENT AGENTS ICE AT OUR
AIRPORT ON SUNDAY EVENING AND THROUGHOUT.
WE HAVE ALL BY NOW SEEN THE VIOLENT AND AGGRESSIVE ARRESTS
BY ICE OF A WOMAN WHO WAS WITH A YOUNG CHILD AT SFO ALL WHILE
BIASED GENDERS TOOK VIDEO AND REQUESTED TO SEE
IDENTIFICATION. AND YET STILL THEY WERE
IGNORED. I ALSO WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT
WE HOLD MEMBERS OF OUR LINES LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT INCLUDING
SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT ACCOUNTABLE.
WHEN THEY WERE SEEN SURROUNDED THE ICE AGENTS DURING THIS
ACTION PROVIDING A SHIELD AND DID NOT APPEAR TO ASK FOR
PROPER IDENTIFICATION DURING THIS INCIDENT WAS OCCURRING
AND AS A VOTE ONCE AGAIN WE NEED TO ALL UNDERSTAND THAT SAN
FRANCISCO IS A SANCTUARY CITY AND AS SUCH WE DO NOT WE DO NOT
ABSOLUTELY NOT AID OR SUPPORT ANY IMMIGRATION ACTION BY THE
FEDERAL AGENCY IN OUR CITY OR ON OUR CITY PROPERTIES.
AND THANKS TO SUPERVISOR BYLAW MEMO WE NOW ALSO HAVE ICE FREE
ZONES THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO .
SO WE MUST ONCE AGAIN REMIND OUR LAW ENFORCEMENT URGING THEM
TO WRITE TO COMPLY TO OUR SANCTUARY CITY POLICY AND TO
STAND TOGETHER WITH OUR IMMIGRATION COMMUNITY.
LASTLY, WE ARE URGING THE UNITED STATES CONGRESS TO
REJECT ANY FUNDING FOR ICE AND INSTEAD PASS THE FUNDING
FOR THE TRANSPORTATION SECURITY ADMINISTRATION TSA SO THEY CAN
DO THEIR JOBS AND GET ICE OUT OF OUR AIRPORTS.
>> I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR BELAL MEMO JACKIE FELDER,
SHERMAN WALTON AND JANE CHEN FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP
AND COLLEAGUES. I LOOK FORWARD TO HAVING YOUR
SUPPORT AS WELL. AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHAN. SUPERVISOR CHEN WILL SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER
THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT AT THIS TIME.
>> THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE STILL REMAINING IN THE CHAMBER LINE
UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER YOU MAY SPEAK TO
ITEMS 40 THROUGH 46 THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE FOR OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE
AGENDA BUT WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION WE
ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
WE WELCOME OUR FIRST SPEAKER. COME ON UP.
WELCOME. >> QUICK QUESTION IS THE PUBLIC
COMMENT PUBLIC COMMENT OR JUST FOR THOSE ITEMS?
THIS IS GENERAL PUBLIC. OKAY COOL COOL.
THIS WEEK. A TWO YEAR OLD CHILD OVERDOSED
AND DIED ON FENTANYL. SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS IS NOT THE FIRST CHILD WHO'S DIED FROM FINNING ON OUR
CITY AND UNFORTUNATELY IT PROBABLY WON'T BE THE LAST.
WALKING AROUND DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO TODAY I SEE OUTSIDE
OF OUR SCHOOLS AND PLAYGROUNDS A CONFERENCE AREAS OR MAIN
CORRIDORS JUST EVERYWHERE YOU LOOK ARE THE SIGNS OF THE
DECLINE OF WESTERN CIVILIZATION.
PHENOL IS A FORM OF CHEMICAL WARFARE ON THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
COMES FROM CHINA, CROSS THE SOUTHERN BORDER INTO OUR
COMMUNITY BIG CITIES AND SMALL TOWNS.
I LOVE IMMIGRANT ARTS. I BELIEVE THERE'S SOME OF THE
BEST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD. UNFORTUNATELY THERE ARE OFTEN
ART DEALERS HERE IN OUR COMMUNITY TRANSNATIONAL NARCO
TERRORISTS WHO ARE EXPLOITING AND TAKING ADVANTAGE OF OUR
SANCTUARY CITY 5000 PEOPLE OF ALL RACES AND RELIGIONS HAVE
DIED FROM PHENOL IN SAN FRANCISCO BETWEEN THE YEARS
2019 2026 INCLUDING MANY OF MY FAMILY AND FRIENDS.
>> CORRUPT FAR LEFT DEMOCRATS SUCH AS YOURSELVES HAVE ENABLED
CHAOS AND LAWLESSNESS FOR FINANCIAL GAIN VIA FIN OR
THROUGH CORRUPT NONPROFITS. CORRUPT ORGANIZATION ORGANS,
NGOS THAT BENEFIT FROM THE SUFFERING THE LESS FORTUNATE ON
THE STREETS WE ARE ON THE 20TH YEAR ANNIVERSARY OF GAVIN
NEWSOM'S TEN YEAR PLAN TO SOLVE HOMELESSNESS.
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS HAVE BEEN SPENT ONLY FOR THE SITUATION
GET WORSE. MY APARTMENTS HAVE BEEN BROKEN
IN SEVERAL TIMES. I'VE HAD TO FIGHT OFF BURGLARS
WHILE MY GIRL SCREAMING BLOODY MURDER SO NICK SHIRLEY'S COMING
TO TOWN NEXT WEEK AND YOU GUYS WILL ALL BE UNDER THE
MAGNIFYING GLASS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. LET'S RECAP MARCH IN HEADLINES
MARCH 5TH OUSTED DHS CHIEF KNOWN PRAISES LAURIE SAYS HE
WORKS VERY WELL WITH FEDS. HE PROBABLY DOESN'T WANT ME TO
TALK ABOUT IT A LOT. >> WE HAVE GREAT CONVERSATIONS
AND TALK QUITE OFTEN. MARCH SIXTH BAY AREA MOM
AND HER TWO KIDS DEPORTED TO COLOMBIA THREE DAYS AFTER ICE
ARREST IN S.F. SAME FAMILY DEATH CHILD DEATH CALIFORNIA
CHILD DEPORTED WITHOUT HEARING AIDS.
ALSO MARCH 6TH LORI'S BODYGUARDS INJURED DURING
TENDERLOIN SCUFFLE THE MAYOR WAS UNHURT AFTER TWO
SUSPECTS WERE ARRESTED IN THE TENDERLOIN.
ALSO MARCH SIX VIDEO SHOWS MAYOR LURIE SECURITY SHOVED MAN
TO GROUND BEFORE FIGHT MARCH 10TH.
WHAT WAS THE SIN? ASKED REP ERIC SWALWELL
DECRYING THE DEPORTATION OF SIX YEAR OLD JOSEPH RODRIGUEZ AT A
NEWS CONFERENCE OUTSIDE OF HAYWARD CITY HALL MARCH 11TH
S.F. JUDGE RELEASES MAN VIOLENTLY ASSAULTED BY
MAYOR LURIE SECURITY IN STREET FIGHT.
THE JUDGE SAYS MR. PHILLIPS WAS THE ONE WHO WAS ASSAULTED MARCH
16TH S.F. HOMELESS MAN WHO BRAWLED WITH LORI SECURITY
JAILED AGAIN. HE'S BEING ACCUSED OF LIVING ON
THE SIDEWALK BECAUSE HE HAS NO OTHER PLACE TO GO.
MARCH 18TH DEPORTED SIX YEAR OLD DEAF BOY COULD DIE
IN COLOMBIA WITHOUT MEDICAL MEDICAL ATTENTION.
HIS ATTORNEY SAYS MARCH 19TH HE'S REALLY STRUGGLING
ADVOCATES VOICED CONCERN ABOUT DEPORTED SIX YEAR OLD DEAF BOY
MARCH 23RD ICE AGENTS SEEN TERRORIZING WOMAN AND CHILD AT
SFO. >> LET'S GO BACK IN TIME MAY
9TH, 2023 SAN FRANCISCO SUPERVISORS PASSED RESOLUTION
RESOLUTION URGING RELEASE OF VIDEO IN BIANCO BROWN KILLING
IN 2026. >> COULD YOU EVEN IMAGINE
PASSING A RESOLUTION URGING D.A. JENKINS TO DROP THE
CHARGES AGAINST MR. PHILLIPS, A HOMELESS BLACK MAN JUST LIKE
BINGO BROWN OR A RESOLUTION URGING THE RETURN OF LITTLE
JOSEPH AND HIS FAMILY SO JOSEPH DOESN'T DIE AND THE RESOLUTION
URGING THE MAYOR TO ACTUALLY CONDEMN ICE'S VIOLENCE AGAINST
US. >> I CAN'T.
>> NOT IN THIS FASCIST SERVING BOARD AS A WHOLE.
>> IT SHOULDN'T BE CONTROVERSIAL TO WANT TO SAVE A
BROWN DEAF KID'S LIFE AND A HOMELESS BLACK MAN FROM JAIL
AND TO PROTECT US FROM ICE VIOLENCE.
SAN FRANCISCO MARCHED SHOULD BE OUR RED LINE.
DON'T SELL YOUR SOUL FOR THE SAKE OF PEACE AND PARADES
AND PARTIES. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI MY NAME IS RICHARD
JOHNSON AND I'M A CO-FOUNDER OF HIV SAFE.
I WANT TO ADDRESS THE ROLE OF DEVICE SUPERVISOR MAHMUD
AND WHAT NOW IS UNFOLDING ON HAYES STREET SPECIFICALLY THE
EFFORT TO PERMANENTLY CLOSE IT BASED ON WHAT BEGAN AS A COVID
ERA TEMPORARY PROGRAM. RECENT PUBLIC RECORDS SHOW THIS
DID NOT ORIGINATE AS A NEUTRAL AGENCY PROCESS.
IT WAS INITIATED AND DRIVEN FROM THE SUPERVISORS OFFICE
INCLUDING DIRECTING THE USE OF OCTAVIA FUNDS COORDINATE ING
ACROSS AGENCIES AND PLANNING THE STUDY BEFORE THE PUBLIC HAD
ANY AWARENESS OF IT. AT THE SAME TIME THE PUBLIC HAS
BEEN TOLD THIS IS SIMPLY A NEUTRAL PUBLIC LIFE STUDY.
IT IS NOT. AND THAT RAISES A SERIOUS
CONCERN CONCERN ABOUT OVERREACH.
THIS IS A TRANSPORTATION TO DECISION ONE THAT SHOULD SIT
WITH S.F. MTA AND FOLLOW A CLEAR PUBLIC PROCESS.
INSTEAD THAT EFFORT NOW EXTENDS TO THE USE OF TRANSPORTATION
FUNDS ORIGINALLY INTENDED FOR OCTAVIA, IMPROVEMENTS TOWARD A
PLAN TO PERMANENTLY CLOSE A NEIGHBORHOOD BUSINESS CORRIDOR.
THAT SHOULD GIVE EVERYONE PAUSE BECAUSE AT NO POINT WAS THERE
ANY OPEN DISCUSSION ABOUT REOPENING HAYES STREET NOR WAS
THERE ANY MEANINGFUL COMMUNITY LEVEL PROCESS TO ESTABLISH A
MANDATE FOR A PERMANENT CLOSURE.
CALIFORNIA LAW IS CLEAR THAT STREET CLOSURES ARE TIED TO
SAFETY ACCESS AND NECESSITY NOT PREFERENCE.
WHAT IS HAPPENING HERE MOVES IN THE OPPOSITE EXIT.
IT SETS A DANGEROUS PRECEDENT WHERE A SINGLE OFFICE CAN
DIRECT TRANSPORTATION POLICY, REDIRECT OR RESTRICT IT FUNDS
AND RESEARCH, RESHAPE A PUBLIC STREET WITHOUT A CLEAR MANDATE
OR A TRANSFER DECISION. I ENCOURAGE ALL OF YOU TO VISIT
TO VISIT OUR WEBSITE AND FEEL SAFE.
DOT COM. WE HAVE A THOROUGH HISTORY
AND WE DO OUR DUE DILIGENCE OF LOOKING AT THE PROCESS AND TO
HEAR IT IS A PROCESS THAT'S AT FAULT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> JEANETTE POWELL RECORD
PETERSON TODAY IS NOT HERE SO I GUESS I HAVE TO BE THE GADFLY
BUT I REALLY DON'T HAVE MUCH TO SAY TODAY.
>> BUT I WOULD LIKE TO SUGGEST AS A RULES CHANGE THAT SINCE
MONDAYS ARE ALWAYS SEEM TO FALL ON A GOVERNMENT HOLIDAY AND THE
COMMITTEE MEETINGS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CAN'T MEET ON
MONDAYS AND SO THE SUPERVISORS CAN'T REALLY DO BUSINESS ON
TUESDAYS. >> SO THE SUPERVISOR HAS TO
ESSENTIALLY HAVE TWO DAYS OFF THE SECOND DAY PERHAPS THEY
COULD HAVE ALL OF THEIR COMMEMORATIONS AND THEIR THEIR
AWARD MEETING. I MEAN THIS IS TURNING INTO
LIKE THE HOLLYWOOD WALKER AWARDS.
ANYWAY, THAT'S ONLY A SUGGESTION AND I WANTED TO KEEP
OFF TOPIC. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR FINAL NAMES.
WELL WELL DUFFY I LIVE NEARBY. I HAD A COUPLE OF SPEAKERS I
GUESS WE'RE ENGAGING IN A LITTLE BIT OF HYPERBOLE THERE.
ONE OF THEM THAT SAID YOUR BOARD WAS ULTRA FASCIST
AND THEN THE OTHER ONE SAID WAS ULTRA LEFT WING.
WELL, I'M PRETTY SURE YOU'RE NOT ULTRA LEFT WING AND YOU
KNOW, PROBABLY NOT FASCIST EITHER.
>> THEY BOTH MADE GOOD POINTS OUTSIDE OF THE HYPERBOLE PART I
THINK YOU HAVE TO HANG AROUND FOR A WHILE AND SEE HOW THE
CITY WORKS AND YOU START TO FIND OUT THAT IT'S A KIND OF A
COMPLICATED SITUATION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE LET'S GO TO
OUR FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA
PLEASE CALL ITEMS 4346 ITEMS 40 THROUGH 46 WERE INTRODUCED FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TODAY ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE TO REVISE WALTON
CIVIL 43 AND 44 MR. CHAIR OKAY. ANYBODY ELSE?
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE
BALANCE OF THE ITEMS ON ITEMS 4041, 4245 AND 46?
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MIDDLEMAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR ONE HUANG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE CALL ITEM 43 ITEM 43
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE MARCH 2026 AS
ENDOMETRIOSIS AWARENESS MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY SAN
FRANCISCO SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
>> COLLEAGUES THIS RESOLUTION DECLARES MARCH AS ENDOMETRIOSIS
AWARENESS MONTH HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IS PERSONAL TO MY
OFFICE. ENDOMETRIOSIS IS A CHRONIC
INFLAMMATORY CONDITION WITH TISSUES SIMILAR TO THE LINING
OF THE UTERUS GROWS OUTSIDE OF IT THROUGHOUT THE BODY.
IT CAN CAUSE INCAPACITATING PAIN INFERTILITY, ORGAN DAMAGE,
KIDNEY FAILURE, INCREASED RISK OF CARDIOVASCULAR DISEASE
AND CERTAIN CANCERS AND IMMUNE DYSFUNCTION.
>> IT IS NOT JUST BAD OR PAINFUL PERIODS.
IT IS A SYSTEMIC DISEASE THAT CAN AFFECT EVERY PART OF A
PERSON'S LIFE FOR THEIR ENTIRE LIFE WITH NO KNOWN CURE.
IT AFFECTS 1 IN 10 PEOPLE APPROXIMATELY 200 MILLION
WORLDWIDE AND 15 MILLION IN THE UNITED STATES ALONE.
>> IT IS ONE OF THE LEADING CAUSES OF SCHOOL ABSENCES
AND TEENAGERS. BUT DESPITE HOW WIDESPREAD THIS
CONDITION IS, IT RECEIVES A FRACTION OF THE FEDERAL
RESEARCH FUNDING COMPARED TO OTHER DISEASES.
PEOPLE WITHIN THE METROS WAIT AN AVERAGE OF 6 TO 10 YEARS FOR
A DIAGNOSIS AND SOME GO 20 TO 40 YEARS WITHOUT ONE.
>> THEY ARE DISMISSED BY DOCTORS TOLD IT IS JUST PERIOD
PAIN CYCLE THROUGH TREATMENTS THAT DO NOT WORK OR CAUSE THEM
SERIOUS HARM AND LEFT TO NAVIGATE A MEDICAL SYSTEM THAT
WAS NOT BUILT TO TAKE ON THEIR PAIN SERIOUSLY.
THAT IS ESPECIALLY TRUE FOR BLACK WOMEN AND PEOPLE OF COLOR
. BLACK WOMEN ARE ONLY ABOUT HALF
AS LIKELY TO BE DIAGNOSED WITH ENDOMETRIOSIS AS WHITE WOMEN
BECAUSE OF LONG STANDING BIASES IN MEDICINE THAT CONSISTENTLY
THAT CONSISTENTLY UNDERESTIMATE PAIN IN BLACK PATIENTS.
FOR BLACK WOMEN WITH ENDO THE DIAGNOSTIC DELAY IS LONGER THE
DISMISSAL SHARPER AND THE CONSEQUENCES OF DELAY CARE ARE
MORE SEVERE. THIS IS PERSONAL TO MY OFFICE.
AS WE HAVE STATED IN THE PAST, MY ONE OF MY LEGISLATIVE AIDES
NOW LEAGUE HAS LIVED WITH ENDOMETRIOSIS FOR THE MAJORITY
OF HER LIFE. SHE WENT UNDIAGNOSED FOR YEARS
DESPITE REACHING OUT TO MULTIPLE DOCTORS AND ADVOCATING
FOR HERSELF AT EVERY TURN. HER STORY IS NOT AN EXCEPTION.
IT IS EXACTLY WHAT MILLIONS OF PEOPLE EXPERIENCE AND IT IS WHY
AWARENESS AND EDUCATION MATTER SO MUCH.
SHOUT OUT TO CONGRESS WOMAN NIKKI WILLIAMS OF GEORGIA WHO
HAS INTRODUCED H R 6682 THE ENDOMETRIOSIS CARE ACT THAT
WILL EXPAND TREATMENT AND RESOURCE.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. SUPERVISOR MELGAR FILLER CHIN.
>> AMENDMENT FOR YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP.
AND I WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE ANALOGY FOR
BRINGING AWARENESS TO THIS ISSUE.
>> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 44.
ITEM 44 RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE WEEK OF MARCH 29TH THROUGH
APRIL 5TH 2026. AS COMMUNITY BASED DOLLAR WEEK
IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO SILVER AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES TODAY WE ARE
DECLARING MARCH 29TH TO APRIL FIFTH AS COMMUNITY DIALOG WEEK
IN SAN FRANCISCO AS PART OF A NATIONAL EFFORT.
COMMUNITY BASED DOULAS PROVIDE CONTINUOUS CULTURALLY GROUNDED
SUPPORT TO BIRTHING PEOPLE THROUGH ONE OF THE MOST
PHYSICALLY AND EMOTIONALLY DEMANDING EXPERIENCES OF THEIR
LIVES. >> WHAT MAKES COMMUNITY DO THIS
DISTINCT IS THAT THEY SHARE LIVED EXPERIENCE WITH THE
PEOPLE THEY SERVE. THAT COMMONALITY MATTERS.
RESEARCH CONSISTENTLY SHOWS IT IMPROVES OUTCOMES PARTICULARLY
FOR BLACK AND BROWN MOTHERS WHO FACE THE STEEPEST DISPARITIES
IN MATERNAL HEALTH. >> HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THOSE
DISPARITIES ARE REAL. BLACK MOTHERS IN OUR CITY
EXPERIENCE SIGNIFICANTLY HIGHER RATES OF PREGNANCY RELATED
COMPLICATIONS AND MORTALITY THAN OTHER RACE COMMUNITY.
>> THOSE ARE ONE OF THE MOST EFFECTIVE EVIDENCE BASED TOOLS
WE HAVE TO CLOSE THAT GAP BECAUSE THEY WORK ALONGSIDE
DOCTORS, MIDWIVES AND NURSES PROVIDING INFORMATION ON
EMOTIONAL SUPPORT THROUGHOUT LABOR DELIVERY AND THE
TRANSITION TO PARENTHOOD. THEY MEET FAMILIES WHERE THEY
ARE HELP NAVIGATE A SYSTEM THAT WAS NOT ALWAYS BUILT FOR THEM
AND STAY ENGAGED WELL AFTER BIRTH.
AS YOU KNOW, THE MAYOR EARLY CHILDHOOD EDUCATORS DEPARTMENT
OF STATUS OF WOMEN, DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MYSELF HAVE ALL COME TOGETHER TO MAKE THIS A
PRIORITY. THANK YOU TO MY COLLEAGUES
SUPERVISOR MELGAR FIELDER CHAN, CHERYL AND MENDELSOHN FOR YOUR
CO-SPONSORSHIP AND TO SISTER WHIP FOR BRINGING THIS ISSUE TO
OUR OFFICE. >> THANK YOU.
AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
AND MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> I HAVE NONE TO REPORT. >> OKAY.
COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL. ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR THE LATE MR. JOSE DE SOUZA GARCIA.
>> AND I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR END OF OUR
AGENDA, COLLEAGUES. MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY
FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY THAN WE WERE
ADJOURNED